<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><add><doc><field name="id">d1e2</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">header</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 8  </field><field name="fulltext_t">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 8 (The Winter's Tale) [a
     machine-readable transcription] Shakespeare, William Creation of machine-readable version: Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia Creation of digital images: Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. 25 kilobytes University of Virginia Library. Charlottesville, Va. Bibliographic Society, Sha8WTP Publicly-accessible URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/bsuva/promptbook/ 1997 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century The electronic text contains the Introduction and the Collations. The selected pages of
     the Prompt-Book included in this Volume have been rendered as images. Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 8 William Shakespeare Editor G. Blakemore Evans Issued in portfolios. The prompt-books are reproduced in collotype facsimile. Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia Charlottesville, VA 1996 Print copy consulted: First Edition provided by the BSUVA Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century In Memoriam Fredson T. Bowers  Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. All quotation marks retained as data. All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has
     been joined to the preceding line. The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and
     thumbnail GIFs. Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing
     analytical groupings. Library of Congress Subject Headings  1960-1996 English drama; prose LCSH 24-bit color; 400 dpi  July 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Corrected transcriptional errors. May 1997 corrector Michele Ierardi, Electronic Text Center Added TEI header </field><field name="file_s">Sha8WTP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e139</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">front</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 8  </field><field name="fulltext_t">Image of the spine: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, Vol. VIIIImage of the cover, part 1: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, Vol. VIII: Ki! Henry VIII,
       The Merry Wives of Windsor, Twelth Night, The Comedy of Errors, The Winter's TaleImage of the titlepage, part 1: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, Vol. VIII: King Lear,
       Henry VIII, The Merry Wives of Windsor, Twelth Night, The Comedy of Errors, The Winter's Tale
        SHAKESPEAREAN PROMPT-BOOKS of the SEVENTEENTH CENTURY  Vol. VIII King Lear, Henry VIII,The Merry Wives of WindsorTwelfth Night, The Comedy of ErrorsThe Winter's TaleEdited byG. Blakemore Evans A Publication ofThe Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia
      Charlottesville1996 </field><field name="file_s">Sha8WTP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e193</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">introduction</field><field name="title_s"> Smock AlleyThe Winter s Tale Third Folio  Introduction </field><field name="fulltext_t"> Smock AlleyThe Winter s Tale Third Folio  Introduction  THE Smock Alley Winter's Tale prompt-book (PB) is not, strictly considered, a
     prompt-book but a preliminary (and probably incomplete) cutting of the play, similar in this
     respect to the Padua Winter's Tale.[1] The method of cutting
     is noticeably like that in the Smock Alley King Lear PB, where it is associated with
     Hand II, who, as here, cuts by circling lines, phrases, and single words. Aside from the
     various cuts, no other prompt notations occur.   There is no record of any performance of The Winter's Tale during the Restoration,
     and the play was not produced in the eighteenth century until 1741-42 (fourteen performances).
     No further performances are recorded until 1754, at which time and in the years following the
     original play was replaced by three much shortened adaptations dealing primarily with the
     pastoral elements in Acts IV-V: The Sheep-Shearing: Or, Florizel and Perdita (1755),
     by MacNamara Morgan; Florizel and Perdita, A Dramatic Pastoral (1756), by David
     Garrick; The Sheep Shearing (1777), by George Colman. These and a somewhat shortened
     version of the original by Thomas Hull (1771) held  the boards for the remainder of the eighteenth
      century.[2] A second version of the original was produced by John
     Philip Kemble at Drury Lane in 1802.[3] Both Hull's and Kemble's
     acting texts have been compared with the Smock Alley promptbook; also compared are the Padua
      Winter's Tale PB and the so-called Collier MS.   1. See Vol. II: Part i, of this series, pp. 21-29.   2. See C. B. Hogan, Shakespeare in the Theatre, 1701-1800, II (1957),
     674-698. Hogan indicates the principal cuts in Morgan, Garrick, Hull, and Colman, pp. 674-676.
     Hull's acting version was first published in John Bell's Shakespeare's Plays, As they are
      now performed at the Theatres Royal in London, Vol. V, 1773.   3. The edition of Kemble's acting version here used was published in Mrs.
     Inchbald's British Theatre, Vol. III, 1808. </field><field name="file_s">Sha8WTP</field></doc></add>