<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><add><doc><field name="id">d1e2</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">header</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 8  </field><field name="fulltext_t">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 8 (The Comedy of Errors) [a
     machine-readable transcription] Shakespeare, William Creation of machine-readable version: Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia Creation of digital images: Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. 55 kilobytes University of Virginia Library. Charlottesville, Va. Bibliographic Society, Sha8CEP Publicly-accessible URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/bsuva/promptbook/ 1997 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth centuryThe electronic text contains the Introduction and the Collations. The selected pages of
     the Prompt-Book included in this Volume have been rendered as images. Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 8 William Shakespeare Editor G. Blakemore Evans Issued in portfolios. The prompt-books are reproduced in collotype facsimile. Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia Charlottesville, VA 1996 Sha8CEP Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century In Memoriam Fredson T. Bowers  Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. All quotation marks retained as data. All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has
     been joined to the preceding line. The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and
     thumbnail GIFs. Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing
     analytical groupings. Library of Congress Subject Headings  1960-1996 English drama; prose LCSH 24-bit color; 400 dpi  July 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Corrected transcriptional errors. May 1997 corrector Michele Ierardi, Electronic Text Center Added TEI header </field><field name="file_s">Sha8CEP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e139</field><field name="section_s">front</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 8  </field><field name="fulltext_t">Image of the spine: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, Vol. VIIIImage of the cover, part 1: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, Vol. VIII: Ki! Henry VIII,
       The Merry Wives of Windsor, Twelth Night, The Comedy of Errors, The Winter's TaleImage of the titlepage, part 1: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, Vol. VIII: King Lear,
       Henry VIII, The Merry Wives of Windsor, Twelth Night, The Comedy of Errors, The Winter's
       Tale  SHAKESPEAREAN PROMPT-BOOKS  of the SEVENTEENTH CENTURY  Vol. VIII King Lear, Henry VIII,The Merry Wives of WindsorTwelfth Night, The Comedy of ErrorsThe Winter's TaleEdited byG. Blakemore Evans A Publication ofThe Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia
      Charlottesville1996 </field><field name="file_s">Sha8CEP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e193</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="section_s">introduction</field><field name="title_s"> Smock Alley The Comedy of ErrorsThird Folio  Introduction </field><field name="fulltext_t"> Smock Alley The Comedy of ErrorsThird Folio  Introduction  THE Smock Alley Comedy of Errors, like the Smock Alley Midsummer Night's
      Dream and The Winter's Tale, strictly considered, is not a prompt-book. It
     contains no scene settings, actors' names, advance character calls, calls for stage properties
     or sound effects, and act notations.[1] What it offers is a text of
     the play as it appears in the Third Folio (1663/ 64) fairly heavily cut for acting, possibly,
     as R. C. Bald has suggested, to be presented as an afterpiece.[2] If we accept Bald's suggestion, the Errors PB should most probably be dated sometime
     after 1700, since before that date afterpieces were rarely included as part of an evening at
     the theatre.[3] Though considerably cut the Errors PB is
     still somewhat  too long (about 1,215 lines) for the average
      afterpiece,[4] and such external and internal evidence as the
     prompt-book affords, admittedly slender, suggests that it was probably prepared at Smock Alley
     sometime before 1700. It was, we know, part of the same copy of the Third Folio in which the
     seventeenth-century Smock Alley prompt-books were prepared before that volume was finally
     broken up by Halliwell-Phillipps around the middle of the nineteenth century.[5] This common provenience, though suggestive, proves nothing, of course, so far as
     dating is concerned. Internal evidence in the Errors PB depends entirely on an
     analysis of the revising hands responsible for the cutting.  The Errors PB contains one main revising hand (Hand I). Hand I is responsible, I
     believe, for most of the cutting, a few changes in the Folio stage directions, all but possibly
     three of the linking bits of added dialogue, and probably the greater number of the single word
     substitutions. So far as I am able to judge, Hand I occurs nowhere else in the Smock Alley
     prompt-books and so offers no relatively datable link with other Smock Alley prompt-hands. What
     appears to be a second hand (Hand II) is found most clearly in a number of 'stet' notations
     (see I.i.99-109; III.i.86-106; III.ii.33-40; V.i.52-54, 58, 61), notations that are noticeably
     and consistently different from Hand I's 'stet' notations.[6] Besides
     restoring some of Hand I's cuts, Hand II is probably responsible for some of the single word
     substitutions and perhaps for three of the linking tags (see I.i.65-78, 88-95; III.i.108-114).
     Hand II may be the same as Hand II in the Smock Alley Henry VIII (see 'stet' at
     I.iv.37-38; II.ii.97-107; II.iv.38), a hand that also appears in the Smock Alley Lear
     (Hand II) and perhaps as Hand V in the Smock Alley Hamlet.  Whether, however, Hand II's work as a whole, apart from
     the use of 'stet', in Errors and Henry VIII, is indeed by the same hand, it
     is, I think, nearly certain that at least the 'stet' notations, associated above with Hand II
     in both plays, are by the same hand, in themselves representing possibly a third hand common to
     both prompt-books. This 'stet' link, then, between Errors and Henry VIII,
     since the Henry VIII PB can be dated as not later than 1682,[7] suggests (though does not prove) a seventeenth-century provenience for the Smock
     Alley Errors.  Already the shortest of Shakespeare's plays (1,753 lines),[8] the
     Third Folio text of Errors has been cut by about 538 lines (a figure including
     half-lines), leaving a play of about 1,215 lines. The principal cuts (of 10 lines or more) are:
     I.i.65-78; II.i.8-42, 88-111; II.ii.26-40, 65-111, 32-148, 172-182; III.i.87- 97; III.ii.45-58,
     159-169; IV.iii.16-35; V.i.75-84, 92-108, 138-154, 231-253, 397-406. Adriana's role is
     proportionately the most heavily cut, and the character of Balthazar has been omitted, his
     lines, when uncut, being spoken by Angelo. In addition to his omission of Balthazar, Hand I
     makes two other, apparently quite senseless, rearrangements. The first occurs in III.ii, where
     Hand I decides to make Antipholus of Syracuse exit with Luciana at line 70, thus clearing the
      stage.[9] He then begins a new scene and, following line 70, brings
     Dromio of Syracuse and Antipholus of Ephesus on together, these two carrying on the dialogue
     describing Luce the kitchen maid through line 151, at which point, realizing that only
     Antipholus of Syracuse could take part in the following exchange with Dromio of Syracuse, he
     exits Antipholus of Ephesus, after a new two-line speech (only partly legible), and enters
     Antipholus of Syracuse. As a result of this rearrangement, Dromio of Syracuse's farcically
     exaggerated description of Luce loses all point when addressed to Antipholus of Ephesus, who,
     as her master, must already know her. The second alteration is much slighter but equally
     difficult to understand. Near the end of V.i, at line 414, the first two lines of Dromio of
     Syracuse's speech are assigned, again by Hand I, to Dromio of Ephesus, and the third line (416)
     is reassigned to Dromio of Syracuse. So far as I can see, this  redistribution of the dialogue makes nonsense, and I can
     only suppose that here (as in III.ii) Hand I has fallen victim to his own comedy of errors.  The confused nature of Hand I's alterations and the absence of the other stigmata
     characteristic of a prompt-book make it clear, of course, that the Smock Alley Errors
     could never have served as a prompt-book unlike the probably somewhat earlier 'Nursery'
      Errors, which was produced not later than 1677.[10] Had the
     Smock Alley Errors been produced, however, it would probably have been very similar to
     the version that emerged under Hands I and II (with Hand I's unhappy alterations ironed out).
     Together the 'Nursery' PB and the Smock Alley Errors extend our knowledge of the
     acting tradition by nearly a hundred years, the first post-Restoration performance of the play
     of which we possess an acting text being Thomas Hull's adaptation (acted 1762, privately
     printed 1770, revised edition 1793).[11] The cuts and other changes in the Smock Alley Errors PB have been compared
     throughout (see Collations) with: (1) the 'Nursery' Comedy of Errors PB (not later
     than 1677; about 1,375 lines), (2) Thomas Hull's 1793 revised adaptation of The Comedy of
      Errors (about 1,544 lines); (3) The Comedy of Errors (about 1,565 lines), edited
     by Francis Gentleman in Vol. VIII, 1774, of John Bell's Shakespeare's Plays, As they were
      performed at the Theatres Royal in London (Gentleman only suggests cuts but claims no
     authority for them as representing performance at either Drury Lane or Covent Garden); (4)
      The Comedy of Errors in Mrs. Inchbald's British Theatre, Vol. I (1808),
     essentially Hull's adaptation (see Collations); (5) John Philip Kemble's acting text (1815) of
      The Comedy of Errors (essentially the same as Inchbald; see Collations). Occasional
     reference is made to the Douai MS of The Comedy of Errors (l694);[12] the so-called Collier MS; and William Woods' The Twins, or Which Is
      Which (1780; see note 4).   1. The Smock Alley Errors will be referred to by the abbreviation PB. It
     is worth noting, perhaps, that the Smock Alley Midsummer Night's Dream, though only an
     unacted cutting like the Errors PB, includes scene settings (see Vol. VII of this
     series). It is possible, therefore, that the absence of scene settings in Errors
     reflects the revisers' intention to use a single setting for the whole play (see Introduction
     to the Smock Alley Henry VIII PB, p. 19). Capell first introduced a single setting
     ('Ephesus. A publick Place.') and is followed by Gentleman (see below); Hull,
     Inchbald, and Kemble (see below) introduce a number of scene changes, following Pope.  2. "Shakespeare on the Stage in Restoration Dublin," PMLA, 56 (1941) 373.   3. See The London Stage 1660-1800, Part I: 1660-1700 (ed. William Van
     Lennep, 1965), p. cxxxix; Part II: 1700-1729 (ed. E. L. Avery, 1960), pp. cxvi-cxx.   4. The Comedy of Errors was made into an afterpiece, and so described,
     entitled The Twins, or Which Is Which by William Woods and acted at Edinburgh in 1780,
     Woods himself playing the role of Antipholus of Ephesus (the text was published in John Bell's
      British Theatre, Vol. XV, 1780, pp. 1-21). Errors is there cut to under 800
     lines.   5. S. W. Singer, The Text of Shakespeare Vindicated (1853), pp. vi-vii.   6. Hand I's form of 'Stet' (capital 'S', Secretary 'e', both 't's uncrossed, see
     I.i.32-36; II.i.86-l06; IV.i.110-113; IV.iii.83-92; V.i.92-112, 341-345) differs from Hand II's
     form of 'stet' (lower case 's', italic 'e', both 't's crossed) and appears very similar to the
     form used by Hand I in the Smock Alley Henry VIII PB (see II.iv.64-68, 69). Since,
     however, apart from 'Stet', Hand I in Errors is markedly different from Hand I in
      Henry VIII and since there is good reason for believing that 'Stet' is the work of
     the otherwise different Hand I in each play, this particular form of 'Stet' furnishes no link
     between Errors and Henry VIII.   7. See Introduction to the Smock Alley Henry VIII PB, p. 17.   8. My line-count is based on Alfred Hart's total of 1,753 lines for the whole
     play (Review of English Studies, 8 [1932], 21).   9. See F stage directions altered , III.i.69, 70 s.d., 151, 152;
      Textual cuts and textual changes, III.ii.151.   10. See Vol. III: Part i of this series, p. 7.   11. The earliest recorded post-Restoration performance of The Comedy of
      Errors did not take place until 1741 (acting text not extant); two earlier adaptations,
      Every Body Mistaken (1716) and See If You Like It (1734), were never
     published. An account of the principal cuts and additions in Hull's 1770 and 1793 texts may be
     found in C. B. Hogan, Shakespeare in the Theatre, 1701-1800 II (1957), 149 150 (see
     also I [1952], 98-99, for information on earlier eighteenth-century performances).   12. See G. Blakemore Evans, "The Douai Manuscript--Six Shakespeare Transcripts
     (1694-95)," Philological Quarterly, 41 (1962), 158-172. </field><field name="file_s">Sha8CEP</field></doc></add>