<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><add><doc><field name="id">d1e2</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">header</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 3 (The
                            Comedy of Errors and Midsummer Night's Dream)  </field><field name="fulltext_t">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 3 (Comedy of
                    Errors) [a machine-readable transcription] Shakespeare, William Creation of machine-readable version: Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia Library Creation of digital images: Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia Library Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. 80 kilobytes University of Virginia Library. Charlottesville, Va. Bibliographic Society, ShaComP Publicly-accessible URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/bsuva/promptbook/ 1997 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century The electronic text contains the Introduction and the Collations. The
                    prompt-book is rendered as page images taken from volume 3, part 2. Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 3 (The
                            Comedy of Errors and Midsummer Night's Dream) William Shakespeare Editor G. Blakemore Evans Issued in portfolios. The prompt-books are reproduced in collotype
                            facsimile. University Press of Virginia Charlottesville, VA 1964 Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PR 2757 .E9 1960 v.3 pt.
                            1-2 Copy 3 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century Published for the Bibliographical Society of the University of
                            Virginia The production of this volume was supervised by Fredson Bowers  Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. All quotation marks retained as data. All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line. The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs. Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings. Library of Congress Subject Headings  1960-1964 English drama; prose; non-fiction LCSH 24-bit color; 400 dpi  July 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant Corrected various transcriptional errors; corrected an error in the print
                    source: Introduction, note 28: next] text; fixed missing or broken images.
                February 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant Added TEI header </field><field name="file_s">ShaComP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e140</field><field name="section_s">front</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 3 (The
                            Comedy of Errors and Midsummer Night's Dream)  </field><field name="fulltext_t">Image of the spineImage of the cover, volume 3, part iImage of the title page, volume 3, part iImage of the cover, volume 3, part iiImage of the title page, volume 3, part ii  SHAKESPEAREAN  PROMPT-BOOKS of the SEVENTEENTH CENTURY Vol. III: Part i Introductions to the 'Nursery'The Comedy of ErrorsMidsummer Night's Dream CollationsEdited by G. Blakemore EvansPublished for The Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia University
                    Press of Virginia, Charlottesville 1964 EDITORIAL ADVISORY
                    COMMITTEE The Bibliographical Society Of the University Of Virginia
                    ARTHUR F. STOCKER, Chairman FREDSON BOWERS JOHN COOK
                    WYLLIE The production of this volume was supervised by Fredson Bowers
                 ContentsIntroduction to The Comedy of Errors . . . . . . 1 The Comedy of Errors: Collations . . . . . . . . . 13 Introduction to A Midsummer Night's Dream . . . 27 A Midsummer Night's Dream: Collations . . . . . . . 31 </field><field name="file_s">ShaComP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e240</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="section_s">introduction</field><field name="title_s">Introduction The Comedy of Errors First Folio </field><field name="fulltext_t">Introduction The Comedy of Errors First Folio  THIS prompt-book of The Comedy of Errors is, I believe, the only
                    surviving Restoration prompt-book of a Shakespearean play which can be
                    connected, though perhaps only indirectly, with the London theatre.1 The evidence for provenience is unusually full and at
                    the same time teasingly inconclusive. Working from the prompter's calls it is
                    possible to construct the following complete cast for the play: 2  Antipholus of Ephesus: Mr. Biggs  Antipholus of Syracuse: Mr. Disney  Dromio of Ephesus: J. Coish  Dromio of Syracuse: J. Wall  Aegeon: Mr. James  Duke of Ephesus: Wm. Wall  Gaoler: Wm. Wall  Officer: Wm. Wall  Angelo: Mr. Wingfield  Merchant: Tady (or Taddy)  Pinch: Tady (or Taddy)  Adriana: Mrs. Coish  Luciana: Mrs. Cook Lady Abbess: Mrs. Wall  Courtezan: Mrs. Chocke  Two definite points emerge from a study of this cast: it contains the names of no
                    major actors or actresses; 3 and those names (John
                    Coysh, Thomas Disney, Mrs. Sarah Cooke and Mrs. Wall) which can be identified
                    with known theatrical performers in the Restoration are, with the exception of
                    Mrs. Wall, all associated with Thomas Killigrew's King's Company. 4 Reference to Genest and Nicoll shows that Coysh,
                    spelled 'Cash', 5 played one of the roles in Thomas
                    Duffett's Spanish Rogue, produced about March of 1672/3,6 and Genest remarks that "from the names of the
                    performers it seems probable that it came out at a nursery for the King's
                    Company." Of the actors named, however, only two (Cash and Powell) 7 were not established
                     members of the King's Company since at least
                    1669 and the title-page of The Spanish Rogue asserts that the play was
                    performed by "His Majesties Players." Coysh also appeared in Nathaniel Lee's
                        Nero at Drury Lane in May, 1674, and continued to play minor roles
                    with the company down to 1681. Coysh is linked with Mrs. Sarah Cooke in John
                    Leanerd's The Country Innocence, presented about March 1676/7 at Drury
                    Lane, and with Thomas Disney and Mrs. Cooke in Leanerd's Rambling
                        Justice, presented about March 1677/8 also at Drury Lane. He also
                    appeared in William Chamberlayne's Wits Led by the Nose, produced at
                    Drury Lane about July 1677. I have singled out these three last plays because,
                    apart from the fact that Coysh is here associated with Disney and Mrs. Cooke,
                    Genest, as in the case of The Spanish Rogue, links two of them
                        (Rambling Justice and Wits Led) with the Nursery and the
                    other (Country Innocence) with what he calls "the younger part of the
                    Company." The seeming contradiction here has been dealt with by P. H. Gray in a
                    useful article called "Lenten Casts and the Nursery: Evidence for the Dating of
                    Certain Restoration Plays." 8 He argues that a Nursery
                    provenience for these (and other) plays is a mistake arising from a confusion on
                    Genest's part between the "younger part of the Company" and the Nursery (of
                    which Genest mistakenly thought there were two at this period, one for each
                    company); that, in fact, none of these plays was acted at or by the Nursery but
                    at the Theatre Royal 9 by the younger or hireling
                    members, as distinguished from the share-holding members, of the King's Company.
                    Gray bases his argument on the assumption that the actors at the Nursery were
                    all young, inexperienced, apprentice actors. This I think is a questionable
                    assumption. Unfortunately we know almost nothing of the actual personnel of the
                    Nursery, but of neither Joseph Haines nor John Coysh who joined the Nursery
                    ranks around 1667 can it be said that they were exactly inexperienced
                     apprentices. 10 It
                    is possible, I think, that Dryden's well-known lines in Mac Flecknoe
                    have somewhat biased our view of the Nursery and that, indeed, a Nursery company
                    was a widely assorted one, including seasoned actors and every other
                     gradation down to the apprentice. But the
                    objection I have raised does not seriously vitiate Gray's arguments so far as
                    the particular plays which he considers are concerned. Apart from Coysh, Disney, and Mrs. Cooke, the only other player in The Comedy
                        of Errors cast whom I have been able to trace is Mrs. Wall. She appears
                    as a member of the cast in the Smock Alley prompt-book (MS) of John Wilson's
                        Belphegor, the production of which has been dated either about 1677
                    or 1682-83.11 It is also possible that Mrs. Chocke
                    should be identified as the mother of the precocious 'Miss Denny Chock' who, in
                    1696, at the age of six, spoke a smutty epilogue at Drury Lane. The problem in the case of The Comedy of Errors is considerably
                    complicated by the absence of any exact date around which to work. Authorities
                    seem to agree that Coysh, Disney, and Mrs. Cooke were younger members of the
                    King's Company by 1677 (Coysh by 1673), but Coysh at least (and we have no
                    record of either Disney or Sarah Cooke before 1677) was, as we have already
                    observed, at the Nursery in Hatton Garden with Captain Bedford around 1667. It
                    would also seem highly probable that both Disney and Mrs. Cooke were at the
                    Nursery before 1677 Thus the apparent Nursery connection throws some question on
                    a King's Company (Theatre Royal) provenience. Moreover, in no other cast
                    preserved for the Lenten or other vacation performances allowed to the "younger
                    members" of the King's Company (and the same statement may be made for the
                    Duke's Company) are there anything like the number of noncenames. As we have
                    seen, of the twelve individuals named in The Comdy of Errors cast only
                    three appear in the records of the King's Company or, with one exception
                     elsewhere. For this reason alone the Nursery
                    provenience seems more likely than one which supposes such a large number of
                    otherwise totally unknown actors and actresses among even the hireling ranks of
                    the King's Company. A combined performance between three younger members of the King's Company and
                    recruits from the Nursery is, of course, another possibility, either as a Lenten
                    or vacation play at the Theatre Royal, or as a Nursery production "glamourized"
                    by the addition of King's Company actors. But such a supposition seems on the
                    whole unlikely. A third different, though related, provenience remains to be considered. In
                    August, 1672, John Coysh, presumably with allowance from George Jolly, then
                    patentee of the Nursery, led a troupe of players to Norwich. 12 Unfortunately no details of the personnel of the troupe have
                    survived, but in all probability it was composed of members of the regular
                    Nursery Company, for it seems to be generally agreed that Nursery companies
                    (probably under the title of the Duke of Monmouth's Men) toured in the
                    provinces. From 1673-1681 Coysh seems to have been a regular, if minor, member
                    of the King's Company, 13 and does not appear again
                    connected with provincial touring until 1683. Since both Thomas Disney and Sarah
                    Cooke were regular members of the King's Company by 1677,14 the 1672 Norwich tour would give a date when all three might well
                    still be members of the Nursery and willing to undergo provincial touring
                    conditions. It may also be noted that the fourth identifiable name in The
                        Comedy of Errors cast, Mrs. Wall, also fits into a possible 1672
                    Norwich performance.  &lt;/page&gt;   &lt;page n=7&gt;  Setting aside the unlikely possibility of a King's Company provenience for the
                    prompt-book, all the evidence points to a date at least before 1677 and probably
                    earlier than 1673. The absence of Haynes from the cast may possibly indicate a
                    date after 1667. On the evidence so far advanced I have argued, fairly I believe, against a direct
                    King's Company provenience for this prompt-book. But two pieces of evidence must
                    still be considered which further link The Comedy of Errors and this
                    particular prompt-book with Killigrew's company. First, The Comedy of
                        Errors (as well as Midsummer Night's Dream) was among a group
                    of plays assigned to Killigrew in 1667/8. This means that the acting rights in
                    the-play belonged to the King's Company. Since, however, neither the
                        Errors nor the Dream was later produced in the regular
                    repertory of the King's Company, this fact does nothing more than underline the
                    already established contacts with the King's Company and may even be interpreted
                    to support a Nursery provenience. The second point seems at first sight rather
                    more difficult to account for in terms of a Nursery (or Nursery-related)
                    provenience: that is, Hand II in The Comedy of Errors (see below)
                    appears also, I believe, as one of the principal prompt hands in the King's
                    Company prompt-book of Shirley's The Sisters. The date of this
                    production can be placed with certainty between 1668 and 1671. The
                        Sisters was acted by leading members of the King's Company, actors like
                    Beeston, Cartwright, Haines, Mrs. Knepp, and Nell Gwyn appearing in the cast.
                    Montague Summers in his study of The Sisters prompt-book assigns the
                    prompter's marginalia to Charles Booth, who as Downes describes him was
                    'sometime Book-keeper' at the Theatre Royal. 15 The
                    ascription may in part be right, but there seems to be no real evidence to
                    support it. Moreover, there are at least two and probably three different hands
                    at work in the prompt notations,  a
                    complicating fact which Summers does not appear to consider. Exact
                    identification of the hand common to the two prompt-books is not perhaps of
                    immediate significance for the present study, though it might conceivably be
                    suggestive. The important point is the appearance of this hand in a promptbook
                    associated on almost every other count with either the Nursery or a Nursery
                    touring company. It is possible that part of the answer to the difficulty lies
                    in the disastrous fire which almost ruined the King's Company in January of
                    1671/2, destroying part of the theatre, their costumes and scenery. Possibly in
                    the period immediately following that fire Booth, or more likely another
                    prompter formerly associated with Killigrew's men, found work with the Nursery
                    and perhaps (since the dates fit in very neatly) accompanied Coysh's troupe to
                    Norwich later in 1672.16 At this point the argument has been carried as far as our very fragmentary
                    knowledge of the Nursery and provincial companies will allow. The case against
                    considering this promptbook as one belonging to the King's Company proper seems
                    to me strong. To distinguish between the claims of the Nursery and those of a
                    provincial Nursery touring company (most probably at Norwich) is much more
                    difficult and in this instance not of great importance since the actors and the
                    acting version would be essentially the same in both. Two hands may be distinguished in the prompt notations. Hand I, an early type of
                    secretary hand, is responsible for textual changes and cutting and occurs again
                    in the 'Nursery' cutting of Midsummer Night's Dream. Hand II, a fairly
                    consistent Italian hand (with occasional secretary e's) is associated
                    with the calls for the characters (regularly by actor's name) and
                     with stage business. This hand appears also
                    in the King's Company prompt-book of Shirley's The Sisters, where again
                    characters are usually called by actors' names. The prompt-book was prepared in a copy of the First Folio. Unfortunately, at some
                    stage in its history, probably before it was divided from the rest of the volume
                    and bound separately, the last page of the text (sig. I2) was lost. The missing
                    page has been restored from another copy of the First Folio -- with small
                    comfort to us! 17 It is quite possible that this final
                    page contained a license from the Master of the Revels or his deputy, 18 a license which might have settled the whole problem
                    of provenience immediately. The absence of any indications of scene-settings in this prompt-book is unusual
                    for the Restoration, though significantly, perhaps, the same lack of settings is
                    found in the Smock Alley prompt-book of The Comedy of Errors. Their
                    absence in the Smock Alley version may be explained, perhaps, by the fact that
                    the play never seems to have reached production. 19
                    But this explanation will not serve for the 'Nursery' prompt-book. Probably the
                    answer lies in the nature of The Comedy of Errors itself, since the
                    play requires almost nothing in the way of formal settings. Bell's text (1774),
                    for example, edited by Francis Gentleman, gives a single setting for the whole
                    play ('A public Place').20 Where one set
                    served for the whole play no indication of the set used would necessarily appear
                    in the prompt-book. I advance a similar argument to explain the absence of
                    scenes in the Smock Alley Henry VIII prompt-book,
                     but, so far as I know, there is no actual
                    evidence of Restoration practice in such a case. Apart from the absence of scenes, The Comedy of Errors bears the
                    characteristic marks of Restoration prompt-books: 'Act Ready' placed a number of
                    lines before the conclusion of each act (except the last, which, though missing,
                    would not presumably call for the 'Act'); 'Ring' at the end of each act for the
                    inter-act music; and points of entry marked with the usual diagonal crossed
                    line. The prompter's habit of using actors' names instead of the usual character
                    names in his calls has already been noticed. He also at times, most often at the
                    beginning of an act where no advance calls had been entered, writes in the
                    actor's name above or below the character name in the Folio stage direction.
                    This characteristic appears in various other Restoration prompt-books, but only
                    very sporadically within any single prompt-book. 21 A total of 378 lines has been cut by the reviser (probably Hand 1).22 This leaves a play of approximately 1,375 lines.
                        23 The cutting here is somewhat lighter than that
                    in the Smock Alley version, where the play is reduced to around 1,208 lines. In
                    discussing the Smock Alley version, Professor Bald suggests that it was being
                    prepared as an after-piece. This is possible, but the difference in length
                    between these and the later eighteenth-century acting versions which were not
                    played as after-pieces is so comparatively slight that it does not seem very
                    likely. 24 On the whole the cutting in the 'Nursery'
                    version is aimed at reducing the number of lines in the long speeches,
                    particularly that of Aegeon in I.i. The parts of Adriana and Luciana have also
                     been quite heavily cut throughout, as also
                    that of the Abbess in the last scene. Apart from these the only major cut comes
                    in II.ii.67-110 -- a passage of tiresome nonsense between Antipholus and Dromio
                    of Syracuse. The character of Luce has been either intentionally dropped or
                    confused with that of Luciana; at any rate Luce's lines in III.i are spoken by
                    Mrs. Cooke who plays the role of Luciana. An important aspect of this prompt-book, and one which helps to explain the
                    amount of cutting, is the number of songs and dances which both Hand I and Hand
                    II have inserted throughout, usually at the beginning of a new scene. Three
                    songs are called for and three dances (including 'Wingfields Jigg'). No
                    indication of added songs or dances appears in the Smock Alley prompt-book.
                        25 The earliest recorded post-Restoration performance of The Comedy of
                        Errors did not take place until 1741.26 Two
                    earlier adaptations, Every Body Mistaken (1716) and See If You Like
                        It (1734), were never published and are presumably lost. The earliest
                    acting version, as altered by Thomas Hull, was privately printed in 1770.27 In 1774 Francis Gentleman, in Bell's
                        Shakespeare (Vol VIII), produced a text in which he suggested a
                    number of cuts; he makes no claim, however, to 'regulation' from the official
                    prompt-book, although it is possible that this version may owe something to the
                    1741 revival. 28 The complete collation of the 'Nursery' prompt-book
                     which follows has been compared throughout
                    with the cuts and readings found in (1) the Smock Alley prompt-book, of
                    uncertain date but almost certainly before 1700; (2) Thomas Hull's version
                    (revised edition, 1793); and (3) Francis Gentleman's text, in Bell's
                        Shakespeare (Vol. VIII, 1774). Occasional reference is also made to
                    the version of Hull's text in Inchbald's British Theatre (Vol. I,
                    1808), and the cuts in the Collier-Perkins Second Folio (1632) have likewise
                    been compared. 29  &lt;/page&gt;   &lt;page&gt;  1. The associated Midsummer Night's Dream (see p. 27) is not
                    strictly a prompt-book, only a bare cutting. Both these theatre versions were
                    presented to the University of Edinburgh Library by Halliwell-Phillipps. They
                    are here used by the kind permission of the late Dr. L. W. Sharp, Librarian of
                    the University of Edinburgh Library. The only printed reference to these
                    versions I have encountered appears in Alexander Cargill's Shakespeare the
                        Player (1916), Appendix D. 2. The character of Luce has been dropped; see the Collations
                    III.i.47. 3. Mrs. Cooke (Sarah Cooke) makes the nearest approach. 4. The appearance of a 'Mr. James' in the cast raises, of course, the
                    problem of a possible relationship with the Mrs. James who was a regular member
                    of the King's Company from, at least, June of 1669. The problem is further
                    complicated by the slight uncertainty of the reading 'Mr; it
                    is barely possible that we should read Mrs.' (see the PB,
                    sig. I1r, p. 97). Apart from the difficulty posed by Mrs.
                    James' early association with the King's Company (see later discussion below),
                    the fact that the James who figures in The Comedy of Errors plays the
                    role of Aegeon makes it most unlikely that Mrs. James could be involved, though
                    admittedly not impossible (scarcely, however, a breeches role!) . Mr. James was
                    perhaps the husband of the King's Company actress, though it may be noted that
                    Montague Summers (The Restoration Theatre, 1934, p. 334) claims that
                    "About 1677 she was by force of Love Erept the Stage." I do not know his
                    authority (he is using Downes' well known words in Roscius Anglicanus
                    (1708), where, however, they are applied to three actresses of the Duke's
                    Company), but it is true that Mrs. James disappears from the casts of the King's
                    Company about 1677. 5. The usual spelling is 'Coysh,' but PB spells it 'Coish' and the
                    spellings 'Costa' and 'Cash' also appear (the last independently of the
                        Spanish Rogue cast). He is called 'strowling Coish' in the
                    scurrilous 'Satyr on the Players' (see Roscius Anglicanus, ed. Montague
                    Summers, n.d., p. 55). 6. John Genest, Some Account of the English Stage from the
                        Restoration in 1660 to 1830 (1832), I, 162; Allardyce Nicoll, A
                        History of English Drama, 1660-1900 (1952), I, 407 7. The Powell here associated with Coysh seems to be Martin Powell. He
                    was certainly a member of the King's Company by 1677. In 1668/9 he was busy
                    petitioning against Joseph Haynes (this constitutes a link with Bedford's
                    Nursery group which Haynes had presumably just left) and he and Coysh were in
                    turn petitioned against in 1675/6 (see Nicoll, I, 320). Martin Powell is: also
                    identified as the 'Poel' who acted with Coysh in a production of The Indian
                        Emperour described as 'Acted by the Duchess of Portsmouth Servants'
                    (see Downes' Roscius Anglicanus, ed. Montague Summers, n.d., p. 288)
                    . 8. PMLA (1938), LIII, 781-794. 9. We may note that both of Leanerd's plays are described on the
                    titlepage as being "Acted at the Theatre Royal." 10. Sybil Rosenfeld, Strolling Players and Drama in the
                        Provinces, 1660-1765 (1939), p. 38: About 1667 he [Coysh] had induced
                    Joseph Haines to join his company at Cambridge and, after visiting many towns,
                    both actors joined Edward Bedford at the newly opened Nursery in Hatton Garden."
                    I wish it were possible to be more certain of this date. Haynes' biography is a
                    mass of conflicting statements. I suspect that Miss Rosenfeld bases the place of
                    meeting with Coysh on the statement in Tobyas Thomas' The Life of the Late
                        Famous Comedian, Jo. Hayns (1701), pp. 4-5, which recounts how, after
                    Haynes had taken his M.A. at Cambridge, he met 'Costa' and at Cosh's invitation
                    he "Metamorphoses his Cap and Gown to a Plum of Feathers, and a Persian
                    Robe; . . . After he had strowled thus about some Parts of the Country, he comes
                    to London; a timely arrival to Cap. Bedford, who at present was looking
                    for such sparks, as raising a Company of Actors, Cosh and
                        Haynes list themselves under the Captain, become his Principal Men,
                    whilst the Play House in Hatton Garden lasted, which this Captain
                        Bedford Built. But as everything has its Period in little time,
                    arrives the dissolution of this House, Haynes betakes himself to the
                    King's Play House in Drury-Lane, is entertain'd, at which time the Rehearsal
                    writ by his Grace the Duke of Buckingham, was to be Acted; . . ." Actually, of
                    course, Haynes went to Oxford, not Cambridge, where he entered Queen's College
                    and matriculated 3 May, 1659, although there is no record that he received any
                    degree (see Alumni Oxonienses, ed. Joseph Foster, 1891, II, 681; Wood
                    mistakenly [Athenae Oxonienses] gives the date as 1689). According to
                    Chetwood (The British Theatre, 1750, pp. 119-120), when Haynes was at
                    Queen's he came to the notice of Sir Joseph Williamson, who, when he became
                    Secretary of State, made Haynes his Latin Secretary. Haynes, however, could not
                    keep state secrets and Sir Joseph had to discharge him, giving him letters to
                    the "Heads of the University of Cambridge, where he was willingly
                    received; but a Company of Players coming to Stourbridge Fair, near
                    that place, Joe fell so much in Love with their Employment and Way of Living,
                    that he threw away his Cap and Band, and made one of their Company. He was soon
                    called to the King's Company in Drury-Lane . . . " (Baker,
                        Biographia Dramatica, 1812, Vol. I, Pt. I, 308, simply repeats
                    Chetwood's account). The connection with Sir Joseph Williamson is suggestive,
                    since Williamson was also a Queen's College man and (so the D.N.B.
                    tells us) a great friend to Queen's College men. Williamson, however, did not
                    become Secretary of State until 1674, long after Haynes was well launched on his
                    erratic dramatic career. It is possible, however, that Haynes became associated
                    with him in 1662 when Williamson became secretary to Sir Edward Nicholas.
                    Unfortunately, the Cambridge incident, as told by Chetwood, sounds rather like
                    an attempt to bring the story as told by Thomas into line with Haynes' Oxford
                    education. We do know, however, that the Nursery in Hatton Garden was built
                    probably during 1667 (Nicoll, I, 312) and that Haynes had joined the King's
                    Company by March 1667/8 (see Pepys' Diary, ed. H. B. Wheatley, 1896,
                    VII, 354-55). Since the schedule here outlined is pretty close, I would suggest
                    that perhaps 1666 would be a better date for the meeting of Coysh and
                    Haynes. 11. See W. S. Clark, The Early Irish Stage, 1955, p. 81, and
                    Allan Stevenson, "The Case of the Decapitated Cast," SQ (1955), VI, 292-293.
                    Stevenson admits the possibility of the earlier date, but suggests 1682-83 as an
                    equally good possibility. In the absence of other evidence for the existence of
                    a Mrs. Wall, Stevenson suggests that "Wall" in the Belphegor cast may
                    be an abbreviated form for "Walmesley," a known Smock Alley actress; such a
                    supposition is no longer necessary. 12. See, especially, Rosenfeld, pp. 3841. She also notes (pp. 38-39)
                    that the following year (1673) John Perrin, who had succeeded Edward Bedford as
                    manager of the Nursery, came to Norwich as manager of the Duke of Monmouth's
                    Men. 13. See Nicoll, I, 314; and Rosenfeld, pp. 40-41. I give the earlier
                    date as 1673 on the strength of Coysh's appearance in Duffett's Spanish
                        Rogue, about March 1672/3. 14. Disney seems to disappear with the union of the two companies in
                    168: (his last appearance being in the King's Company Unhappy
                    Favourite, 1682 [Genest, I, 330]), but Mrs. Cooke became a member of the
                    newly formed united Company. 15. See Montague Summers, "A Restoration Prompt-Book," Essays in
                        Peto, n.d., pp. 103-110. Summers is able to limit the dates through the
                    cast of actors. He repeats the statement about Charles Booth in The
                        Restoration Stage (1934), p. 142, but without any further supporting
                    evidence. 16. Against this, particularly if Booth is the person concerned, is
                    the fact that the King's Company seems to have been functioning again in late
                    February of 1672 at Lincoln's Inn Fields (see Leslie Hotson, The
                        Commonwealth and Restoration Stage, [1928], p. 254) . The fact that the
                    characters are called for their entries by the actor's name makes it impossible
                    to consider the suggestion that the prompt-book was first prepared by Booth and
                    then turned over to the Nursery for performance. The prompter, whoever he was,
                    was intimately connected with this specific performance of the play. 17. Sig. 12 has not been reproduced in the facsimile. The same kind
                    of restoration appears in the 'Nursey' cutting of
                        Midsummer Night's Dream, the last three leaves (plus one earlier)
                    having been replaced by leaves from another copy of the First Folio. 18. Such as those found in the promptbooks for the Duke's Company
                    revivals of Cartwright's Lady-Errant and The Ordinary (see the
                    reproduction of Herbert's license for The Ordinary in The Plays and
                        Poems of William Cartwright, ed. G. Blakemore Evans, 1951, p.
                    260.) 19. See the introduction to the Smock Alley prompt-book in a later
                    volume. 20. Thomas Hull's text (1793), see below, does suggest a number of
                    changes of setting, as do the edited texts from Pope on. 21. It is not found in the King's Company prompt-book of The
                        Sisters, in which I have identified the main prompt-hand with Hand II.
                    The prompter in The Sisters also very occasionally calls the characters
                    (minor ones) by character name. 22. This figure does not allow for whatever cutting may have been
                    done after V.i.282; probably not very much. 23. Based on Alfred Hart's total of 1,753 lines (see RES
                    [1932], VIII, 21). The figure for the Smock Alley version is based on this same
                    count. 24. R. C. Bald, PMLA (1941), LVI, 373. The Bell-Gentleman
                    text (1774) contains about 1,565 lines; the Hull text about 1,544 lines. 25. Hull's version (1793 ea.) adds a song in III.ii. An anonymous
                    version, printed in 1819, uses The Comedy of Errors as a frame for
                    introducting a large number of Shakespeare's lyrics from other plays. 26. See C. B. Hogan, Shakespeare in the Theatre, 1701-1800,
                    I (1952), 99. 27. Hogan, II (1957), 149-150. Hogan offers an account of Hull's
                    principal cuts and revisions for both the edition of 1770 and the revised
                    edition of 1793. 28. The MS copy of 'The Famous Comedy of Errors Written by the
                    renowned poet Mr. William Shakespear' which appears in the Douai MS (fols.
                    66-93), dated '1694', although it presents an edited text (based eventually on
                    the Second Folio), shows no points of agreement in readings or cuts with the
                    'Nursery' prompt-book. For a discussion and collation of the Douai MS, see my
                    article "The Douai Manuscript--Six Shakespearean Transcripts (1694-95)," in
                        Studies in English Drama Presented to Baldwin Maxwell (1962), pp.
                    158-172. 29. After my Introduction was in page proof, I received information
                    through the kindness of Miss Sandra A. Burner and Miss Lucyle Hook of a
                    promptbook, now in the Folger Shakespeare Library, of Thomas Heywood's The
                        Wise Woman of Hogsdon that contains a cast identical to that in the
                    'Nursery' Comedy of Errors, but with the addition of a thirteenth actor
                    (Mr. Kew). Certain of my remarks about the uniqueness of five or six of the
                    names in The Comedy of Errors list are, therefore, no longer
                    accurate.</field><field name="file_s">ShaComP</field></doc></add>