<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><add><doc><field name="id">d1e2</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">header</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 4 (Smock
                            Alley Hamlet)  </field><field name="fulltext_t">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 4 (Smock Alley
                    Hamlet) [a machine-readable transcription] Shakespeare, William Creation of machine-readable version: Lorrie Chisholm, Electronic Text Center Creation of digital images: Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. 150 kilobytes University of Virginia Library. Charlottesville, Va. Bibliographic Society, ShaHamP Publicly-accessible URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/bsuva/promptbook/ 1996 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century. The electronic text contains the Introduction and the Collations. The
                    prompt-book is rendered as page images. Images of the manuscript have been included from volume 4, part 2. Act V, scene ii, lines 201-203 have erroneously been referred to as lines
                    101-103 on page 46 of the Collations. The electronic text contains both the
                    original and the corrected reference.Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 4 (Smock
                            Alley Hamlet) Editor G. Blakemore Evans Issued in portfolios. The prompt-books are reproduced in collotype
                            facsimile. University Press of Virginia Charlottesville, VA 1966 Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PR 2757 .E9 1960 v.4
                        Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century Published for the Bibliographical Society of the University of
                            Virginia The production of this volume was supervised by Fredson Bowers.
                         Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. All quotation marks retained as data. All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line. The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs. Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings. Library of Congress Subject Headings  1960-1966 English drama; prose; non-fiction LCSH 24-bit color; 400 dpi  July 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Corrected various transcriptional errors; fixed missing or broken images.
                January 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Added TEI header and tags. Corrected the following errors: p.6: At I.i. 78 th
                    ] the; p.10: [(4) Word B] Ward B; p. 33: III.ii] III.iii </field><field name="file_s">ShaHamP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e142</field><field name="section_s">front</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 4 (Smock
                            Alley Hamlet)  </field><field name="fulltext_t">Image of the spine: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, Smock Alley
                            HamletImage of the cover, part 1: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, Smock Alley
                            Hamlet Introduction and CollationsImage of the titlepage, part 1: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, Smock
                            Alley Hamlet Introduction and CollationsImage of the cover, part 2: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, Smock Alley
                            Hamlet TextImage of the titlepage, part 2: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, Smock
                            Alley Hamlet Text  SHAKESPEAREAN  PROMPT-BOOKS of the SEVENTEENTH CENTURY  Vol. IV: Part i Introduction to the Smock AlleyHamlet Collations Edited by G. Blakemore Evans Published for The Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia University
                    Press of Virginia, Charlottesville 1966 EDITORIAL ADVISORY
                    COMMITTEE The Bibliographical Society Of the University Of Virginia
                    ARTHUR F. STOCKER, Chairman FREDSON BOWERS JOHN COOK
                    WYLLIE The production of this volume was supervised by Fredson Bowers
                 ContentsIntroduction to The Smock Alley Hamlet . . . . . . 1 Collations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 11 </field><field name="file_s">ShaHamP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e225</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="section_s">introduction</field><field name="title_s">Introduction Smock Alley Hamlet Third Folio</field><field name="fulltext_t">Introduction Smock Alley Hamlet Third Folio THE apparent connection, somewhat confused though that connection may seem to be,
                    of the Smock Alley Hamlet (preserved in the University of Edinburgh
                    Library) with one of the two 1676 actors' quartos, 1
                    would appear to afford a date before which the prompt-book cannot have been
                    prepared. There is, of course, the slight possibility that this connection may
                    be explained through something like a common source, for example, the
                    prompt-book in use at the Duke of York's Theatre. But as we shall see the weight
                    of the evidence is against such a possibility, though influence from the London
                    productions may, I believe, be postulated apart from the direct contribution of
                    the actors' quartos. Other evidence for dating may be found in the names
                    Trefusis and Williams (see IV.v.96; IV.vii.35; V.ii.172). Joseph Trefusis acted
                    at the Smock Alley Theatre from about 1675 to 1688; David Williams left Smock
                    Alley in 1679. 2 Prompt hands found elsewhere in the
                    Smock Alley promptbooks (in Lear, Macbeth, Othello, Henry VIII, Merry Wives,
                        Twelfth Night, and the Julius Caesar cast) can be identified
                    in this prompt-book and serve to link it closely with these plays, several of
                    which can be dated between 1674 and 1682. We may,
                     therefore, with some assurance place
                        Hamlet within a period most probably not earlier than 1676 and not
                    later than 1679. Such a date makes the Smock Alley Hamlet by more than
                    seventy years the earliest prompt-book of Hamlet now extant. 3 I have, with some trepidation, distinguished nine
                    separate hands among the various revisions and prompt-notations. Hand I (the
                    same as Hand I in Macbeth, Lear, and Twelfth Night) writes in
                    the stage setting called for at the beginning of a new scene; and the same hand
                    is also probably responsible for the anticipatory 'scean' calls which precede
                    each scene change (see, for example, I.i. opening s.d. and 164). Hand II (the
                    same as Hand II in Macbeth, Othello, and IHenry IV and Hand I in Henry VIII) is responsible for most of
                    the entry calls for characters and for most of the textual changes and
                    deletions; it is thus the most important hand in the promptbook (see, for
                    example, I.i.1, 72-80). Hand III (the same as Hand IV in Macbeth, Hand
                    VI in Othello, Hand I in Merry Wives, the hand in the
                        Julius Caesar acting list, and the main prompt hand in Wilson's
                        Belphegor) furnishes a few speech-prefixes and prompt-notes for
                    sound effects (see I.ii.17-41; I.iii.90-92; V.i.307). Hand IV is a
                    mid-eighteenth-century hand which seems to make its corrections from
                    eighteenth-century edited texts; it appears again as Hand II in Twelfth
                        Night, Merry Wives, and Midsummer Night's Dream and
                    Hand III in Lear (see, for example, II.i.87; II.ii.197). Hand V
                    (perhaps ,the same as Hand II in Lear and Henry VIII) limits
                    itself to a  few textual changes (see
                    III.i.173-175; IV.iii.3, 4; IV.vii.14). Hand VI (the same as that of the copyist
                    in Merry Wives and Wilson's Belphegor)4 adds one actor's name, a property note, and sound
                    effects (see I.iv.6; III.i. opening; IV.vii.35 s.d.; V.ii.291). Hand VII writes
                    'Redy' under Hand II's calls, adds a few additional calls (see I.i.19-20;
                    II.ii.116; IV.iii.89; V.i.27; V.ii.172-179) and is probably responsible for the
                    crossed diagonal lines marking point of entry. Hand VIII occurs rarely and is
                    concerned with changes in scene settings and with properties (see IV.ii.
                    opening; IV.v. opening; V.ii. opening, 236 s.d.). Hand IX makes a few textual
                    changes (see I.iii.2-4, 20; IV.v.103-106; IV.vii.6; V.i.281). What may probably
                    be considered as a tenth hand appears in certain passages marked with a red
                    pencil (see I.iii.22-28; II.i.80; III.iv.118-122; V.ii.338-339). As I noted at the beginning of the last paragraph, it is with considerable
                    trepidation that I have attempted to sort out these nine hands. The evidence is
                    frequently so fragmentary that often one is left grasping at a single word or
                    even a few letters. Moreover the conditions under which the notations were made
                    were many times unfavorable, so that the writer was cramped and his writing
                    distorted. Two hands trouble me particularly. Is Hand II really responsible not
                    only for the majority of the character calls and act divisions, but also for the
                    greater part of the actual cutting and textual revision? I am not absolutely
                    sure, and it is possible that we have here two distinct hands at work under what
                    I have called Hand II. Again, is Hand V, in fact, only Hand II in a more formal
                    (and secretary) guise? Since I cannot be sure of the answers to either of these
                    questions, I have decided to allow the designations to stand and to let my
                    comments here serve as a warning. The question of cutting in the Smock Alley Hamlet presents several
                    problems. Because of the difference in length between the quarto and folio
                    texts, the text used by the Smock Alley performers was already, before any
                    cutting was undertaken, about 115 lines shorter than the quarto version employed
                    by the Duke of York's players in London. 5 This fact
                     has been kept in mind in arriving at some of
                    the following figures. In the 1676 quartos (here called Q6, since the two
                    quartos of that year are essentially identical for our purposes) and in all the
                    later quartos (the last 1703) approximately 845 lines have been marked for
                    deletion. Of the six other theatre versions here compared, Ward A and B (c.
                    1745) and the 1703 Folger prompt-book employ quarto editions as the bases of
                    their acting texts; 6 the Tonson 1734 edition
                    (representing the play as staged at Drury Lane about 1723) and the Garrick 1763
                    edition 7 are composite texts based on both quarto and
                    folio and influenced by Rowe and later editors. The Garrick prompt-book (1772),
                    to be distinguished from the 1763 Garrick version, is based on a 1747 text very
                    close to that in the 1734 edition. Ward A cuts roughly 1,237 lines, Ward B about
                    1,056 lines; the 1734 edition marks approximately 1,081 lines for deletion and
                    the 1763 Garrick version omits about 1,220 lines. The Garrick prompt-book and
                    the1703 Folger promptbook (obviously related versions) 8 cut too drastically at the end to make comparative figures very
                    helpful. 9 In comparing these figures with the amount of cutting in the Smock Alley
                        Hamlet one is confronted not only by the discrepancy in length
                    between the quarto and folio texts, but also by the difficulty of determining
                    the exact amount of cutting intended. Two distinct layers of cutting may be
                    distinguished. The earlier layer is, in general, indicated by a rough circling
                    of a line or group of lines; the second layer by a crossing through of
                    individual lines (or occasionally by rough crisscrossing of a group of lines).
                        10 Someone apparently went
                     through the play (possibly with a copy of Q6
                    beside him) and circled lines and groups of lines with a view to preliminary
                    cutting. This individual circled, in all, about 607 lines. Following this, Hand
                    II (possibly, of course, the same person as the first 'circler') went through
                    the play again, straightening out some of the tangles created by the circling,
                    crossing through roughly 427 of the circled lines, at the same time crossing
                    through an additional 175, making a total of 602 lines clearly marked for
                    deletion. To these must be added 8 lines at IV.iv (the momentary entrance of
                    Fortinbras in the folio text) which, though only circled, were certainly meant
                    to be deleted, and another 7 lines in a torn section at II.ii.244 and
                    III.iii.26. In all, then, the Smock Alley Hamlet would appear to cut
                    around 617 lines. Allowing for the difference in length between quarto and folio
                    texts, this figure gives a version only slightly longer than that of Q6. 11 There still remain, however, about 169 lines which
                    have been circled but not otherwise marked, a number of which 'cuts' agree with
                    suggested cuts in Q6. In many cases, moreover, I find it difficult to believe
                    that these cuts were not finally intended, particularly, for example, in the
                    play-within-the-play, which otherwise remains completely uncut. 12 If, then, we may suppose that the cutting includes
                    all the circled passages not otherwise marked for deletion by partial crossing
                    through, we arrive at a final total of around 786 lines, leaving a play of
                    approximately 2,860 lines, 13 version nearly the same
                    length as that of the suggested cutting of Q6 (2,832 lines). The relation of the Smock Alley Hamlet to Qq. 6-7 (1676) must now be
                    examined. Some connection with the text of Hamlet as it is found in Qq.
                    6-7 (and in the succeeding quartos) is certain, but whether the connection comes
                    through the use of a copy, or copies, of Qq. 6-7 or through the reviser's
                    (largely Hand II) knowledge of the London production on which Qq. 6-7 are based,
                    requires consideration. The evidence is confusing. Many of the cuts, both those
                    circled and those crossed through, agree exactly with cuts marked in Qq. 6-7.
                     Moreover, passages omitted from the quarto
                    version are often circled or crossed through, and many readings (mostly
                    introduced by Hand II) which appear in print for the first time in Qq. 6-7 have
                    been inserted throughout in the folio text. 14 On the
                    other hand, many passages marked for deletion in Qq. 6-7 are not cut in the
                    Smock Alley Hamlet; it makes independent cuts, and it sometimes follows
                    the Qq. 6-7 reading only in part, giving the appearance of a reviser working
                    rather from memory than from a printed text. 15
                    Occasionally, moreover, Hand II will alter phrasing in the folio (also revised
                    or different in Qq. 6-7), but produce something quite unlike the Qq. 6-7
                    reading. 16 There is, however, one piece of evidence
                    which points with some certainty to the use, at some stage, of a copy of Q6 (or
                    Q7). At I.i.78 the Folio has been altered to read (Hand ?II): 'makes the night
                        joynt-laborouror with the day:' to bring it into
                    agreement with the reading of Qq. 6-7: 'Makes the night joynt labour with the
                    day?' The word 'labour' in Qq. 6-7 is obviously an error (shared with Q5 [1637]
                    and corrected in Q8 [1683]) and the only way in which I can explain the
                    redundant form 'laborouror' in the Smock Alley PB is to
                    postulate careless copying from a corrected copy of Q6 (or Q7). The evidence, as
                    a whole then, suggests considerable but not very systematic use of Qq. 6-7, eked
                    out, as I shall suggest below, with what the reviser (or revisers) remembered
                    from London performances. At certain places the handling of the text in the Smock Alley Hamlet
                    might seem to be more closely connected with eighteenth-century usage than with
                    that in Q6. The most obvious example is the omission of the dumb show in III.ii
                    and the changes in the dialogue between Hamlet and Ophelia immediately
                    following. Actually, however, Q6 here most probably fails to record contemporary
                    London stage usage, while the Smock Alley PB preserves it, since it is most
                    unlikely that the direction of influence would have been from Dublin to the
                    later English stage. Other examples, where the Smock Alley PB may certainly or
                    probably be interpreted as revealing contemporary
                     London production or cutting, may be
                    studied, in the text or collations, at I.i.30-31, 33-34, 70 (discussed below);
                    I.ii.202-204; I.iii.2-4; I.iv.65; I.v.135, 142, 156; I.ii.489; III.ii.192-195;
                    IV.i.1-2, 14-23, 25-27; IV.iii.8, 58-70; IV.v.147-148, 152; IV.vii.162; V.i.240
                    s.d.; V.ii.278. In his article on the Ward prompt-books, Dr. McManaway discusses the method there
                    followed for getting the Ghost on and off stage in I.i, I.iv-v, and III.iv. It
                    is clear that a trap was used for the Ghost's exit in I.v and for his entrance
                    in III.iv. In I.i he seems to have 'stalked' on and off both times. 17 But Dr. McManaway and the late W. J. Lawrence would
                    like to postulate the use of a trap for entrance and exit in I.i and for
                    entrance in I.iv on the Elizabethan stage. The Smock Alley Hamlet,
                    however, does not support this view; no trap seems to have been used in any of
                    the scenes in question. 18 One piece of 'business' in
                    I.i should perhaps be particularly noticed since it may have some bearing on the
                    presentation of the Ghost's two entrances. The quarto and folio texts contain
                    lines which make it clear that Horatio, Marcellus, and Barnardo are meant to be
                    seated just before each appearance of the Ghost, but the Smock Alley PB, Ward A
                    and B, Folger 1703 quarto, the Garrick 1763 text, and the 1734 Tonson text
                    (though the last does not for some reason appear to cut the reference in line
                    30) all agree in deleting the several references to sitting. Such a change, of
                    course, makes it unnecessary to have something 'on stage' upon which the three
                    men can sit and hence cuts down on stage props, but it is also possible that the
                    change was made to facilitate the entrance of the Ghost 'OP' or 'PS' instead of
                    by way of the 'long trap' in the centre of the stage. If this argument may be
                    allowed any weight, it would imply that a change took place in the Restoration
                    London staging of this scene, a change not 
                    reflected in Q6, and that the failure of the Smock Alley PB to employ a trap
                    entrance for the Ghost need not be interpreted as evidence against Elizabethan
                    use of the trap in this scene. The Smock Alley Hamlet makes use of a number of the stock scenes, all
                    but one appearing in several of the other plays: Castle (I.i, iv; IV.vi), Court
                    (I.ii; II.ii; IV.i, iii, vii; ?V.ii), 19 Chamber
                    (I.iii; III.iv; IV.ii, v), bed chamber (II.i), Towne (V.i, ii [cancelled]),
                    Church (V.i.240). The change of scene to 'Church' in V.i at line 240 introduces
                    a setting not used elsewhere in the Smock Alley prompt-books; moreover a change
                    of scene at this point, where the original text does not call for it, is
                    interesting in itself, especially when it is also found in the 1734 Tonson and
                    1763 Garrick texts, suggesting once again that the Smock Alley Hamlet
                    reflects Restoration London usage. The scene opens, we may suppose, with the
                    'graveyard' set up against a flat depicting houses and perhaps the outside of a
                    church (this 'Towne' setting is employed in five other Smock Alley plays); at
                    line 240 the scene is drawn, 20 discovering some sort
                    of 'church interior' out of which the procession with Ophelia's body issues. At
                    the conclusion of the scene, the scene would be 'closed,' as Hand I indicated
                    with his setting 'Towne' at the beginning or V.ii. This scene was later
                    recognized as unsatisfactory and resulted in the cancelling of 'Towne' and the
                    call for a 'new sceen' by Hand VI. In its handling of the soliloquies the Smock Alley Hamlet is close to Q6
                    and to most eighteenth-century versions. 21 'To be, or
                    not to be' and "Tis now the very witching time' escape untouched (though Q6 and
                    the later versions cut the last three lines of the second); 'Now might I do it
                    pat' also appears to be uncut, though the Smock Alley PB is imperfect here (Q6
                    cuts 'Then trip . . . goes:' [93-95], but nothing in the earlier
                     part of the speech which is missing from
                    Smock Alley PB); 'How all occasions do inform' is, of course, omitted in the
                    Folio text and hence in the Smock Alley PB, but in most of the later versions
                    this speech was also cut entirely. 22 In his attitude toward Shakespeare's language, the reviser (largely Hand II)
                    honors, for the most part, the modernizations found in the Q6 text. Occasionally
                    he introduces variants of Q6's forms, 23 and from time
                    to time makes changes or additions of his own (see, I.ii.64; I.ii. 126, 133-134,
                    202-204; I.iii.56, 108-109; I.iv.73-74; I.v.91; II.ii.6-12, 15-18;
                    III.i.173-175; III.ii.146, 149, 152, 153, 154; III.iii.37; III.iv. 19; IV.iii.3,
                    4, 45, 46-47, 58-70; IV.v.77-94, 94, 101, 103-106, 151, 171, 172; IV.vii.6, 162;
                    V.ii.294).  &lt;/page&gt;   &lt;page n=10&gt;  The Smock Alley Hamlet has been compared throughout with the following
                    seven stage versions: (1) the Betterton cutting first published in 1676 (here
                    represented by a copy of the four-line imprint edition and referred to as Q6);
                    the remaining quartos (1676, 1683, 1695, 1703) all present essentially the same
                    text. (2) The 1734 Tonson edition, representing the Wilks' text of 1723
                    (referred to as 1734). (3) Ward A and (4) Ward B (see Note 3, above). (5) The
                    first Garrick version, represented by the 1763 edition referred to as 1763. (6)
                    The autograph Garrick prompt-book of his 1772 version (referred to as Garrick
                    PB). (7) The 1703 quarto Folger prompt-book, dating sometime after 1772
                    (referred to as 1703 Folger). 24 The cuts in the
                    Collier-Perkins Second Folio (1632) have also been compared. 1. A later quarto (Q8, 1683, etc.) is almost certainly ruled out by
                    (a) the evidence in I.i.78 (see discussion below) and (b) the supporting
                    evidence of the other related Smock Alley prompt-books. 2. W. S. Clark, The Early Irish Stage (Oxford, 1955), pp.
                    208-209. The identification of '&lt;?W&gt;illian' in the call at V.ii.153 as
                    Williams is not, of course, certain. Williams appears elsewhere only in the
                        Julius Caesar cast, a cast which can be dated as not later than
                    1676. 3. The nearest contestants are two prompt-books prepared by the actor
                    John Ward probably around 1745 (hereafter referred to as Ward A [Tudor and
                    Stuart Club, Johns Hopkins University] and Ward B [Folger Shakespeare Library]).
                    Ward A makes use of one of the 1676 quartos (four-line imprint); Ward B, of a
                    copy of the 1683 quarto. See James G. McManaway, "The Two Earliest Prompt Books
                    of Hamlet," PBSA, XLIII (1949), 288-320. Dr. McManaway dates these two
                    Ward prompt-books 'shortly after 1740' (p. 310), but Ward's use of Warburton's
                    emendation 'Hernshaw' at II.ii.398 (Ward A) ) would suggest a date after 1744.
                    When Dr. McManaway wrote his article, the whereabouts of the Smock Alley
                        Hamlet was unknown and it is to his kindness that I owe my
                    knowledge of it.  A copy of the 1703 quarto (Folger Shakespeare
                    Library, hereafter referred to as 1703 Folger) which shows definite evidence of
                    stage provenience is much later and can be closely associated with Garrick's
                    1772 version (see, below, note 22). Another theatre version in the Folger
                    Library, employing a 1750 Dublin edition of Hamlet, dates from Richard
                    Daly's management of the Crow Street Theatre, Dublin (i.e. 1788-97). It has
                    interesting notes on the acting of Hamlet's role, but is not properly speaking a
                    prompt-book. I have not included it among the theatre versions compared in the
                    Collations. 4. I have mistakenly described Hand VI as the same as Hand V in
                        Othello and Hand III in I Henry IV in the General
                    Introduction, p. 17, found in Volume I, Macbeth. 5. The Folio text lacks roughly 200 lines found in Quarto 2 (1604) and
                    in all the later quartos, but it also contains about 85 lines not found in the
                    quarto texts. The large amount of prose in Hamlet further complicates
                    the counting of lines in texts which range from double column folio to duodecimo
                    format. 6. See note 3, above. 7. I have not been able to see a copy of the 1751 edition of the first
                    Garrick version, but C. B. Hogan (Shakespeare in the Theatre, II
                    (1957), 188) asserts that the 1763 edition is identical with the 1751 edition
                    'save for minor omissions or restorations.' See Hogan's list of the more
                    important omissions in the 1751 edition (pp. 187-188).  8. See note 22, below. 9. The 1703 Folger prompt-book cuts about 712 lines through IV.v; the
                    Garrick prompt-book appears to cut only about 361 lines down to IV.vi, though I
                    am somewhat suspicious of the apparent lack of cutting in the first four acts in
                    view of the relationship between the Garrick prompt-book and the 1703 Folger
                    version.  10. For the evidence establishing the relative order, see the text or
                    collations at I.i.72-80, 90-96, 99-107; I.ii.17-41; II.i.1-74; II.ii.6-12;
                    IV.iv.123-125. A third layer of cutting may be indicated by the use of a red
                    crayon at II.ii.172, 173; III.iv.118-122, V.ii.338.  11. The omission of the dumb show in III.ii (retained by Q6) by Smock
                    Alley PB would further serve to level the playing time.  12. By this I mean circled passages in which none of the lines has
                    been separately deleted by being crossed through. There are, in support of the
                    view that circling also implies cutting, two places where circled passages have
                    been marked 'stet' (see III.iii.40-64 and III.iv.118-122).  13. My count is based on Alfred Hart's total of 3,761 lines for
                        Hamlet, with allowance made for the Folio text (see RES,
                    VIII [1932], 21) .  14. See, for example, I.ii.141, 195; I.iii.7, 20, 46; I.v.187;
                    II.ii.437; IV.vii.10, 14.  15. See, for example, I.ii.77-81, 195; I.iii.30; I.v.91, 133; II.ii.
                    553; III.i.30-31; IV.iii.46-47; IV.v.123-125, 147-148; IV.vii.63, 128-129.
                    Compare the use of the D'Avenant Macbeth in the Smock Alley PB.  16. See, for example, I.v.186; II.i.77, 79; IV.v.123-125, 151;
                    IV.vii.63.  17. McManaway, op.cit., 315-317. It is interesting
                    to compare also the handling of these scenes in the 1703 Folger PB. In I.i the
                    Ghost walks on 'OP' and exits 'PS'; he then re-enters 'PS' and exits 'OP'
                    (incidentally the 'cock crowing' is here deleted). In I.iv the Ghost walks on
                    'PS' and exits with Hamlet 'PS', re-entering immediately with Hamlet 'OP'. A
                    trap, however, is used for his exit, the direction reading 'Ghost sinks PS' (the
                    understage swearing is here cut to a single 'Swear' on the Ghost's part at line
                    149, lines 150-163 being deleted). In III.iv the Ghost walks on 'OPd' and off
                    (his exit position not noted since he only appears and does not move).  18. That the Smock Alley theatre was equipped for trap appearances is
                    proved by two such entrances in the Smock Alley prompt-book of Wilson's
                        Belphegor (c. 1677), a play more or less exactly
                    contemporary with the Smock Alley Hamlet. 19. V.ii was originally marked 'Towne' (Hand I), but this was crossed
                    through and altered to 'new sceen' (Hand VII), by which is meant probably the
                    'Court' scene (Hand I having originally suggested a change of scene to 'Court'
                    at line 235, also crossed through).  20. Compare the s.d. in the 1734 Tonson version: 'Scene draws, and
                    discovers the King, Queen, Laertes and - Priest, with a Corse.' Rowe
                    describes the whole setting of V.i as 'SCENE A Church.' 21. See Hazelton Spencer, 'Hamlet under the Restoration,'
                        PMLA, XXXVIII (1923), 770-791, and 'Seventeenth-Century Cuts in
                    Hamlet's Soliloquies,' RES, IX (1933), 257-265. G. W. Stone, Jr.
                    ('Garrick's Alteration of Hamlet,' PMLA, XLIX [1934], 890-921) also
                    offers some interesting figures on cutting in several eighteenth-century printed
                    versions.  22. First restored in Garrick's 1772 version (see Stone, op.cit.,
                        p. 903). It is also restored (and arranged as in the Garrick version,
                    except that Rosincrantz takes the Captain's place instead of Guildenstern) in
                    the 1703 Folger PB, which concludes IV.iv and begins IV.v as follows (beginning
                    with line 59) :  "And let all sleep, Awake my Soul awake! 
                    Wake Nature, Manhood Vengeance [wake deleted;] rouse at once 
                    My Father's Spirit calls! the hour is come!  From this time forth--My
                    thoughts be bloody all  I'll fly my Keepers--Sweep to my Revenge.
                     Exit PS. Scene Enter King &amp; Queen PS.  King:
                    See where She comes--it is a piteous Sight. Queen. O She Cleaves my heart--her distemperd mind 
                    Communicates Infection to my own. Enter Ophelia distracted Where is the beauteous &amp;c"  The
                    connection with Garrick's concluding lines in Hamlet's soliloquy is obvious: 'O
                    from this Time forth,/ My Thoughts be bloody all! the hour is come-- / I'll fly
                    my Keepers--sweep to my revenge.' (see Stone, op.cit., p. 912). On the
                    other hand, the beginning of Garrick's equivalent of IV.v shows no connection
                    with the opening lines as given in the 1703 Folger PB. Later in IV.v, however,
                    we find 1703 Folger PB following Garrick's insertion of lines 203-219 ('go but .
                    . . with me.') after line 152 ('.. . your eye.'). These points of contact with
                    Garrick's 1772 version explain why the prompt-markings stop with the end of
                    IV.v, what little remains in Garrick's version having been separately copied out
                    by the prompter (and since lost). The fact that the lines quoted from the
                    conclusion of Hamlet's soliloquy (IV.iv) agree exactly with the conclusion of
                    that soliloquy as quoted by the younger Boswell (Boswell's edition of Malone's
                        Shakespeare, 1821, II, 692) from another copy of the 1703 quarto
                    prepared by William Hopkins, Garrick's prompter (see Stone, op.cit., p.
                    891) would suggest perhaps that this version, rather than that quoted directly
                    from Garrick's autograph copy by Stone (op.cit., p. 912), was the final
                    stage form and that the opening lines inserted in the 1703 Folger PB for IV.v
                    also represent Garrick's final version. If this is so, then the 1703 Folger
                    version deserves further study since a number of the earlier cuts agree only in
                    part with the cuts listed by Stone for Garrick's adaptation.  23. See Note 14, above.  24. The version in Bell's Shakespeare (1773), Vol.III, is
                    essentially a reprint of the 1751 Garrick text.   &lt;/page&gt;   &lt;page n=11&gt; </field><field name="file_s">ShaHamP</field></doc></add>