<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><add><doc><field name="id">d1e2</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">header</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 1
                            (General Introduction and Padua Macbeth)  </field><field name="fulltext_t">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 1 (Preface and
                    General Introduction) [a machine-readable transcription] Shakespeare, William Creation of machine-readable version: Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia Library Creation of digital images: Electronic Text center, University of Virginia Library Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. ca. 70 kilobytes University of Virginia Library. Charlottesville, Va. Studies in Bibliography, ShaIntP Publicly-accessible URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/modeng/modeng0.browse.html URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/bsuva/ 1997 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 1
                            (General Introduction and Padua Macbeth) William Shakespeare Editor G. Blakemore Evans Issued in portfolios. The prompt-books are reproduced in collotype
                            facsimile. University Press of Virginia Charlottesville, VA 1960 Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PR 2757 .E9 1960 v.1 pt.
                            1-2 Copy 2 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century Published for the Bibliographical Society of the University of
                            Virginia The production of this volume was supervised by Fredson Bowers and
                            Sears Jayne  Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. All quotation marks retained as data. All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line. The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs. Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings. Library of Congress Subject Headings  1960 English drama; prose; non-fiction LCSH 24-bit color; 400 dpi  February 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant Added TEI header </field><field name="file_s">ShaIntP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e130</field><field name="section_s">front</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 1
                            (General Introduction and Padua Macbeth)  </field><field name="fulltext_t"> SHAKESPEAREANPROMPT BOOKSof
                        theSEVENTEENTH CENTURYVol. I: Part i General IntroductionIntroduction to the Padua
                        MacbethCollations  Edited byG. Blakemore Evans  The Bibliographical Society of the University of
                    VirginiaUniversity Press of Virginia,
                    Charlottesville1960EDITORIAL ADVISORY COMMITTEEThe
                    Bibliographical Society of the University of VirginiaArthur F. Stocker,
                    ChairmanFredson BowersJohn Cook WyllieThe production of this
                    volume was supervised by Fredson Bowers and Sears Jayne </field><field name="file_s">ShaIntP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e237</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="section_s">introduction</field><field name="title_s">General Introduction</field><field name="fulltext_t">General Introduction I am concerned in the present study with a comparatively small collection of
                    special Shakespeare materials: printed texts of Shakespeare's plays which give
                    evidence of a seventeenth-century theatrical provenience and thus record for us
                    some of the acting innovations, readings, and traditions current on the stage
                    during that period. In general, such texts may be described as prompt-books,
                    though I have included several acting versions which strictly do not fall into
                    this category.  The complete study will afford a large body of detailed evidence about the text
                    of Shakespeare's plays as they were presented on the stage during the last
                    three-quarters of the seventeenth century. Since the time of Capell and Jennens
                    in the second half of the eighteenth century the textual guesses, sometimes
                    inspired and sometimes not, of a whole army of learned editors have been
                    reverently and meticulously recorded, an accumulation which resulted finally in
                    the Cambridge Shakespeare and the New Variorum of Furness and his successors.
                    Curiously, however, although there are numerous excellent general studies of
                    seventeenth- and eighteenth-century Shakespearean acting versions, both
                    published and manuscript, there is little detailed study or record of the actual
                    texts as such. For eighteenth-century printed theatre versions C. B. Hogan's
                    recent and invaluable Shakespeare in the Theatre,
                        1701-1800 (1952-57) must be noticed as an exception, though even Mr.
                    Hogan does not pretend to be complete in his lists of cuts and (particularly)
                    textual changes. This study, therefore, is an attempt, using special and
                    generally unavailable materials, partially to fill this gap in our knowledge of
                    Shakespeare in the theatre for the seventeenth century. It should be emphasized,
                     perhaps, that seventeenth-century printed
                    texts such as the 1681 Othello or the 1676 Hamlet, which represent published acting texts, are
                    included only so far as they serve to illustrate the theatre prompt-book under
                    discussion. Since in this study I have aimed at a measure of completeness, every
                    effort has been made to establish the relationship between the
                    seventeenth-century and the principal eighteenth-century acting versions. In
                    order to do this it has been necessary to compare in detail each cut, textual
                    change, setting, etc. with its several seventeenth- and eighteenth-century
                    counterparts and to record the results in the notes to the collations and, more
                    generally, in the separate introductions to each play. Only in this way can the
                    uniqueness or community of a cut or reading in the seventeenth- and
                    eighteenth-century versions be recognized and a picture of the oral stage
                    tradition (for the text especially) begin to emerge. Nineteenth-century acting
                    versions, except for an occasional use of Mrs. Inchbald's British Theatre (1808), I have considered outside the scope of the
                    present study.  The materials may be divided into four groups. (I) Three pre-Restoration
                    prompt-books (Macbeth, Measure for
                        Measure, Winter's Tale) which belong together,
                    being found in a copy of the First Folio now in the University Library at Padua,
                    and may be linked, as I shall try to show, with Sir Edward Dering of Surrenden
                    in Kent (c. 1625-35). (II) Two prompt-books (Comedy of Errors, Midsummer Night's
                        Dream), both from a copy of the First Folio, connected with the Hatton
                    Garden Nursery (c. 1672). (III) Eleven prompt-books (Hamlet, Macbeth, Othello, King Lear, Twelfth Night, Midsummer Night's
                        Dream, Henry VIII, I Henry
                        IV, Comedy of Errors, Merry
                        Wives, and Winter's Tale), all from a copy of
                    the Third Folio, belonging to the Smock Alley Theatre in Dublin (c. 1676-85). (IV) A prompt-book of Twelfth Night (Second Folio) which, though it is of unknown
                    provenience, is almost certainly seventeenth-century; an incomplete cutting of
                        Merchant of Venice, Second Folio, which, though also
                    of uncertain provenience, is probably seventeenth-century in origin; and three
                    texts (Romeo and Juliet, 1599 quarto; Merry Wives, 1633 quarto;  Inside front board: Padua First FolioImage of Inside Front Board: Padua First Folio Inside back board: Padua First FolioImage of Inside Back Board: Padua First Folio Sig. 3b6v: Padua First FolioImage of Sig. 3b6v: Padua First Folio Sig. 3M4v: Smock Alley Third FolioJulius Ceasar acting
                            listImage of Sig. 3M4v: Smock Alley Third Folio, Julius Ceasar acting
                            list  &lt;/page&gt;   &lt;page n=5&gt;  Much Ado, 1600 quarto), of which the theatrical
                    provenience is doubtful. Finally, as an appendix, I have included a complete
                    list of the deletions marked in the notorious Collier-Perkins Second Folio.  Group I: Pre-Restoration prompt-books. The Padua
                    prompt-books, part of a First Folio in the University Library at Padua, have
                    been 'discovered' several times. Attention was first called to them by an
                    'Occasional Correspondent' in the Scotsman (11 July
                    1895). Sir Sidney Lee then listed the Padua Folio in the Supplement to his
                    facsimile of the First Folio (Oxford, 1902) and described it as having "early
                    MS. notes, made apparently by an acting manager." It was not until 1932,
                    however, that anyone seems to have paid further attention; in that year G. N.
                    Giordano Orsini published an account of them as part of an article entitled
                    "Nuovi orientamenti della Filologia shakespeariana" in Civiltà moderna (1932, IV, 3-46), an account which contained,
                    as an appendix, a nearly complete list of the textual deletions in the three
                    prompt-books. Giordano Orsini's study seems to have passed almost unnoticed in
                    this country.[1] In 1936, Leslie F. Casson,
                    apparently independently of Giordano Orsini's article, offered a general
                    discussion of all three prompt-books, noting the principal changes (and some of
                    the deletions), and made an attempt to date them by trying to associate the
                    actors' names and initials with particular actors in the Restoration.[2] That Casson was mistaken in his identifications
                    will I think appear from the discussion below. Like Giordano Orsini's, Casson's
                    article passed unnoticed, except for a listing in Studies in
                        Philology. Finally, in 1950, I 'discovered' the Padua prompt-books all
                    over again and was subsequently considerably chagrined to find that I had been
                    anticipated not once, but three times!  It is not known how or when this copy of the First Folio
                     came into the hands of the University
                    Library at Padua. The volume was accidentally discovered about 1895 "amongst a
                    number of uncatalogued books".[3] My letter of
                    enquiry has received no response, and Casson, though on the spot, was unable to
                    uncover any further information. The book is bound in brown leather, almost
                    certainly its original English binding.[4] A label
                    which reads 'Tutte le Opere di: / Sakespear / Commedie e Tragedie. / manca il
                    Frontispizio' has been pasted on the inside of the front board (the front and
                    back end-papers, sig. A1, and the engraved title-page are lacking). The
                    handwriting is eighteenth-century, or possibly seventeenth, and suggests that
                    the volume arrived in Italy fairly early in its career. Below the label, in the
                    same hand, is written 'F in capsa / ad Læuam' (i.e., ?Folio in the
                    left-hand chest or drawer).[5] The number '385'
                    appears in the upper left corner. On sig. 3b6v another hand
                    has written a phrase of which I can make no sense whatever: 'in /
                    &lt;Som.are&gt; contentum.'. The letters recorded for
                    the second word are very uncertain: 'S' might well be read as 'T', 'm' as 'ui'
                    or 'ni', etc.; and the form 'contentum' should perhaps
                    be read 'contentionem'. Below, on the same page, another hand has added what may
                    be a date 'M'y 6'. The inner back board contains what may possibly be either a
                    library number or acquisition date (?1695), perhaps both (see the reproduction
                    opposite page 4), and a scrawl in English, in yet another hand, beginning 'and
                    one y &lt;.n.&gt; &amp; &lt;ta.n.&gt; &lt;etc&gt;' (all but the first two words
                    badly smudged). Finally, we may notice what appears, when disentangled, to be
                    the name 'joh: B ffort' scribbled down the left margin of sig. F6v in the prompt-book of Measure for Measure. I
                    cannot associate the hand with that in the prompt-book or with any other in the
                    volume.  The full importance of the Padua prompt-books has not hitherto been recognized;
                    they are, I believe, our earliest examples of Shakespearean prompt-books and
                    should be dated about 1625-35. The evidence for such dating must now be
                    considered in full.  The Padua prompt-books contain no indication of location or scene setting.
                    Restoration prompt-books, except in unusual circumstances, regularly indicate
                    the set to be used with each change of scene.[6] In
                        Macbeth and Measure for
                        Measure the prompter's calls are not anticipatory (except in one or two
                    cases). This fact at once distinguishes these two Padua promptbooks from
                    Restoration prompt-books and in itself suggests a date in the later 1620's, for,
                    as W. J. Lawrence observes, " . . . so far as the prompter was concerned, the
                    system of advance calls for players, musicians, and properties first came into
                    vogue somewhere in the period 1625-31."[7] Other points also serve to support an early date. A 'Senett' is called for at the
                    opening of IV.iv in Macbeth, where the Folio stage
                    direction makes no such provision. By 1660 the technical theatre term 'sennet'
                    seems to have been completely obsolete; indeed the NED
                    records no later use than 1619. The  calls
                    'Bee ready Group II:' (Measure for Measure, IV.iii) and
                    'Bee ready' (V.i.259) are definitely on a pre-Restoration formula found
                    occasionally in prompt-books belonging to the second and third decades of the
                        century.[8] I have seen no cases of this
                    particular imperative warning in Restoration promptbooks. Again, the complete
                    absence of any attempt to 'modernize' Shakespeare's language immediately
                    distinguishes the Padua prompt-books from most Restoration acting versions,
                    particularly among the tragedies. There is also the evidence of the handwriting.
                    Two quite distinct hands are et work: Hand I, that in Macbeth and Measure for Measure;[9] and Hand II, that in The
                        Winter's Tale. Both hands give the impression of early rather than late
                    seventeenth-century formation, though this is a matter on which it is possible
                    to be badly misled.  Finally, there is the important matter of provenience. Like a number of others,
                    the Padua prompt-books contain the names or initials of certain minor actors
                    among the prompt-calls, and it is possible, I believe, to identify three of
                    these individuals with persons who took part in an amateur performance of
                    Fletcher's Spanish Curate produced by Sir Edward Dering
                    at his estate, Surrenden, in Kent, between 22 October 1622 (the date on which
                    the play was licensed) and "the summer of 1624".[10] Among the names listed by Sir Edward for The
                        Spanish Curate are 'Jhon Carlile', 'Tho: Slender', and 'Mr. Kemp'.
                        [11] In the Padua Macbeth we find 'Mr Carlile' (and 'Mr Carl'),  'T S', and 'Mr K'. The other three names which appear in Macbeth are 'Mr G', 'E H', and 'Mr H&lt;e&gt;w&lt;it&gt;', none of which occurs in The Spanish Curate list. Trying to link these with Sir
                    Edward Dering is perhaps hazardous. I would, however, suggest that 'Mr G' may be a certain 'Georg Perd' who figures in The Spanish Curate list and who knew Sir Edward well
                    enough to subscribe a letter with 'Thus in hast with my service to your dearr self and &lt;vert&gt;uous Lady in some hast I end
                        Your most affectionate friend Geo: Pearde.'[12] The only 'E H' I can associate with Sir Edward
                    is the well-known Sir Edward Hales and that he should appear as a mere 'E H'
                    seems highly unlikely. The third name, which should prove most helpful, is
                    unfortunately very questionable. Giordano Orsini reads 'H.wit'[13] and Casson 'H&lt;ewi&gt;t', remarking, "This
                    name is difficult to decipher, but is possibly 'Mr. H&lt;ewi&gt;t'".[14] I am fairly sure of two letters: 'H&lt;.&gt;w&lt;.
                    .&gt;'. There are two possible candidates. One is a certain 'Geo: Haule' or 'Cosen
                    Hawle' as Dering calls him.[15] The other is an
                    individual called 'Hugett', an acceptable spelling of 'Hewit'', who figures in a
                    long list of names at the end of Sir Edward's 'pocket-book' for the year
                        1637.[16] That Sir Edward Dering was interested in the theatre and in Shakespeare is
                    apparent from the telescoped version of I and II Henry IV which is now generally known as the Dering
                    MS. This manuscript, the first page of which is in Dering's hand,[17] contains numerous corrections and additions by
                    him.  We also hear, in 1619, of nine
                    shillings spent for 'twenty-seven play-bookes'[18]
                    and, in 1637, eighteen years later, Dering was still buying more 'playbookes'.
                    In his pocket-book for that year a list of 'Bookes in print' begins with 'Duche
                    armes in print / Epitaphes. epithalamy's. playbookes / witchery.' and ends with
                    'Lat. Bible. Septuagint / Tertullian / Shakespeare / &lt;....&gt; &lt;....&gt;
                    painted / virgel and other poets of ye best / qu: de omni
                    modis biblijs / Lat Graec Anglic.'.[19] The exact
                    purpose of this list (mostly crossed through) is not clear, though it most
                    probably represents a collection of books sent to be bound and not necessarily
                    recent purchases. Dates of individual volumes range from 1573 to 1632, and the
                    'Shakespeare' so temptingly exhibited could be either a First or Second Folio.  In setting out the evidence for the Dering provenience I have tried to avoid
                    pressing the claim too strongly. The case hangs essentially on one name and two
                    initials and cannot be considered conclusive. Nevertheless, it may, I think, be
                    admitted as at least persuasive, especially as the Dering provenience squares
                    perfectly with the other evidences of date already discussed. One point,
                    however, must now be noticed which may be considered to argue against attaching
                    the Padua prompt-books to the amateur Dering group. This is their apparently
                    professional appearance. In format they give the impression of having been
                    prepared by persons thoroughly familiar with the conventions of prompt-book
                    makers during the later 1620's and 1630's. It might be argued that Dering had
                    procured professional assistance in preparing these copies from
                     the official prompt-book, but this approach
                    seems to be ruled out by the fact that where an actor is named as playing one of
                    the minor roles, the hand is the same in both call and actor's name. Moreover
                    The Winter's Tale, which is cut only up to I.iii, assigns two small roles to 'T
                    S', showing that here at least the roles were assigned as the calls were written
                    in. Various solutions might be advanced, but none could be more than the merest
                    hypothesis.  But even if we cannot argue very warmly for professional help with the actual
                    preparation of the prompt-books, the question remains of how far Dering's
                    changes, if we accept them as either his or changes made by one of his
                    associates, may be taken to reflect contemporary theatre practice. Considering
                    Dering's known interest in the drama, it seems fair to assume that in some part
                    at least the alterations may be taken to represent what Dering had seen on the
                    professional stage during his visits to London, and it is interesting to notice
                    how often the changes in Macbeth are reflected in the
                    Restoration D'Avenant and Smock Alley versions. Such continuity suggests a
                    professional source, however come by, for some of the changes in the Padua Macbeth, and, by association, in the Padua Measure for Measure and The Winter's
                        Tale. This last argument will hold, of course, even if we refuse to
                    accept the Dering provenience.  Detailed discussion of the individual prompt-books will be given in the separate
                    introduction to each play.  Group II: Restoration 'Nursery' prompt-books. These
                    prompt-books of The Comedy of Errors and Midsummer Night's Dream, now preserved in the University
                    of Edinburgh Library, the gift of Halliwell-Phillipps, are our only extant
                    examples of seventeenth-century ?London prompt-books of Shakespeare's plays.
                    Only The Comedy of Errors reached production; Midsummer Night's Dream merely shows evidence of cutting
                    (no prompt-calls, etc.). Both are part of a First Folio, and the cutting in both
                    seems to be the work of the same hand. On the basis of the cast for The Comedy of Errors, which it is
                     possible to reconstruct completely from the
                    prompter's calls, we may with some assurance date these prompt-books c. 1672. A full discussion of the provenience, cast, and
                    dating may be reserved for the separate introduction to The
                        Comedy of Errors.  Group III: The Smock Alley prompt-books. The eleven
                    prompt-books in this group (Hamlet, Macbeth, Othello, King
                        Lear, Twelfth Night, Midsummer Night's Dream, Henry VIII, I Henry IV, Comedy of Errors,
                        Merry Wives, Winter's Tale)
                    have been known since the middle of the nineteenth century and were once in the
                    possession of Halliwell-Phillipps.[20] All but two
                    now form part of the Folger Shakespeare Library collection of prompt-books.[21] The remaining two (Hamlet and Midsummer Night's Dream) are
                    preserved in the University of Edinburgh Library.  Originally there appear to have been similar promptbooks of Julius Caesar and II Henry IV, possibly also
                    of Measure for Measure, The Tempest, and Troilus and
                        Cressida.[22] The copies of Troilus and Cressida and Julius
                        Caesar were presented by Halliwell-Phillipps to the Shakespeare
                    Memorial Library at Birmingham and were there unfortunately destroyed in the
                    fire of 1879.[23] For Julius
                        Caesar, however. a cast  (written
                    on the last page of Timon of Athens) has survived, as
                    well as a manuscript couplet scrawled down the right margin of the first page of
                        Macbeth (facing the final page of Julius Caesar). The cast, which can be dated as not later than 1676,
                    gives us important information on the personnel of the Smock Alley Theatre.[24] The cast is as follows: &lt;Jull&gt;ius Cesszer the Acto&lt;rs&gt; naimsFlauius Mr WamslyMurillus Mr WilliamsCobler Mr LysleCarpenter CottsCeazer [Mr Richards][25]
                            Mr CudworthAntoni Mr SmithCalphurnia Mrs SmithPortia Mrs RichardsDesius Mr WamsleyBruttus Mr RichardsCassius Mr AshburyCaska Mr Baker [26] Only two of these actors occur with certainty among the prompter's annotations in
                    the other Shakespearean plays: Walmesley in Othello
                    (I.iii) and Smith in Henry VIII (IV.ii) and Macbeth (V.iii).[27] It is
                    possible, however, that Williams appears 
                    pears as '&lt;W&gt;illian' in Hamlet (V.ii) in the role
                    of Laertes.[28] Other actors whose names appear in
                    the Shakespeare promptbooks are: Andrews (Henry VIII,
                    I.i), Barnes (Othello, I.iii), Charles [?Ashbury] (Othello, I.iii; II.i), Farlow (Macbeth, III.i), Freeman (Othello, II.i),
                    (Mistress) Kaine (Henry VIII, V.i), Longmore (I Henry IV, II.i), Totterdale (Henry
                        VIII, IV.i; Macbeth, V.v.; Othello, I.ii), and Trefusis (Hamlet, IV.v,
                    vii; Othello, I.ii; II.i). What may be illegible or
                    mutilated actors' names occur in Othello (I.ii.63), Henry VIII (I.i.161), and Hamlet
                    (IV.v.113; V.ii.153).[29] Barnes and Freeman also
                    appear in the Smock Alley manuscript prompt-book of Wilson's Belphegor (c. 1677 or 1682) and Totterdale in
                    the Smock Alley cast for Fletcher's Night-Walker
                    (between 1670 and 1676).  The couplet from a Smock Alley production of Julius
                        Caesar which appears in the left margin of the first page of Macbeth reads: poore slavish rome far well: Ceaser
                        now be still I Kild not thee wth half so good a
                        will Dyes R. C. Bald notes that this couplet first appears, spoken
                    by Brutus, in the so-called D'Avenant-Dryden version of the play published in
                    1719 and that it seems likely that "the London alterations were known in the
                    Dublin theatre some years at least before they were available in print."[30] This would seem to suggest that Bald does not
                    consider the possibility that the acting 
                    list, which may be dated before 1677, and the hand that is responsible for the
                    couplet are contemporary (admittedly they are not the same). Though there is
                    nothing to prove that these two hands are contemporary, there is certainly
                    nothing to prove that they are not. Bald's caution is dictated, I suppose, by
                    Hazelton Spencer's rather categorical statement that the "limits of composition of this version [the D'Avenant-Dryden]
                    are thus 1691 and 1719."[31] But the arguments by
                    which Spencer reaches this conclusion do not seem to me entirely satisfactory,
                    and the appearance of this couplet possibly in connection with a production of
                    the play in the middle 1670's (before the appearance of the 1684 Betterton
                    quarto) at least opens up once again the whole question of D'Avenant's and
                    Dryden's possible implication in producing the 'improvement'.[32] Our knowledge of the one-time existence of a Smock Alley prompt-book of II Henry IV we owe to S. W. Singer. In his attack on
                    Collier, The Text of Shakespeare Vindicated (1853),
                    Singer describes (pp. vi-vii) a "tattered copy of the third folio edition of
                    Shakespeare" which "chance has furnished" him ('chance' here being presumably
                    Halliwell-Phillipps). He then gives a list of twelve plays with which he says
                    "the greatest liberties have been taken" in revising them for the stage. This
                    list includes, besides the lost Julius Caesar and ten
                    plays now preserved in the Folger and at Edinburgh, II Henry
                        IV.[33] Finally, the possibility that there were also Smock Alley
                     prompt-books of Measure
                        for Measure, Troilus and Cressida, and The Tempest was first brought to light by J. G.
                        McManaway.[34] He was able to trace
                    Halliwell-Phillipps' 'tattered copy' back to the library of John Dent. It was
                    sold at the sale of Dent's books in 1827. The auction catalogue carefully
                    describes the volume and offers four examples of the kind of manuscript
                    corrections it contained: one each from Troilus and
                        Cressida and Measure for Measure and two from
                        The Tempest. Unfortunately the cataloguer was
                    interested only in textual emendations later suggested by either Rowe or Hanmer.
                    McManaway considers these readings as anticipations of Rowe and Hanmer and does
                    not believe it necessary to "postulate the intrusion of an otherwise unknown
                    literary hand" in these three plays in view of the fact that "the various hands
                    (Bald counts six in Othello) in the Folger copies of the
                    plays appear to be connected with performances". But this is an
                    oversimplification of the state of some of the extant Smock Alley promptbooks.
                    In King Lear, Hamlet, Twelfth Night, Midsummer Night's
                        Dream, and Merry Wives it is certain that some
                    hand (described below as Hand H) about the middle of the eighteenth century
                    busied itself (with what purpose is not clear) with incorporating the readings
                    of various editors through at least Hanmer.[35] It
                    is also, I think, significant that Singer, who saw the volume before it was
                    broken up by Halliwell-Phillipps, did not include Measure for
                        Measure, Troilus and Cressida, or The Tempest among those plays "with which the greatest
                    liberties have been taken". In view of these considerations we must, I believe,
                    accept the one-time existence of actual theatre prompt-books of these plays with
                    some caution.[36] A particularly difficult problem in the study of the Smock Alley prompt-books
                    arises from the number of different prompt hands. Yet the identification and
                    isolation of these hands is most often the only clue to distinguishing the work
                    of different individuals in the preparation of a prompt-book. Several
                    prompt-books contain as many as five or six principal hands and it is frequently
                    hard, sometimes impossible, to assign to its proper hand each prompt-note or
                    textual change. The difficulty becomes even greater when, under changed
                    conditions imposed by new pens, ink, etc., one tries to identify hands in one
                    prompt-book with those appearing in other prompt-books. As in dealing with the
                    Padua and 'Nursery' prompt-books, I have assigned all readings to a particular
                    hand whenever possible, but with the Smock Alley prompt-books I have more
                    frequently been forced to question the exact identification or to admit defeat.  Eight hands appear in more than one Smock Alley prompt-book. The following table
                    will help to establish their interrelationships:[37] HAND A:Hamlet (Hand I); Lear
                        (Hand I); Macbeth (Hand I); Twelfth Night (Hand I)HAND B:Hamlet (Hand III); Julius
                            Caesar (acting list); Macbeth (Hand IV);
                            Merry Wives (Hand I); Othello (Hand VI); [Wilson's Belphegor
                        (main prompt hand)]HAND C:Hamlet (Hand II); Henry
                            VIII (Hand I); Macbeth (Hand II); Othello (Hand II); I Henry
                            IV (Hand II)HAND D:Macbeth (Hand III); Othello (Hand I)HAND E:Henry VIII (Hand II); Lear
                        (Hand II); Hamlet (?Hand V)HAND F:Othello (Hand V); I Henry
                            IV (Hand III)HAND G:Hamlet (Hand VI); Merry
                            Wives (Hand III, copyist); [Wilson's Belphegor (copyist)]HAND H:Hamlet (Hand IV); Lear
                        (Hand III); Midsummer Night's Dream (Hand II); Twelfth Night (Hand II); Merry
                            Wives (Hand II). This is an intrusive mid-eighteenth-century
                        hand. This listing leaves two major hands, each of which, so far as I can determine,
                    appears in only a single prompt-book: Hand I in Midsummer
                        Night's Dream and Hand I in Comedy of Errors.  Exact dates for the Smock Alley Shakespeare productions are unfortunately
                    impossible to arrive at. The presence of particular actors in certain of the
                    plays can be useful in setting date limits, but even such evidence may sometimes
                    be ambiguous, the addition of particular actors' names being possible at various
                    times after the first use of the prompt-book. With this warning, however, a few
                    tentative dates may be suggested. Julius Caesar, as we
                    noticed above, can be dated before 1677 and not earlier than 1670; Jeremiah
                    Lisle, who played the Cobble,[38] was not with the
                    Smock Alley players before 1670 and died in 1681, and Richards, who played
                    Brutus, left for the London stage in the summer of 1676.[39] Both Lisle and Richards also appear in the Smock Alley Night-Walker cast (which thus also falls between 1670
                    and 1676) but they do not appear by name in any of the other Shakespearean
                    productions. This fact would seem to suggest that the other productions are
                    later, but again the nature of the evidence may be somewhat misleading. For both
                        Julius Caesar and The
                        Night-Walker we have more or less complete casts; for the other
                    Shakespearean plays we have only occasional names attached to minor roles.
                    Richards, then, or even Lisle, may well have taken part in some of these other
                    plays; the fact that their names do not occur may simply mean that they did not
                    happen to double in a small  part (as Smith
                    probably did in Macbeth, for example) and so were not
                    particularly singled out for mention by the prompter. Even with this proviso,
                    however, it still seems likely that the other Shakespeare productions may be
                    grouped after the Julius Caesar cast.  The appearance of Henry Smith, who died in August, 1682, in Macbeth (Hand III) and Henry VIII (Hand I)
                    affords us a definite terminal date for these two plays, and the fact that Smith
                    is the only actor there named who also appears in the Julius
                        Caesar cast might be interpreted, always remembering the dangers
                    involved, as an indication of some lapse of time between these plays and the Julius Caesar production. It will be noted, however,
                    that Smith's name occurs in Macbeth in Hand III and may
                    be related to a second state of the prompt-book; in other words the prompt-book
                    may represent an earlier production with which Smith had no connection, a
                    production of the play essentially unaffected by the influence of D'Avenant's
                    version, an influence clearly reflected in the work of Hand III. The presence of
                    Totterdale in both Macbeth (Hand III) and Henry VIII (Hand I), though it links these plays with
                        Othello (Hand V), does not help in fixing an earlier
                    date limit, since, though he is absent from the Julius
                        Caesar cast, he is found in the contemporary, perhaps even earlier, Night-Walker cast. Clark[40] suggests a date between 1674 and 1682 for Macbeth; I would, on the whole, favor the later rather than the
                    earlier limits of this period for both Macbeth and Henry VIII.  Othello, which gives us a greater number of actors' names
                    than any of the other plays, the Julius Caesar cast
                    excepted, shares Walmesley (Hand V) with the Julius
                        Caesar cast and Totterdale (Hand V), as I noticed above, with Macbeth and Henry VIII. The
                    several new names (Trefusis, Freeman, Barnes, and Charles, all in Hand V)
                    suggest perhaps that we should place Othello after Macbeth and Henry VIII.
                    Unfortunately nothing is known about when any of these new names
                     first put in an appearance at Smock Alley,
                    though Freeman and Barnes figure in the Smock Alley cast of Wilson's Belphegor, a production which may be dated 1677-78 or
                        1682-83.[41] I would suggest 1680-82 as a
                    probable date for Othello.  The Hamlet prompt-book mentions Trefusis and possibly
                    Williams (both Hand VI). If the '&lt;W&gt;illian' who played Laertes was indeed
                    the David Williams who figures in the Julius Caesar
                    cast, we may claim a terminal date for this prompt-book in 1679, David Williams
                    having gone to London early in that year.[42] Nor
                    is the appearance here of Trefusis inconsistent with a date prior to 1679; we
                    know nothing of Trefusis' whereabouts before the early 1680's. An early limit
                    for the production is indicated by the strong influence throughout the text of
                    the 1676 actors' quarto of Hamlet. Thus we may, though
                    with proper hesitation, suggest a date between 1676 and 1679 for the Smock Alley
                        Hamlet.  Although the Smock Alley King Lear mentions no actors'
                    names, it is linked with the prompt-books already discussed by several prompt
                    hands and unquestionably belongs to the same general period. Since, however, it
                    gives evidence of influence from Tate's adaptation, it must be dated after 1681.  I Henry IV, of which only a fragment remains, must
                    certainly have been produced at Smock Alley some years before 1685, at which
                    date Baker, who played Falstaff, was well received on the London stage for his
                    performance in that role. The only name mentioned in the surviving half-leaf is
                    that of Longmore. It occurs twice: once as 'Longmo' and once as '&lt;&gt;more'
                    in a hand which I have called Hand II. Hand II links this prompt-book with Hamlet, Othello, Macbeth, and Henry VIII. Clark
                    on the evidence here of Longmore's name associates him, probably correctly, with
                    Smock Alley before 1685, although any references we have to him as a Smock Alley
                    actor date from the 1690's.[43] Using Baker's Falstaff again as an argument for dating, we may also place The Merry Wives prompt-book before 1685. Prompt hand links
                    with Hamlet, Othello, Macbeth, the Julius Caesar cast,
                    and Wilson's Belphegor also support a date in the late
                    '70's or early '80's.  The Smock Alley Twelfth Night also almost certainly
                    belongs to this same period. It contains no actors' names, but it is linked with
                        Hamlet, Lear, and Macbeth by a single prompt hand.  Three Smock Alley prompt-books remain: Comedy of Errors,
                        Midsummer Night's Dream, and Winter's Tale. None of them is strictly speaking a prompt-book and
                    none shows evidence of actual use in the theatre. The
                        Winter's Tale is simply an unfinished cutting (to IV.iv.442) with no
                    markings of any kind except rough circling for suggested deletions. The Comedy of Errors and Midsummer
                        Night's Dream, although they show signs of a good deal of careful
                    preparation, by heavy cutting and rewriting, contain no calls or other
                    prompter's notes. Nor can the reviser's hand in either be associated with any of
                    the revisers' or prompters' hands in the other Smock Alley prompt-books.  Certain general characteristics of the Smock Alley promptbooks may be noticed
                    here. (1) The usual first step in preparing a play for the stage seems to have
                    been a rough preliminary cutting. Such a step may be seen in the Smock Alley Winter's Tale, Midsummer Night's
                        Dream, and Comedy of Errors, none of which, at
                    least in their present form, ever reached production; the remains of this
                    initial cutting are also clearly marked in the Smock Alley Hamlet, and probably in Macbeth. But even in
                    this initial step differences in approach must be pointed out. The reviser who
                    worked on Winter's Tale did nothing except circle
                    passages for deletion (as did the first reviser, I believe, of Hamlet); the reviser of Comedy of
                        Errors, and particularly the reviser of Midsummer
                        Night's Dream, went much further, not only marking cuts but adding new
                    lines or rewriting speeches, and, in the case of Midsummer
                        Night's Dream, including scene settings. (2) The
                     order of events after the initial cutting
                    of the play is difficult to determine. In some cases, the initial cutting was
                    subjected to a thorough revision (as in Hamlet and
                    probably Macbeth). One hand usually seems to be
                    responsible for the advance calls; another hand for the indication of scene
                    settings (though in King Lear and Merry Wives the same hand is responsible for both). The calls
                    themselves are regularly anticipative, though at no set number of lines in
                    advance. They are, moreover, by character name, not as in the 'Nursery' Comedy of Errors, for example, by actor's name. Where
                    actors' names occur in the Smock Alley prompt-books they are always associated
                    with the character name and they appear only in very minor roles, probably where
                    some confusion might arise from doubling. No calls are made at the beginning of
                    an act. (3) Advance calls for the act break ('Act ready') occur regularly, and
                    in Othello the prompter's note 'ring' is used at the end
                    of the act to indicate the point at which the music should begin. (4) The symbol
                     to indicate 'whistle for a change of scene' appears only in Othello (I.iii; II.i, iv; IV.i; V.ii) and in the I Henry IV fragment (II.ii).[44] The Smock Alley Hamlet warns of a
                    change of scene by an advance call 'scean' about ten or twelve lines before a
                    change is necessary. (5) Point of entry is marked in three of the prompt-books
                    by a slanted and crossed line usually in the margin (Hamlet, Othello, I Henry
                        IV); the same symbol is also used in the 'Nursery' Comedy of Errors, the King's Company Sisters, and the unassigned Twelfth Night (mentioned in Group IV above). The
                    Shakespearean prompt-books do not use indications of the exact point from which
                    an actor enters, though such indications ('E.L.' = East Lower; 'W. up.' =West
                    Upper; 'W.L.'=West Lower; 'E upp'= East Upper) occur regularly in the
                    contemporary Smock Alley Belphegor MS prompt-book.[45] (6) Calls for special properties or sound
                    effects are usually in a hand (or hands) other than those responsible
                     for the scene notations and character
                    calls. The same is true of the sporadic appearance of actors' names; except in
                        Henry VIII, they are in a different hand from that
                    appearing in the character call to which the name is attached.  One of the most interesting aspects of the Smock Alley prompt-books is the record
                    they a: ford of the scenic resources of this company during the 1670's and early
                    '80's. Particular aspects of the scenery will be discussed in the separate
                    introductions to each play, but it will be useful here to give a complete list
                    of the scenes.[46] 'Anti-chamber', Othello, IV.ii; ? I Henry IV, II.iii'the baudy house', Midsummer Night's Dream,
                        I.ii'bed chamber', Hamlet, II.i; Othello, V.ii'Castle', Hamlet, I.i, I.iv, IV.vi; Macbeth, V.v; Othello, II.i, V.i'Caue', Macbeth, IV.i'Chamber', Hamlet, I.iii, II.i, III.iv, IV.ii,
                        IV.v; Lear, II.i, IV.v, V.vii; Macbeth, (III.iv); Merry Wives, III.iii,
                        III.iv; Othello, III.iv'Chamber without ye Bed', Merry
                            Wives, I.iv'Church', Hamlet, V.i.240'Court', Hamlet, I.ii, II.ii, IV.i, IV.iii, I' '.vii, (V.ii.236); Lear, I.i, II.ii, III.vii; Macbeth, I.ii, I.iv, 1 vi, III.i, III.iv, V.i; Othello, (IV.i); Twelfth Night, I.iii, I
                        iv, I.ii, III.i, III.iv, IV.ii, V.i'Forrest', I Henry IV, (II.ii); Midsummer Night's Dream, III.i, III.ii.345, IV.i,
                        (IV.i.106)'Garden', Macbeth, I.v, IV.ii'Great Forrest', Merry Wives, V.ii'Groue', Lear, III.i, IV.i, IV.vi, V.i; Macbeth, III.iii, V.iv; Merry
                            Wives, II.iii; Midsummer Night's Dream,
                        (III.i.206)'The little wood', Midsummer Night's Dream,
                        II.ii.34'new scaen', Hamlet, IV.ii, V.ii (probably refers
                        to change of scene)'new Grove', Midsummer Night's Dream, II.i, (III.i)'Pallace', Midsummer Night's Dream, I i; Othello, IV.i'Presence', Othello, I.iii, (IV.ii); Twelfth Night, I.i'Rock', Macbeth, I.i, I.iii, II.iv, III.v,
                        IV.i'ye Shipps', Othello,
                        II.i'Tauern', Merry Wives, I.iii, II.ii, III.v,
                        V.i'Towne', Hamlet, V.i, (V.ii); Macbeth, (II.iv), IV.iii, V.ii; Merry
                            Wives, I.i, II.i, III.i, III.ii; Othello,
                        I.i; Twelfth Night, I.ii, II.i, IV.i (also Belphegor, III.iv)'Wood', I Henry IV, II.ii'Worst Chamber', Merry Wives, (I.iii)[47] A full account of each of the Smock Alley prompt-books will be given in the
                    separate introduction to each play.  Group IV: Each of the five plays in this group offers
                    special problems of provenience, dating, etc., and will be dealt with in the
                    separate introductions.</field><field name="file_s">ShaIntP</field></doc></add>