<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><add><doc><field name="id">d1e2</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">header</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth
                                                 century, vol. 8  </field><field name="fulltext_t">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 8
                                   (The Merry Wives of Windsor) [a machine-readable transcription] Shakespeare, William Creation of machine-readable version: Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia Creation of digital images: Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.
                                   60 kilobytes University of Virginia Library. Charlottesville, Va. Bibliographic Society, ShaMWWP Publicly-accessible URL:
                                          http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/bsuva/promptbook/ 1997 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century The electronic text contains the Introduction and the Collations.
                                   The selected pages of the Prompt-Book included in this Volume
                                   have been rendered as images. Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth
                                                 century, vol. 8 William Shakespeare Editor G. Blakemore Evans Issued in portfolios. The prompt-books are reproduced
                                                 in collotype facsimile. Bibliographical Society of the University of
                                                 Virginia Charlottesville, VA 1996 Print copy consulted: First Edition provided by the
                                                 BSUVA Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century
                                          In Memoriam Fredson T. Bowers  Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
                                   Center. All quotation marks retained as data. All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
                                   trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line. The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
                                   for general use, and thumbnail GIFs. Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
                                   aid in establishing analytical groupings. Library of Congress Subject Headings  1960-1996 English drama; prose LCSH 24-bit color; 400 dpi  July 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Corrected transcriptional errors. May 1997 corrector Michele Ierardi, Electronic Text Center Added TEI header </field><field name="file_s">ShaMWWP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e139</field><field name="section_s">front</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth
                                                 century, vol. 8  </field><field name="fulltext_t">Image of the spine: Shakespearean Prompt-Books,
                                                 Vol. VIIIImage of the cover, part 1: Shakespearean
                                                 Prompt-Books, Vol. VIII: Ki! Henry VIII, The Merry
                                                 Wives of Windsor, Twelth Night, The Comedy of
                                                 Errors, The Winter's TaleImage of the titlepage, part 1: Shakespearean
                                                 Prompt-Books, Vol. VIII: King Lear, Henry VIII, The
                                                 Merry Wives of Windsor, Twelth Night, The Comedy of
                                                 Errors, The Winter's Tale   SHAKESPEAREAN PROMPT-BOOKS  of
                                          the SEVENTEENTH CENTURY  Vol. VIII King Lear, Henry
                                                 VIII,The Merry Wives of WindsorTwelfth Night, The Comedy of ErrorsThe Winter's TaleEdited byG. Blakemore Evans A Publication ofThe Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia
                                          Charlottesville1996 </field><field name="file_s">ShaMWWP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e193</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="section_s">introduction</field><field name="title_s"> Smock Alley The Merry Wives of WindsorThird Folio Introduction </field><field name="fulltext_t"> Smock Alley The Merry Wives of WindsorThird Folio Introduction  IN the absence of any actors' names in the Smock Alley prompt-book
                                   (PB) of The Merry Wives of Windsor, the presence of
                                   which can sometimes date a prompt-book within certain limits,
                                   what evidence there is for dating depends upon (1) handwriting
                                   links in the prompt notations with other Smock Alley prompt-books
                                   and (2) the probability that Francis Baker, -who was associated
                                   with Smock Alley from about 1670 to 1685 and who acted Falstaff
                                   in I and 2 Henry IV, also acted Sir John in
                                          Merry Wives.[1]  Three hands can be distinguished in the Wives PB. Hand I,
                                   which appears also in the Smock Alley Hamlet (Hand III;
                                   c. 1676-79), Macbeth (Hand IV; c.1774-82)
                                          Othello (Hand VI; c. 1677-78or 1682-83), the
                                   Smock Alley acting list for Julius Caesar (before
                                          1676),[2] and perhaps as the main
                                   prompt-hand in  John Wilson's
                                          Belphagor (probably 1677-78), a Smock Alley
                                   manuscript prompt-book now in the Folger Shakespeare Library (MS.
                                   V.b.109), is responsible for the prompt notations: scene
                                   settings, except probably two (I.ii and III.i), act and property
                                   notations, sound effects, advance character calls, added stage
                                   directions, resulting from the Third Folio's (F) use of "massed
                                          entries,"[3] almost certainly all
                                   textual cuts, textual changes, and a single four-word addition
                                   (I.iv.28). It is thus the only significant prompt-hand in the
                                          Wives PB. Hand II is the same intrusive
                                   eighteenth-century hand that appears in King Lear (Hand
                                   III), Hamlet (Hand IV), Midsummer Night's Dream
                                   (Hand II), and Twelfth Night (Hand II). Hand II emends
                                   the Folio text, at least for this play, by reference to a copy of
                                   Thomas Hanmer's edition of Shakespeare (Vol. I, 1744), a text
                                   that incorporates emended readings from Rowe, Pope, Theobald, and
                                   Hanmer himself. Two readings appear to be original with Hand II
                                   (see Textual changes, II.ii.142; V.V.107).[4] There is no reason to suppose that
                                   Hand II's alterations have any connection with Smock Alley or
                                   with the theatre. Hand III is found only in those pages
                                   transcribed from a copy of F2 (1632) prepared to replace two
                                   leaves of the Wives Third Folio text (sigs. E3 and E4;
                                   pages 53-56; III.v.89-IV.v.4), leaves that had somehow been lost
                                   or seriously defaced. The same hand, a large,
                                   professional-looking Italian script, appears again as the main
                                   scribal hand in the Smock Alley prompt-book of Wilson's
                                          Belphagor (see note 3) and in the Smock Alley
                                          Hamlet (Hand VI). Hand III's fifteen manuscript
                                   pages retain the Folio massed entries (see note 4) and contain no
                                   prompt notations, suggesting that the Wives PB was never
                                   used after the additional leaves were inserted. This would in
                                   turn seem to suggest that Hand III made his transcription only
                                   shortly before or after 1685, the year in which Baker, Smock
                                   Alley's Falstaff, left Smock Alley to join the United Company  in London, where,
                                   ironically, there is no record that he ever performed the
                                          role.[5]  If, then, we accept the probability that Baker played Falstaff in
                                   the Smock Alley productions of Merry Wives and that the
                                          Henry IV plays, in which we know he played
                                   Falstaff and which can be dated after 1675 and before 1685, were
                                   more likely to have been produced before Merry Wives at
                                   Smock Alley (as I Henry IV had been in London),[6] we may at least postulate date
                                   limits for the Wives PB as falling roughly within these
                                   same limits, though probably performed somewhat later than the
                                   first productions of I and 2 Henry IV. These
                                   suggested limits receive support from the dating of other Smock
                                   Alley prompt-books that share Hands I and III with the
                                          Wives PB and, as shown above, range in date from
                                   about 1674 to 1683.   The Wives PB is very lightly cut, only about fifty-two
                                   lines (including half-lines) being deleted, by circling, almost
                                   certainly by Hand I (compare his method of adjusting the F massed
                                   entries). Only Fenton's role is significantly cut (thirty-two
                                   lines), two cuts (II.i.52-53, 81-82) may represent some slight
                                   attempt at bowdlerizing, and all reference to the Garter ceremony
                                   (V.v. 67-77) has been omitted. Neither Hand I nor Hand III,
                                   however, makes any attempt to modernize syntax or substitute
                                   familiar for "hard" words, as happens in most of the other Smock
                                   Alley prompt-books.   W. S. Clark tells us that "The Merry Wives and Twelfth
                                          Night were as little cut for Dublin as for London
                                          performances."[7] If this was,
                                   indeed, true of London performances, it would help to explain why
                                   the Smock Alley Merry Wives (and Twelfth Night,
                                   only about ten lines) was so lightly cut, but I know of no
                                   evidence to substantiate such a statement. Certainly, later
                                   theatre texts are much more heavily cut (e.g., [1] as acted  at Drury Lane, in John
                                   Bell's Shakespeare's Plays, As they are now performed at the
                                          Theatres Royal in London, Vol. III, 1773; [2] as
                                   revised by John Philip Kemble and acted at Covent Garden,
                                          1804).[8] Both Bell and Kemble
                                   omit IV.i and IV.vi (Kemble also omits V.i) and cut other scenes
                                   quite considerably (see Textual cuts for further
                                   details). The Wives PB has been compared throughout with
                                   the above two theatre texts and, where possible, with John Dennis
                                          The Comical Gallant; or The Amours of Sir John
                                          Falstaffe (1702), an extensively reworked adaptation
                                   of The Merry Wives. Also compared are the Folger MS of
                                          Merry Wives[9] and the
                                   so-called Collier MS (the Perkins Folio [1632], now in the
                                   Huntington Library), which contains no textual cuts.   Four of the scene settings ('Town', 'Tauern', 'Chamber', 'The
                                   Groue') may be considered as stock, appearing in other Smock
                                   Alley Shakespeare productions,[10] but
                                   four other settings are found only in the Wives PB:
                                   'Clouset' (I.ii,), 'Worst Chamber' (canceled and replaced by
                                   'Tauern', I. iii), 'Chamber without ye Bed' (I.iv), and 'Great
                                   forres :' (V.iii). See Scene settings.   1. William Smith Clark, The Early Irish Stage: The
                                          Beginnings to 1720 (1955), pp. 75-76; Gunnar
                                   Sorelius, "The Smock Alley Prompt-Books of I and 2
                                          Henry IV," Shakespeare Quarterly, 22 (1971),
                                   123-124.   2. See General Introduction, Vol. I: Part i, pp. 17-18,
                                   of this series.   3. For a discussion of "massed entries" in the F text of
                                          Merry Wives and Hand I's solution to the problems
                                   the use of such entries raises, see Advance character
                                          calls and F stage directions altered (there
                                   treated as a single combined category).   4. Since in the Smock Alley Lear Hand II (there
                                   Hand III) makes use of Charles Jennens' edition of Lear
                                   ( 1770), he probably did not begin fiddling with these plays in
                                   the Smock Alley Third Folio (1663/64) until after 1770. One of
                                   Hand II's readings (see Textual changes, V.v.107) is
                                   found elsewhere only in the Collier MS, and perhaps a second (see
                                          Advance character calls, I.iv. 93, 112), though
                                   also found in Kemble, should be included in the same category. On
                                   the possibility that Collier may have known and used the Smock
                                   Alley folio, see Introduction to the Lear PB, note 5.   5. See the index to The London Stage 1660-1800,
                                   Part 1: 1660-1700 (ea. William Van Lennep, 1965), which lists all
                                   the roles Baker is known to have played in London.   6. Ibid., pp. 19-20. We are able to narrow the date
                                   limits from 1670-85 to 1675-85 because Joseph Trefusis who plays
                                   the 1. Carrier in I Henry IV, only began acting at Smock
                                   Alley about 1675 (see Clark, Irish Stage, pp. 77, 208).
                                          Pericles (season of 1659-60), Othello,
                                          I Henry IV, Merry Wives, Hamlet
                                   (season of 1660-61, and Twelfth Night (season of
                                   1661-62) were the earliest of Shakespeare's plays performed after
                                   the Restoration (The London Stage, pp. 7, cxxix).
                                   Although 2 Henry IV, like I Henry IV, was
                                   assigned to the King's Company in 1668-69, it does not seem to
                                   have been acted in London during the Restoration (see The
                                          London Stage, Index). For once Smock Alley struck out
                                   independently in matters Shakespearean.   7. Clark, Irish Stage, p 73.   8. Because Merry Wives is largely written in
                                   prose, comparative line-counts between the Wives PB and
                                   later theatre versions are only misleading.   9. G. Blakemore Evans, "The Merry Wives of Windsor: The
                                   Folger Manuscript," in Shakespeare: Text, Language,
                                          Criticism: Essays in Honour of Marvin Spevack, ed.
                                   Bernhard Fabian and Kurt Tetzeli von Rosador (1987), pp.57-79.   10. See General Introduction, Vol. I: Part i, pp. 23-24,
                                   of this series. </field><field name="file_s">ShaMWWP</field></doc></add>