<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><add><doc><field name="id">d1e381</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n1</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">1. See the General Introduction in the first volume of this series
                    (I,i,16). I would like to thank Mr. C. P. Finlayson, Keeper of Manuscripts,
                    Edinburgh University Library, for his kindness in checking various ink shades on
                    the last page of the Smock Alley Macbeth.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e383</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n2</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">2. The Smock Alley Hamlet was published as Vol. IV (1966) of
                    this series.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e388</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n3</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">3. R.C. Bald ("Shakespeare on the Stage in Restoration Dublin,"
                        PMLA, LVI [1941], 369) was thus slightly misleading when he wrote:
                    "The four missing leaves in Macbeth were discovered mounted in a large portfolio
                    as item 233 of the Shakespearean Rarities preserved at Hollingbury
                    Copse." This find did not complete the Smock Alley Macbeth.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e399</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n4</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">4. Bald, pp. 371-372; W. S. Clark, The Early Irish Stage
                    (Oxford, 1955), p. 75.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e404</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n5</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">5. Clark, p. 208. Totterdale also appears in the Smock Alley cast for
                    Fletcher's Night-Walker (see Allan Stevenson, "The Case of the
                    Decapitated Cast," SQ, VI [1955], 285-286). Stevenson notes that
                    Totterdale had a son baptized at St. John's in Dublin in November, 1675. He also
                    notes (p. 289) that Mrs. Elizabeth Farlowe or Farlee was a member of the King's
                    company. She disappears from the London stage after April, 1678 (see The
                        London Stage, Part I, ed. William Van Lennep [Carbondale, 1965], p. 15
                        et passim) . It is possible, though not, I think, very likely, that
                    Mrs. Farlowe played the role of the Servant. If so, this would place the date of
                    the Smock Alley production between 1678 and 1682.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e418</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n6</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">6. Bald, p. 373.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e420</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n7</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">7. See the General Introduction (I,i,14-15).</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e422</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n8</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">8. Although Hand V does not appear to be the same as the eighteenth
                    century hand which occurs in the Smock Alley Twelfth Night,
                        Hamlet, King Lear, Midsummer Night's Dream, and
                        Merry Wives, I do not believe that Hand V's changes predate Pope's
                    edition. The isolation of the readings in two scenes (I.i and ii) is extremely
                    suspicious.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e440</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n9</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">9. See my analysis of the Douai manuscript, "The Douai Manuscript--Six
                    Shakespearean Transcripts (1694-95)," in Charles B. Woods and Curt A. Zimansky,
                    eds., Studies in English Drama Presented to Baldwin Maxwell (Iowa City,
                    1962), pp. 158-172.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e445</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n10</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">10. See George W. Stone, "Garrick's Handling of Macbeth,"
                        SP, XXXVIII (1941), 609-628. Professor Stone's article also
                    contains some comments on later eighteenth-century stage versions.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e453</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n11</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">11. The Lee-Salmon prompt-book is used by permission of the Harvard
                    College Library. The 1734 Tonson edition of Macbeth is taken from
                    Theobald's 1733 text and shows no connection with the theatre. An edition of
                        Macbeth published in 1785 (with casts for that year at Drury Lane
                    and Covent Garden) reproduces essentially the Garrick version as it appears in
                    Bell (1773).</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e461</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n12</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">12. Bald, p. 373.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e463</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n13</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">13. See the Introduction to the Smock Alley Hamlet
                    (IV,i,4-5).</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e468</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n14</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">14. The figures given for the cutting by Hands II, III, and IV are
                    necessarily tentative, since, frequently, the only clue to which hand is at work
                    is the color of the ink used in the marks of deletion--a dangerous criterion. I
                    have included a cut as belonging to a particular hand even when I have felt it
                    necessary to query the attribution.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e470</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n15</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">15. It may be noted that a somewhat similar situation exists in the
                    Smock Alley Hamlet. There is, however, some slight evidence that,
                    despite the inaccuracies of Hand II's changes when compared with the so called
                    actors' quarto (1676), an actual copy of the printed text of that quarto was
                    used to some degree.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e475</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n16</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">16. I have used Alfred Hart's figure of 2,084 lines for Macbeth ("The
                    Number of Lines in Shakespeare's Plays," RES, VIII [1932], 21).
                    D'Avenant's version runs to roughly 2,124 lines; Padua PB to 1,808; Douai MS to
                    1,888; Garrick (Bell) to 1,846; Lee to 1,857; Lee-Salmon to 1,826. The figure of
                    352 lines cut in the Smock Alley Macbeth as given in my General Introduction
                    (I,i,27) was a careless error.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e480</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n17</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">17. Compare the illustration by du Guernier to Macbeth (IV.i) in
                    Rowe's 1709 edition (actually it represents a scene from D'Avenant's version),
                    the famous painting by Zoffany of Garrick in the role of Macbeth (II.i), and
                    Dawes' painting (IV.i). See W. M. Merchant, Shakespeare and the Artist
                    (Oxford, 1959), pp. 53, 58-59.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e485</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">note_n18</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">18. See the General Introduction (I,i,23-24).</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e189</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">introduction</field><field name="title_s">Introduction Smock Alley Macbeth Third Folio</field><field name="fulltext_t">Introduction Smock Alley Macbeth Third Folio THE Smock Alley prompt-book of Macbeth has suffered a somewhat adventurous
                    career. After the play was separated from the original copy of the Third Folio
                    (1664) by Halliwell Phillipps, [1] four pages (pp. 711,
                    sig. 3O4; 714 [misnumbered], sig. 3O6V; 719, sig. 3P3; 722,
                    sig. 3P4V) were exhibited in the "Rustic Wigwam" at
                    Hollingbury Copse, Brighton, and the last page of the play (p. 729, sig. 3Q2)
                    was eventually bound up with the Smock Alley Hamlet, the first page of
                        Hamlet (p. 730, sig. 3Q2V) being the verso of
                    the last page of Macbeth. [2] All but the last page
                    found their way to the Folger Shakespeare Library, where they were reassembled.
                        [3] The last page has only recently come to light
                    with the discovery of the Smock Alley Hamlet prompt book in the
                    Halliwell Phillipps collection of the University of Edinburgh Library. All these
                    leaves unfortunately bear the marks of their exhibition: wavy ink lines running
                    vertically through the text on the side of the leaf not intended for exhibition.
                    The damage to the last page of Macbeth is especially heavy (see below, pp. 6-7)
                    and indicates that the first page of Hamlet was also exhibited at some
                    stage in its history, probably at Hollingbury Copse.
                     Professor R. C. Bald's identification of 'Smyth' (Hand III), who plays Seyton in
                    V.iii, with the Smock Alley actor Henry Smith who died in 1682 sets a definite
                    date after which what may be considered as probably the first acted form of the
                    Smock Alley prompt book cannot have been prepared. [4]
                    The only other actors named are John Totterdale (at V.v.8, Hand III), who also
                    played in Henry VIII and Othello, and 'farlow' (at III.i.22, 101-104, Hand ?III
                    ). Nothing further is certainly known of Farlow, but Totterdale seems to have
                    been acting in Dublin from about 1674 to 1688. [5]
                    Totterdale's name, therefore, would seem to suggest an early limit of about 1674
                    for this form of the prompt book. Further possible narrowing of the two limits
                    (1674 and 1682) will be discussed later.  It is possible, as Professor Bald points out, [6] to
                    distinguish what appear to be three layers in the prompt markings and four
                    principal hands. Hand I (which appears as Hand I in Hamlet,
                        Lear, and Twelfth Night and as Hand II in I Henry
                        IV) does nothing but mark the scene settings. Hand II, probably the
                    earliest of the prompt hands, indicates the characters to be called and seems
                    responsible for much of the cutting and occasional textual changes. It appears
                    again as Hand II in Hamlet and Othello and is perhaps the same
                    hand responsible for the Julius Caesar couplet. [7] Hand III, another prompt hand and the same as Hand I in
                        Othello, marks a second stage in the preparation of the play and is
                    largely associated with bringing the performance, as originally outlined by Hand
                    II, into closer conformity with certain aspects of D'Avenant's version of
                    Macbeth (published 1674), particularly in III.iii, IV.i, and V.viii. Hand IV, a
                    peculiarly coarse and heavily formed hand, occasionally makes changes in Hand
                    III's notations, cuts a few lines, supplies prompt notes on off-stage effects,
                    and tidies up generally. It occurs also in Hamlet (Hand III), Merry Wives (Hand I),
                        Othello (Hand VI), and the Julius Caesar acting list and
                    is the principal prompt hand in the Smock Alley Belphegor manuscript
                    prompt-book. It is also possible to distinguish a fifth hand (Hand V) in
                    connection with a few textual emendations near the beginning of the play which
                    appear to be echoes of Pope's text (1723). [8] What
                    seem to be other hands occur occasionally, but I have been unable to associate
                    them with any of the hands in the other Smock Alley prompt-books. In the
                    collation which follows all changes and additions and most deletions are either
                    assigned to one of the five hands listed above (sometimes with a query) or
                    marked as by an unidentified hand. The attempt to determine the hands
                    responsible for the deletions (by circling, crossing through, and
                    criss-crossing) is based on a study of the various inks usually associated with
                    a particular hand. There is, of course, considerable danger in this method, and
                    I have tried to indicate those cases where the evidence seemed especially
                    ambiguous.  In the collation I have compared the Smock Alley Macbeth with the following stage
                    or stage related versions: (1) the Padua prompt-book (see Volume 1 of this
                    series; referred to as Padua PB); (2) Sir William D'Avenant's adaptation, 1674
                    (edited by Christopher Spencer in Five Restoration Adaptations of
                        Shakespeare, Urbana, 1965; referred to as D'Avenant) and the Yale
                    manuscript of D'Avenant's adaptation (edited by Christopher Spencer,
                        D'Avenant's "Macbeth" from the Yale Manuscript, New Haven, 1961;
                    referred to as Yale MS, but not included in the collation unless differing
                    significantly from the 1674 printed text). (3) The Douai manuscript, 1694 (in
                    the Douai Public Library, MS 7.87, fols. 171-209; referred to as Douai MS).[9] (4) The Garrick version, 1744 (in Bell's
                        Shakespeare, 1773, Vol. I; referred to as Bell).[10] (5) The John Lee version, Edinburgh, 1753 (referred to as Lee);
                    (6) The Lee Edward Salmon prompt-book  (in a
                    copy of the 1753 edition, now in the Harvard Theatre Collection, marked by
                    Edward Salmon, the prompter, and belonging to West Digges, who played the role
                    of Macbeth in Edinburgh on 26 December 1757; referred to as Lee Salmon PB, but
                    only where it differs from Lee). [11] I have also
                    included the cuts indicated in the Collier Perkins Second Folio, 1632 (referred
                    to as Collier MS).  Two distinct versions of Macbeth emerge from the work of Hands II and III. Hand
                    II seems to have blocked the play out, making a few verbal changes (I.iii.120,
                    145-146; I.vi.9; III.i. 16-17, 28), marking certain passages or scenes (III.vi,
                    V.ii) for cutting, a total of roughly 163 lines, and writing in the prompt calls
                    for the characters. He regularly omits the characters of Angus and Lennox,
                    except for one occasion each (V.i.63-64 and IV.ii. 125), when they were
                    inadvertently, I think, included. In the General Introduction to this series
                    (I,i,19) I suggested, following R. C. Bald, [12] that
                    Hand II's version may represent the original form in which Smock Alley played
                    Macbeth. This view I no longer consider seriously tenable. It is much more
                    likely that Hand II's version represents a preliminary draft for prompt use and
                    that this "prepared book" was then taken over by Hand III and further adapted
                    for the stage with additional emphasis on D'Avenant's version. An analogous
                    situation may be found in the Smock Alley Hamlet, where, I have
                    suggested, possibly the same hand (Hand II) performed essentially the same kind
                    of preliminary spadework. [13] Hand III initiates less cutting than Hand II (roughly 127 lines as compared with
                    some 163),[14] although in a number of cases he
                    reinforces Hand II's suggested cuts by further marks of deletion. On the other
                    side, his individual textual revisions are much more numerous, particularly in
                    III.iii, IV.i, and V.viii, scenes in which D'Avenant's influence is particularly
                    marked. Hand II's  few verbal changes suggest
                    some vague knowledge of D'Avenant, and his cuts sometimes parallel those in
                    D'Avenant's version. Hand III's changes, however, quite apart from the three
                    scenes noted above, reflect a closer recollection of D'Avenant's wording,
                    although almost invariably with slight verbal inaccuracies or changes. This
                    strongly suggests that Hand III worked from memory, without having a text of
                    D'Avenant's version to consult.[15] Such a view might
                    be considered one reason why the Third Folio text was employed as a prompt-book.
                    But all the Smock Alley productions of Shakespeare used the Third Folio text as
                    a source for the prompt-book. It is, moreover, conceivable that the company
                    preferred Shakespeare's basic text, using D'Avenant only in those scenes (the
                    murder of Banquo and the handling of the Apparitions) where his revision did not
                    interfere materially with the original. A somewhat similar case occurs in the
                    Smock Alley King Lear, in which Shakespeare's text is used until V.ii,
                    at which point some form of Tate's happy ending appears to have been tacked on.  The suggested absence of a printed text of D'Avenant's version, first published
                    in 1674 but performed as early as 1664, may also be advanced as an argument for
                    placing the Smock Alley production of Macbeth at the earliest possible
                    date--Totterdale's advent in the company in 1674. If, indeed, a printed copy of
                    D'Avenant's text was literally not available, this would explain the apparent
                    reliance of Hands II and III on recollections of the London performances. While
                    an early limit (1674) must be allowed as a possibility, I still incline to the
                    opinion I expressed in the General Introduction to this series (I,i,19): between
                    1674 and 1682, with some preference for a later rather than an earlier date.  Hand IV seems certainly to be the latest of the main prompt hands. Although it is
                    principally concerned with prompt notations, particularly off-stage effects or
                    special business, e.g., I.iii.3-4; II.iv.10-13, 21; III.ii.22-23; III.iii
                    (opening); III.v (opening and end); V.vii (opening), it makes a few cuts (about
                    38 lines, limited to IV.iii, V.iii, V.iv, and V.viii), one change of scene
                    (IV.i), and occasional verbal substitutions ( IV.iii.8,
                     123, 191-192; V.v.11). Hand IV also restores
                    Folio 'Rosse' for Hand III's'Macduffe' in I.ii.45 s.d. and I.iii.88 s.d. (from
                    D'Avenant) and Folio 'Saward' for Hand III's 'Rosse' in V.vii.4 s.d. (D'Avenant,
                    'Lennox'). There is, I believe, some evidence to suggest that Hand IV worked on
                    the prompt-book at two different times. The changes made in Hand III's notations
                    and some other notations are written in a faded black-brown ink, while those
                    calls which seem merely to tidy up Hand III's work are generally in a light
                    brown ink. It seems possible, therefore, that some of Hand IV's changes may
                    reflect a somewhat later version of the play. But the evidence is tenuous,
                    sometimes uncertain, and resists any definite conclusion.  It is difficult to give a very satisfactory account of the total number of lines
                    cut in the Smock Alley Macbeth. But as the play finally emerged under
                    Hand IV about 328 lines seem to have been deleted from the original and about
                    five lines, which do not merely substitute for deletions (see III.iii.11-22;
                    V.vii.11; V.viii.32-34), added. Also probably another twenty lines (the second
                    (?) song from D'Avenant's version called for in II.iv.10-13, 21) must be
                    included as an addition. All this leaves a production of about 1,781 lines,
                    somewhat shorter than the Padua PB, D'Avenant, Douai MS, Garrick, Lee, and
                    Lee-Salmon versions.[l6] The principal cuts are as
                    follows: II.iii.5-23, 28 ('of three . . .')-46 (the Porter scene); III.vi (the
                    scene of comment between Lennox and a Lord); IV.ii.30-64, 79-85 (the last part
                    of the scene of Lady Macduff's murder); IV.ii.117-123 ('Devilish . . .
                    detraction.'), 125-137 ('I am . . . Quarrel.'), 139 s.d.-159 (' . . . Grace. ')
                    (parts of the Malcolm Macduff interview); and V.ii (scene of comment by
                    Macbeth's enemies).  The final scene (V.viii) requires special comment. This scene occurs on the last
                    page of Macbeth (p. 729, sig. 3Q2 ) and has been defaced by the
                    nineteenth-century exhibitor. In addition to double verticle lines down each
                    column, two of Hand II's advance calls, Hand III's added lines at the bottom of
                    the page, the running title, and the catchword have been crossed through, each
                    with a single pen stroke. All these deletions must, I think,
                     be "credited" to the vandal exhibitor. They
                    are made more neatly, if that is a virtue, than the usual run of deletions in
                    this prompt-book. If this explanation is accepted, the general intention in the
                    final scene is clear enough, although the cutting in lines 35-53 is somewhat
                    confusing. Even so, however, the scene as here developed does nothing to clear
                    up the difficulty in the Folio text as to where Macbeth dies, on- or off-stage.
                    Here, as in the Folio, he seems to die on-stage, with a line lifted from
                    D'Avenant's version of the scene in which he does indeed die on-stage. At this
                    point, Macduff, with a line original to the Smock Alley prompt-book 'Soe may all
                    tyrants fall.' exits, re-entering immediately after the entrance of Malcolm,
                    Siward, Ross, etc. (lines 35-53 being cut) with Macbeth's head. Unless he cuts
                    it off before exiting, where does Macduff get the head? At best this suggests an
                    awkward bit of stage business, all the more surprising in the Smock Alley
                    production in view of D'Avenant's handling of the matter, by more decorously
                    substituting Macbeth's sword, which Macduff takes from the dying Macbeth just
                    before his exit and produces triumphantly on his re-entry some lines later. Was
                    the taste of an Irish audience more Elizabethan than Augustan?  In a number of instances the changes made in the Smock Alley prompt-book parallel
                    those found both in the earlier Padua prompt-book and in eighteenth-century
                    productions; all such parallels are recorded in the running notes to the
                    collation. It should be noticed, however, that the attitude here dictating the
                    cutting in the Porter scene differs from that at work in the Padua prompt-book.
                    In Smock Alley "decorum" and D'Avenant are pretty clearly responsible, although
                    I do not believe that there is otherwise much evidence of a desire to "refine"
                    Macbeth except in the matter of language. As usual in Restoration versions
                    (contrast the Padua prompt-book), Shakespeare's diction and syntax have been
                    simplified, sometimes, but not always, with the aid of D'Avenant (e.g.,
                    I.iii.55-57, 120, 145-146; II.iii.131-133; II.iv.40; III.i.16-17, 110;
                    III.iv.60, 75, 103, 105, 106; IV.i.69, 90, 92-94; IV.ii.75; IV.iii.8, 133,
                    191-192; V.iv.11; V.Viii.14, 32-34), or "poetic" passages simply deleted (e.g.,
                    I.iii.125-126, 137-142; I.vi.3-9; I.vii.2-12; II.iii.135-138; III.i.122-126;
                    IV.iii.117-123, 125-137, 171-173). The desire to clarify what seemed involved,
                    difficult, or obsolete accounts for a large number of the changes and cuts, and
                    sometimes the poetic quality of the play 
                    suffers though considerably less so than in D'Avenant's "flattened" adaptation.  Two further points may be mentioned. Hand III's importation of Banquo into II.iv
                    in the place of the Old Man is so far as I know unique to the Smock Alley
                    production. His presence there may perhaps be explained by the implied inclusion
                    of the Witches in Hand IV's call for a song and dance at lines 4-5 and 10-13,
                    since Banquo would be a more suitable spectator for this extra effect than an
                    anonymous Old Man. In V.iii.36, 48, and V.v.51-52, Hand IV deletes the
                    references to Macbeth's armor (missing, however, the first one at V.iii.33-34),
                    and Hand III cuts the reference to his shield at V.viii.32-34. Such deletions
                    point to a costuming of Macbeth more in keeping with Restoration military dress
                    than with Shakespeare's conception, a view borne out by several
                    eighteenth-century theatrical paintings and engravings.[17] The scenes employed in the Smock Alley Macbeth are for the most part stock: Court
                    (I.ii,iv,vi; III.i,iv; V.i), Towne (II.iv,deleted; IV.iii; V.ii), Groue
                    (III.iii; V.iv), Castle (V.v), and Chamber (II.i; III.iv, deleted). These scenes
                    all appear in other Smock Alley plays,[18] but three
                    scenes are found only in Macbeth: Rock (I.i,iii; II.iv; III.v; IV.i, deleted),
                    Garden (I.v; IV.ii), and Caue (IV.i). The 'Rock' scene is regularly associated
                    with the Witches and must have been specially prepared for this play. It is
                    possible that the 'Caue' scene substituted by Hand IV in IV.i represents a
                    refinement introduced at perhaps some later date. The only setting which raises
                    any particular question is the use of 'Towne' for the interview between Malcolm
                    and Macduff (IV.iii), a scene which according to Shakespeare's text is supposed
                    to take place at the court of Edward the Confessor in England. Possibly some
                    slight influence of the unity of place may be detected here and in D'Avenant,
                    who, curiously enough, sets the scene in Birnam Wood. 1. See the General Introduction in the first volume of this series
                    (I,i,16). I would like to thank Mr. C. P. Finlayson, Keeper of Manuscripts,
                    Edinburgh University Library, for his kindness in checking various ink shades on
                    the last page of the Smock Alley Macbeth. 2. The Smock Alley Hamlet was published as Vol. IV (1966) of
                    this series. 3. R.C. Bald ("Shakespeare on the Stage in Restoration Dublin,"
                        PMLA, LVI [1941], 369) was thus slightly misleading when he wrote:
                    "The four missing leaves in Macbeth were discovered mounted in a large portfolio
                    as item 233 of the Shakespearean Rarities preserved at Hollingbury
                    Copse." This find did not complete the Smock Alley Macbeth. 4. Bald, pp. 371-372; W. S. Clark, The Early Irish Stage
                    (Oxford, 1955), p. 75. 5. Clark, p. 208. Totterdale also appears in the Smock Alley cast for
                    Fletcher's Night-Walker (see Allan Stevenson, "The Case of the
                    Decapitated Cast," SQ, VI [1955], 285-286). Stevenson notes that
                    Totterdale had a son baptized at St. John's in Dublin in November, 1675. He also
                    notes (p. 289) that Mrs. Elizabeth Farlowe or Farlee was a member of the King's
                    company. She disappears from the London stage after April, 1678 (see The
                        London Stage, Part I, ed. William Van Lennep [Carbondale, 1965], p. 15
                        et passim) . It is possible, though not, I think, very likely, that
                    Mrs. Farlowe played the role of the Servant. If so, this would place the date of
                    the Smock Alley production between 1678 and 1682. 6. Bald, p. 373. 7. See the General Introduction (I,i,14-15). 8. Although Hand V does not appear to be the same as the eighteenth
                    century hand which occurs in the Smock Alley Twelfth Night,
                        Hamlet, King Lear, Midsummer Night's Dream, and
                        Merry Wives, I do not believe that Hand V's changes predate Pope's
                    edition. The isolation of the readings in two scenes (I.i and ii) is extremely
                    suspicious. 9. See my analysis of the Douai manuscript, "The Douai Manuscript--Six
                    Shakespearean Transcripts (1694-95)," in Charles B. Woods and Curt A. Zimansky,
                    eds., Studies in English Drama Presented to Baldwin Maxwell (Iowa City,
                    1962), pp. 158-172. 10. See George W. Stone, "Garrick's Handling of Macbeth,"
                        SP, XXXVIII (1941), 609-628. Professor Stone's article also
                    contains some comments on later eighteenth-century stage versions. 11. The Lee-Salmon prompt-book is used by permission of the Harvard
                    College Library. The 1734 Tonson edition of Macbeth is taken from
                    Theobald's 1733 text and shows no connection with the theatre. An edition of
                        Macbeth published in 1785 (with casts for that year at Drury Lane
                    and Covent Garden) reproduces essentially the Garrick version as it appears in
                    Bell (1773). 12. Bald, p. 373. 13. See the Introduction to the Smock Alley Hamlet
                    (IV,i,4-5). 14. The figures given for the cutting by Hands II, III, and IV are
                    necessarily tentative, since, frequently, the only clue to which hand is at work
                    is the color of the ink used in the marks of deletion--a dangerous criterion. I
                    have included a cut as belonging to a particular hand even when I have felt it
                    necessary to query the attribution. 15. It may be noted that a somewhat similar situation exists in the
                    Smock Alley Hamlet. There is, however, some slight evidence that,
                    despite the inaccuracies of Hand II's changes when compared with the so called
                    actors' quarto (1676), an actual copy of the printed text of that quarto was
                    used to some degree. 16. I have used Alfred Hart's figure of 2,084 lines for Macbeth ("The
                    Number of Lines in Shakespeare's Plays," RES, VIII [1932], 21).
                    D'Avenant's version runs to roughly 2,124 lines; Padua PB to 1,808; Douai MS to
                    1,888; Garrick (Bell) to 1,846; Lee to 1,857; Lee-Salmon to 1,826. The figure of
                    352 lines cut in the Smock Alley Macbeth as given in my General Introduction
                    (I,i,27) was a careless error. 17. Compare the illustration by du Guernier to Macbeth (IV.i) in
                    Rowe's 1709 edition (actually it represents a scene from D'Avenant's version),
                    the famous painting by Zoffany of Garrick in the role of Macbeth (II.i), and
                    Dawes' painting (IV.i). See W. M. Merchant, Shakespeare and the Artist
                    (Oxford, 1959), pp. 53, 58-59. 18. See the General Introduction (I,i,23-24).  &lt;/page&gt;   &lt;page n=9&gt; </field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e497</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div1_introduction</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">THE act, scene, and line numbering is that of the standard Globe text (1911
                        ed.). Angle brackets are used to indicate (1) missing words or letters; (2)
                        illegible words or letters; (3) doubtful or conjectural readings. The
                        following abbreviations are employed:Bell .......................................... Garrick's acting
                            version of Macbeth as printed in Bell's Shakespeare
                            (1773), Vol. ICollier MS .................................... the Collier Perkins
                            Second Folio (1632), now in the Huntington LibraryD'Avenant ..................................... D'Avenant's adaptation
                            of Macbeth (1674)Douai MS ...................................... manuscript copy of
                                Macbeth contained in Douai Public Library MS 7.87 (1694),
                            fols. 171-209F.............................................. here used for Third
                            Folio (1664)Lee ........................................... John Lee's acting
                            version of Macbeth, Edinburgh (1753)Lee-Salmon PB ................................. copy of the Edinburgh
                            (1753) edition with the prompt markings of Edward Salmon, now in the
                            Harvard Theatre CollectionPB ............................................ Smock Alley
                                Macbeth prompt-book, now in the Folger Shakespeare
                            LibraryPadua PB ...................................... Padua Macbeth
                            prompt-book, now in the University of Padua LibraryYale MS ....................................... manuscript copy of
                            D'Avenant's version of Macbeth, now in the Yale University
                            Library[In the lower left margin of p. 711 (sig. 3O3), running vertically, Hand ?II
                        has written Brutus' concluding couplet as it appears in the so called Dryden
                        D'Avenant version of Julius Caesar: 'poore slavish rome far well: Ceaser now
                        be still / I Kild not thee wth. half so good a will
                        Dye'. The Smock Alley PB of Julius Caesar has not survived, and the
                        problems raised by the appearance of the couplet here may be found discussed
                        in the General Introduction to this series, I,i,14-15.]</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e554</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div1_act</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">I.I.i.Image of prompt-book page 711(opening) Rock] Hand I. This setting is
                            regularly associated with the appearance of the Witches by Hand I,
                            though Hand IV substitutes 'Caue' in IV.i. Bell, Lee: 'an open
                                Place' (after Theobald); Lee adds '[Stage dark.]'.6 King &amp;c.] Hand II. This is the only
                            example of such a generalized prompt call in this PB.7 There I go to meet] Hand V interlines 'I go',
                            with a caret, above F 'to'. So Pope, Bell; D'Avenant reads: 'There we
                            resolve to meet'; Lee, 'There we'll go to meet'.I.ii.(opening s.d.) Donalbaine, with
                                attendants] Hand ?II deletes F 'Lenox,'
                            following 'Donalbaine,'. PB omits Lennox throughout. D'Avenant,
                            Lee substitute Seyton for the F 'bleeding Captain'.1 Court] Hand I. Part of the Julius
                                Caesar couplet has been written over 'Court'. Bell, Lee: 'a
                                Palace at Foris' (after Theobald, Rowe); Lee adds '[Stage
                                light.]'.7 Doubtful long] Hand V interlines 'long', with
                            a caret, after F 'Doubtful'. So Pope, Bell, Lee; D'Avenant reads: 'It
                            was doubtful ;' for F 'Doubtful . . . stood,'.11-15 Rosse. [crossed through by Hand III] /
                                macduffe [crossed through by Hand IV] / Rosse] Hands
                            II, III, IV. See below, 45 s.d.15 all too] Hand ?V crosses through 's' in F
                            'all's too'. So Pope, Bell, Lee; D'Avenant rewrites 14-15.26 break] Hand ?V crosses through 'ing' in F
                            'breaking'. So Pope, Bell; D'Avenant, Lee rewrite the passage.38 So they redoubled stroaks upon] Hand ?V
                            deletes F 'doubly' and interlines 'up', with a caret, above F 'on'
                            ('vpon' F1 ) . So Pope, Bell, Lee; D'Avenant rewrites 36-41; Douai MS
                            reads: 'for doubly they redoubled stroakes on'.41 I cannot tell:] Crossed through (Hand
                            ?II).45 s.d.] Hand II first deletes F 'and
                            Angus.'; next Hand III deletes F 'Enter Rosse' and writes above
                            F s.d. 'Enter Macduffe'; this in turn is deleted by Hand IV, which then
                            restores 'Rosse', following deleted F s.d., but neglects to restore
                                'Enter' (compare the prompt call at 11-15, above) . In
                            substituting Macduff for Ross, Hand III was following D'Avenant, who
                            completely omits the characters of Ross and Angus from his version of
                            the play. PB cuts the character of Angus throughout, though Hand II
                            inadvertently included his name in the prompt call (later cancelled) for
                            V.ii. Lee retains Angus, but Lee-Salmon PB deletes him here and
                            elsewhere; both retain Ross. Gentleman (Bell) remarks that at Covent
                            Garden the "characters of Rosse and Angus have been
                            judicially blended . . . into those of Macduff and Lenox, to make them
                            more worthy the attention of good performers and the audience"; Drury
                            Lane, however, with Garrick, retained all four characters.45 Thane of Rosse. [crossed
                                    through] Macduffe [crossed through]] Hand
                            III first crosses through F 'Thane of Rosse.' and writes
                            'Macduffe', but Hand IV, after deleting 'Macduffe', fails to restore
                            Ross. Something (perhaps 'Ma') has been written in the extreme right
                            margin opposite Hand III's 'Macduffe', but the leaf has been shaved.
                            D'Avenant substitutes 'Noble Macduff!'.46-47 Lenox. Whathast . . . strange.]
                            Circled (Hand II). This deletion of Lennox's speech follows the deletion
                            of Lennox in the opening s.d. D'Avenant, Bell, Lee omit 47.47, 48, 58, 66 macd] Hand III deletes F
                                'Rosse.' and substitutes 'macd' or (66) 'Macd'. Although
                            Hand IV removes Macduff from the scene, the altered speech prefixes
                            remain uncancelled. Compare V.vii.5,6,8,10.48 worthy Thane? [crossed through] braue
                                Mac&lt;duffe&gt; [crossed through]] Hand III deletes
                            F 'worthy Thane?' and supplies 'braue Mac&lt;duffe&gt;'
                            following it; Hand IV then deletes 'braue Mac&lt;duffe&gt;'. No attempt
                            is made to restore the original F reading. D'Avenant retains 'worthy
                                Thane?'; so, too, Bell, Lee.50 Witches] Hand 11.53 gan] 'be' of F 'began' crossed through by
                            Hand ?V. So Pope, Bell, Lee. D'Avenant substitutes 'long
                            maintain'd'.I.iii.Image of prompt-book page 712(opening) &lt;Ro&gt;ck] Hand I. Bell, Lee:
                                'a Heath' (after Rowe). Lee adds '[Stage dark.]'.
                            D'Avenant brings on the 'Witches flying'; Lee-Salmon PB,
                            interpreting the 'Witches rise again' in Lee, precedes the
                            scene with: `x Ring for 3 Traps to rais Witches / Stage Dark /
                            Thunder Lightning &amp; Rain'; in Bell the Witches 'rise from under the
                            stage.'.3-4 drum / Redy] Hand IV. A warning note for F
                                'Drum within.' at 29. Lee-Salmon PB gives no advance call
                            for the drum at 29, although it keeps the F s.d. in the form of '
                                [Drum heard within.]'. It does, however, call for 'Drum /
                            ready' at 35 in preparation for Macbeth's and Banquo's entry to a
                            'Scotch Ma&lt;rch&gt;'.11-13 Macbeth / Banquo.] Hand 11. For the
                            entry at 37 D'Avenant adds 'Attendants' and Bell 'A
                                March.... Soldiers and other Attendants' (after Rowe); Lee adds
                            only 'A march beat.', but the Lee-Salmon PB notes in its call for
                            Macbeth and Banquo 'men to cry / halt', and the entry is made 'PS'.39 How far . . . Soris?] Crossed
                            through (Hand III).41] PB appears to read 'Earth;' for F 'Earth,'
                            but the reading is probably the result of an ink smudge from the facing
                            page.44-45 By each . . . Lips:] Crossed through
                            (Hand II).55-57 prediction hereafter / of Royal hope,]
                            Hand III crosses through F 'Of . . . and' and 'That . . . withal';
                            'hereafter' may have been deleted; at any rate the ink is so badly
                            smudged as to make the word almost illegible. D'Avenant keeps the
                            substance of F but rephrases (PB's 'hereafter' is not from D'Avenant);
                            Lee slightly rephrases but deletes 57 ('That . . . withal').62 Rosse] Hand II.88 s.d. macduffe [crossed through] enter
                                here. Rosse] In the F s.d. 'Enter Rosse, and Angus.'
                            Hand II originally deletes 'and Angus.'; Hand III then deletes
                            the rest of the F s.d. and writes above it 'macduffe enter here.';
                            finally, Hand IV deletes 'macduffe' and adds 'Rosse'. It should be noted
                            that Hand II's original call for Ross was never deleted. Hand III's
                            'macduffe' follows D'Avenant; Bell, Lee retain the F s.d., but
                            Lee-Salmon PB deletes 'and Angus' and adds 'Flourish' before
                            the entry, which is made 'LD OP'.89 Ma:] Hand III substitutes 'Ma:' for F
                            'Ross.' This speech-prefix was not changed after Ross was restored by
                            Hand IV, nor did Hand III alter Ross's speech-prefix at 104.93-98 silenc'd with . . . post,] Circled (Hand
                            III). D'Avenant reduces and rewrites these lines.100-103 Ang. We are . . . thee,]
                            Circled (Hand II). D'Avenant omits; Bell, Lee retain, but Lee-Salmon PB
                            deletes.Image of prompt-book page 713109 Ross] Hand III. 'Ross' written over F
                                'Ang.'. D'Avenant assigns to Macduff. The speech is still
                            given to Angus in Lee-Salmon PB despite his omission from the scene (see
                            88 s.d., above).120 throughly beleiv'd] Hand 11 circles or
                            doubly crosses through F 'trusted home,' adding 'throughly beleiv'd'
                            after it. D'Avenant rephrases the half line as 'If all be true,'.122 Besides the . . . Cawdor.]
                            Circled or doubly crossed through (Hand II). D'Avenant and Lee both
                            rephrase slightly.125-126 Winne us . . . consequence.] Crossed
                            through (Hand ?III). D'Avenant completely rephrases.127 Cousin] The 's' in F 'Cousins' has been
                            deleted (Hand ?III). This change was dictated by the omission of Angus.
                            Although Lee-Salmon PB deletes Angus, it fails to correct to the
                            singular form; Ross is made to retire 'OP'. D'Avenant omits the
                            half-line.127 King Malcolm / Donalbin] Hand II.129 I thank you Gentlemen:] Crossed through
                            (Hand III). Lee omits, and D'Avenant, in rephrasing Macbeth's whole
                            speech, also omits.135 fflourish] Hand II. Presumably an advance
                            call for the F 'Flourish.' at the beginning of I.iv.137-142 present fears . . . not.] Circled
                            (Hand III). Except for 'present fears' D'Avenant completely recasts
                            these lines; Lee keeps them through 138 and then reverts to a cut
                            version of D'Avenant.145-146 Like strange Garments which weare / not easy
                                but wth help of use.] Hand II substitutes
                            these lines, crossing through F 'our' and 'cleave . . . use.'. Compare
                            D'Avenant: 'and resemble / New Garments, which but seldom fit men well,
                            / Unless by help of use.'. Lee retains F essentially, but with some
                            slight influence from D'Avenant.152-155 Mackbeth / Banqo / Rosse] Hand IV.
                            Hand II seems to have omitted a call for these characters at I.iv.14,
                            though it may have come at the foot of the page (column one), which has
                            been partly torn off.154 The Interim . . . it,] Circled
                            (Hand III). D'Avenant rephrases.I.iv.(opening) Cou&lt;rt&gt;] Hand I. Following
                            Rowe, Bell and Lee give the setting as 'the Palace'; Lee adds
                                '[Stage light.]'; Lee-Salmon
                             PB notes ' Door open
                            OP.'.(opening s.d.)] F 'Lenox' crossed
                            through. Note that the F 'Attendants' are, as usual, not
                            included in Hand II's advance call for this entry at I.iii.127.14 s.d. Banquo and Capt: Ros] Hand
                            III crosses through F 'Ross, and Angus.' and writes above 'and
                            Capt: R'; Hand IV then adds 'os'. D'Avenant introduces Macduff in the
                            place of Ross and Angus; Lee-Salmon PB deletes Angus and marks the entry
                            as 'LD PS'.30-31 nor must . . . so:] Circled (Hand III).
                            Lee cuts; D'Avenant rephrases; Bell retains but substitutes 'and' (Rowe)
                            for F nor.32 Lady.] Hand II. Lee-Salmon PB adds 'a
                            written letter' below its call for Lady Macbeth.44 The Rest . . . you:] Circled (Hand III).
                            The last half of the line is missing in PB, since a tear at the bottom
                            of p. 713 (Sig. 3O5) affects the ends of lines 36-49. D'Avenant
                            completely rephrases.I.v.Image of prompt-book page 714 (first one)(opening) &lt;Gar&gt;den] Hand I. Bell, Lee
                            give 'Apartment in Macbeth's Castle, at Inverness'
                            (from Pope, after Rowe).(opening) &lt;M&gt;essenger] Hand II.32 Macbeth] Hand II.57-62 King / Malcolme / Donalbin / Banquo / Macduffe
                                / Rosse] Hand II.65 Lady] Hand IV.I.vi.(opening) Court] Hand I. Bell, Lee give
                                'before Macbeth's Castle-gate' (from Theobald,
                            after Rowe).(opening s.d.)] PB deletes F 'Lenox'
                            and 'Angus'; these are presumably Hand II's deletions, since
                            these characters are omitted in the advance call at I.v.57-62. D'Avenant
                            omits Ross and Angus; Lee-Salmon PB deletes Angus and marks entry as
                            'OP'.3-9 This Guest . . . haunt:] Circled (Hand III)
                            and underlined (probably by Hand II), though the circling does not seem
                            to include 'This Guest of Summer,' (underlined), which is necessary to
                            the cut. D'Avenant slightly rephrases; Douai MS omits 3 ('This Guest . .
                            . ')-9.9 observ'd it &amp;] Hand ?II adds 'it &amp;'
                            after F 'observ'd', probably influenced by D'Avenant's 'observ'd the
                            Air, / 'Tis delicate.'.12-14 Herein I . . . trouble.] Circled (Hand
                            III). D'Avenant retains but substitutes 'us welcome' for F 'god-eyld
                            us'; Douai MS reads 13-14: 'how you shall thank us for your present
                            trouble.'; Bell retains but reads 'Heav'n-eyld us'; Lee retains, but
                            Lee-Salmon PB cuts 12-14 ('Which . . . trouble.').20 Macbeth.] Hand II.I.vii.Image of prompt-book page 715 (first one)(opening) Lady] Hand II.(opening s.d.) ] F s.d. 'Enter a Sewer,
                                and divers Servants with Dishes and Service over the Stage.'
                            has been crossed through by Hand III. PB marks no new scene setting,
                            thus continuing the 'Court' setting of scene vi. Padua PB, D'Avenant,
                            Bell, and Lee also bring Macbeth on without the banquet preparations;
                            Lee enters him as 'musing'; Lee-Salmon PB enters him 'PS';
                            Douai MS reduces F s.d. to 'Divers Servants with dishes pass over / The
                            Stage--'. D'Avenant, Bell, and Lee omit F 'Ho boyes. Torches.';
                            their retention in PB is probably an oversight. Bell, Lee (subs.) change
                            the scene to 'an Apartment in Macbeth's Castle' (from
                            Theobald after Rowe).2-12 if th' Assassination . . . lips.] Circled
                            (Hand ?II). F3 makes nonsense of 10-11 by combining them. Padua PB cuts
                            5-12 ('Heere . . . lips.'); D'Avenant reduces to five flat lines; Bell
                            as in PB cuts through 'Success:' (4).45-46 Act / Banq [crossed through]]
                            Hand II starts to write 'Banquo' but does not even complete the 'q'.
                            Since the characters are not given advance calls for the first scene of
                            a new act, the call for Banquo was a slip of Hand II's and probably
                            deleted by him.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1052</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div1_act</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">II.II.i.(opening) Chambe&lt;r&gt;] Hand I. The 'm'
                            in 'Chambe&lt;r&gt;' is far from clear. Bell, Lee (subs.) give the scene
                            as 'a Hall in Macbeth's Castle'; Lee adds '[Stage
                                dark.]', and Lee-Salmon PB notes 'Door OP Shut'.Image of prompt-book page 714 (second one)8-9 Merciful Powers . . . repose.] Underlined
                            (Hand II) and circled (Hand III). D'Avenant rephrases; Bell retains but
                            omits 'Give me my Sword ;' in 9; Lee omits 8-9 (' . . . Sword:'). There
                            is no advance call for Macbeth's and the Servant's entry at 9 in PB.27-28 Beell / Redy] Hand IV.38 Lady] Hand II.40-45 I see . . . rest:] Circled (Hand II).
                            D'Avenant omits all but the last line-and-a-half.53-54 Alarum'd by . . . pace,] Circled (Hand
                            III). D'Avenant rephrases.57 which they may walk,] Crossed through (Hand
                            ?II). Part of a longer cut in D'Avenant; Lee substitutes 'feel not my
                            tread,'; Douai MS omits as in PB.58 desines] Hand III substitutes 'desines' for
                            F 'where about,' (underlined by Hand ?III). Part of a cut in D'Avenant;
                            Lee reads the line as: 'Thy very stones shou'd check my purpose,'.60 Whilest] Hand ?III inserts 't' after F
                            'Whiles'. Part of a cut in Bell, Lee.63-64 Bell / Rings my coronation and thy
                                Knell.] Hand III substitutes 'Bell . . . Knell.' for F
                            'Knell, That . . . hell.' (F 'Knell' crossed through by Hand III; 'That
                            . . . hell.' by Hand II). Based on D'Avenant: 'bell / That rings my
                            Coronation, and thy Knell.'.II.ii.(opening) Macbeth] Hand II. PB marks no
                            change of scene setting. Bell, Lee ignore F 'Scaena Secunda.'.
                            In an advance prompt note for this scene Lee-Salmon PB calls for '2
                            Daggers / &amp; Blood / ready OP'.21 Redy / to knok] Hand IV.Image of prompt-book page 715 (second one)52 Mackduff / Rosse] Hand IV. This replaces a
                            later call by Hand II at the opening of scene iii. See below,
                            II.iii.1-46.62 multitudinous] This word appears to be
                            crossed through, but what looks like a deletion results from an ink show
                            through from verso (p. 716, sig. 3P1V).63 Porter.] Hand II.74 Macbeth] Hand IV.II.iii. (opening) Macduffe / Rosse [both crossed
                                    through by Hand IV]]  Hand II. Hand ?II has also
                            written something to the left of F 'Scena Tertia.' which may be
                            the beginning of 'Macbeth', but only the first ?three letters were
                            written and then crossed through. PB marks no new scene setting; Bell no
                            new scene (after Rowe); Lee indicates 'a hall' (but this was
                            the setting of the preceding scene); Lee-Salmon PB adds 'Door OP Shut'
                            and below 'Time giuen.'.1-46] The order of cutting and restoration in
                            these lines is uncertain. In what seems to be the final form, 5 ('Here's
                            . . . ' )-23 and 28 ('of three . . . ')-46 were cut. Judging by the inks
                            used, Hand II first deletes, by circling, the whole of 1-46, then
                            changes his mind and marks both circled sections with 'stet' and
                            'stett'. Hand III then crisscrosses 5-23 and 28-46 for deletion, adding
                            'to sle&lt;ep&gt;' at the end of 27 to complete the sense. Hand IV
                            tidies things up by placing an advance call for Macduff and Ross at
                            II.ii.52 (deleting Hand II's call at the beginning of scene iii) and an
                            advance call for Macbeth at II.ii.74. Apparently Hand II neglected to
                            mark an advance call for Macbeth; however, see above, II.iii (opening).
                            The order of events as here described presents certain problems, but I
                            am unable to offer any more satisfactory alternative. Padua PB cuts the
                            whole of the Porter's soliloquy; D'Avenant also cuts the soliloquy,
                            reduces the Porter's role to one line (he, here called Servant, and
                            Lennox enter together and after three lines Macduff enters), and
                            replaces 23-46 with eleven lines 
                            between Lennox and Macduff based on F lines 59-66; Douai MS reduces the
                            Porter's soliloquy to 'P: here's a knocking indeed: who's there in the
                            name of belzebub? anon; anon; I am coming. (Opens the doore.)' and omits
                            27-46 ('and drink . . . him.'); Bell cuts everything down to Macduff's
                            entry (24), the Servant, who has opened the 'door' to Macduff
                            and Lennox, being given F 26-27 ('Faith . . . cock:'), and then adds
                            Lennox's speech from F (59-66). These last two speeches are in italics,
                            and Gentleman (Bell) remarks: ". . . and the Italic lines, by
                            transposition, judiciously introduced to give Macbeth time for
                            change of appearance, of which, even now, he is allowed too little.";
                            Lee cuts the Porter's soliloquy, bringing Lennox on alone (Lee-Salmon PB
                            notes 'PS' ), 'who knocks at the chamber door several times pretty
                                hard, then a servant opens it.' (Lee-Salmon PB adds 'OP'),
                            follows D'Avenant's opening two speeches, inserts F 47 ('Is . . .
                            stirring?'), and adds: 'Serv. Not yet, Sir, but he'll scarce
                            lye late; he's of an active spirit, that never suffers his body to lye
                            still when once his mind is up. / Len. Well, say I wait his
                            leisure. / Serv. I will, Sir.' Collier MS shows points of
                            resemblance to Smock Alley PB, since it cuts lines 5-22 ('Here's . . .
                            Bonfire.'), 27-46 ( 'And Drink . . . him.').23 s.d. Enter Macduff, and Rosse [Hand
                                    III] Rosse [Hand II, crossed through] and
                                Ro&lt;sse&gt; [Hand III]] Hand II first deletes F
                                'and Lenox.' and writes 'Rosse' following the deletion;
                            then Hand III deletes Hand II's 'Rosse' and writes 'and Rosse' above the
                            deleted F 'and Lenox.'; finally, Hand III writes 'and
                            Ro&lt;sse&gt;' following the deleted 'Rosse' by Hand II (the order of
                            Hand III's changes may, of course, have been reversed).28 to sle&lt;ep&gt;] Hand III substitutes 'to
                            sle&lt;ep&gt;' for F 'of three things.'. See above, 1-46.49 Lenox.] This speech-prefix has been crossed
                            through but not reassigned. Presumably Hand II deleted it but failed to
                            give it to Ross, who takes Lennox's place in the scene. Lennox's
                            speech-prefixes otherwise remain untouched in this scene, though his
                            speeches must have been spoken by Ross.76 Macd.] Some hand has altered F
                                'b' in 'Macb.' to 'd', thus restoring the
                            reading of F1.Image of prompt-book page 71678 Lady] Hand II.78 s.d. Macbeth and Rosse ['Rosse' crossed
                                through]] Hand ?III deletes F 'Lenox.' and writes
                            'Rosse' below (also heavily deleted). Whoever (Hand ?IV) here deleted
                            'Rosse' neglected to cancel the advance call for his re entry at 85.
                            Despite  this oversight, I suspect
                            that he is not intended to exit with Macbeth at this point but remains
                            on stage to speak Lennox's speech (106-111).79 Banquo] Hand II.83-85 Macbeth / &lt;R&gt;osse] Hand II.88-89 &lt;Ma&gt;lcolme / &lt;Don&gt;albine]
                            Hand II.95 s.d.] Hand ?IV crosses through
                                F'Lenox,'. For Ross's re-entry, see above, 78 s.d.105 Macd.] The ink blot on this
                            speech-prefix does not indicate deletion but is a smudge from the facing
                            page (717, sig. 3P2).131-133 Lady: &amp; instantly let us meet,]
                            Hand II underlines and Hand III crosses through 132-133 ( 'And . . .
                            exposure: ' ) and inserts '&amp; instantly' (after 131). See below,
                            135-138.135-138 Feares and . . . all.] Underlined
                            (Hand II) and crossed through (Hand III). Considering this and the
                            preceding deletion together, one notes that D'Avenant also omits these
                            lines (and a good many others) and works part of 133-135 ('let . . .
                            further.') into a speech by Macbeth a few lines later. In Bell and Lee,
                            Lady Macbeth does not appear in the scene at all, apparently a
                            long-standing practice (G. W. Stone, SP, XXXVIII [1941],
                            621-22); except for references to Lady Macbeth, Lee preserves 131-138
                            essentially intact, but Bell omits 132-133 ('And . . . exposure:') as in
                            PB.139-141 Banqo [Hand IV] / Rosse / Old man
                                    [crossed through]]  Hand II originally calls for
                            'Rosse/ Old man'; then Hand IV deletes 'Old man' and inserts 'Banqo'
                            above 'Rosse'. See scene iv, s.d. (opening).II.iv.(opening) Rock scan / Towne [crossed
                                    through]] Hand I originally gave the setting as
                            'Towne'; then Hand ? crossed through 'Towne' and inserted 'Rock scan'
                            above. The reading 'scan' is doubtful. Perhaps a form of 'scene'? Bell,
                            Lee: 'Outside of Macbeth's Castle'; Lee adds
                                '[Stage light.]'(opening) Macduffe] Hand II.(opening s.d. ) Banquo and Captaine [Hand
                                    III, 'Captaine' crossed through] / Roose [Hand
                                    IV]] The F s.d. remains untouched; Hand III inserts
                            'Banquo and Captaine' above it; Hand IV then deletes 'Captaine' and adds
                            'Roose' below (cf. I.iv.14 s.d.), clarifying the advance call at
                            II.iii.139-141 by adding 'Banqo' and deleting 'Old man'. R. C. Bald
                                (PMLA, LVI [1941], 375 n., 377-78) explains the change of
                            setting from 'Towne' to 'Rock' as the result of what seems to be an
                            appearance of the Witches later in the scene at Macduff's entrance (20)
                            and suggests that "at least one" of D'Avenant's witch songs was here
                            used (see below, 10-13, 21). Of the two witch
                             songs (D'Avenant, II.v) probably
                            the second is the more likely choice, since it alone is followed by a
                            dance in D'Avenant's version (the first sixteen lines of the song also
                            appeared in the 1673 quarto of Macbeth, interpolated between
                            scenes iii and iv, which is otherwise substantially a reprint of F1).
                            The substitution of Banquo for the Old Man in PB may also perhaps be
                            explained by the importation of the Witches, since their song might seem
                            more suitable for Banquo's ears, though it should be noted that the
                            directions implying the Witches are in Hand IV. In D'Avenant the scene
                            is carried by Lennox and Seyton, down to Macduff's entrance; nor do the
                            witch songs appear in this scene. They are part of the following scene
                            (II.v), a scene ('An Heath.') almost entirely D'Avenant's own
                            creation, and are directed at Macduff and Lady Macduff. Bell, Lee retain
                            Shakespeare's scene with Ross and the Old Man, but place it at the
                            beginning of Act III, inserting a scene with all the Witch business, but
                            minus the Macduffs, from D'Avenant II.v. Bell, Lee-Salmon PB exit the
                            Old Man just before Macduff's entry. Clearly PB, Bell, Lee have one aim
                            in mind: entertainment at any cost. Lee gives no scene setting; in Bell
                                'The SCENE changes to a Wood. Thunder and Lightning.'.1-2 Threescore and . . . time,] Circled (Hand
                            III). This cut and those at 4-5 and 39 are obviously made to adapt the
                            lines in some sort to Banquo, but the Old Man's speech-prefixes remain
                            untouched. The D'Avenant Yale MS substitutes 'Three score and one' for F
                            'Threescore and ten', but the printed text cuts the whole phrase and
                            begins 'I can remember well,' thus better adapting the following lines
                            to Seyton.4-5 Ha, good . . . seest] Crossed through (Hand
                            III). D'Avenant reduces to 'Thou seest'. Collier MS cuts 6-20 ('by th'
                            clock . . . upon't').10-13 Song / Redy / daunce] Hand IV. See
                            above, II.iv (opening).Image of prompt-book page 71721 Sing heere / and daunce] Hand IV. See
                            above, II.iv (opening).27 Act] Hand II.39 Father.] Crossed through (Hand III).
                            D'Avenant, Bell, Lee cut 39-41.40 all happenesse go with you and] Hand III
                            crosses through F 'God's benison' and, with a caret, substitutes 'all
                            happenesse', at the same time crossing through F 'Sir,'. Douai MS
                            substitutes 'blessing' for F 'benison'.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1391</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div1_act</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">III.III.i(opening) Court] Hand I. Bell, Lee: 'an
                                Apartment in the Palace' (Theobald, after Rowe).(opening) Macbeth Lady Rosse ['Rosse' crossed
                                    through]] Hand II. The deletion of 'Rosse', by Hand
                            ?II, has been badly smudged.10 s.d.] F 'Lenox, Rosse,' crossed
                            through; 'Lenox' by Hands II and III, 'Rosse' very
                            lightly, possibly by Hand II, the hand probably responsible for deleting
                            'Rosse' in advance call above. D'Avenant gives only 'Macbeth, Lenox,
                                and Attendants.'; Bell, Lee, like D'Avenant, omit Lady
                            Macbeth, but otherwise follow F.16-17 Command me, and my dutie / is with most
                                obedient ty] Hand II circles and/or crosses through F 'upon',
                            'to the which' ('the' separately circled), the 's' in 'duties', 'Are',
                            'a', and 'indissoluble tye' and substitutes 'and', 'is', and 'obedient
                            ty'. Before inserting 'and' Hand II seems to have intended reading 'to
                            which'. D'Avenant rewrites; Douai MS reads 'lay your commands on me, to
                            which . . . tye'; Bell, Lee retain but read 'Lay' for F 'Let' in 15
                            (after D'Avenant and Rowe; compare Douai MS).22 farlow] Hand ?III. Nothing seems to be
                            known about this actor, and his name appears in none of the other Smock
                            Alley prompt-books. W. S. Clark (The Early Irish Stage, 1955,
                            p. 207) places him with the Smock Alley company "c. 1674," but
                            this date depends, I assume, on dating the Macbeth PB somewhat
                            earlier than I believe likely. See Introduction, p. 2. Farlow here plays
                            the Servant, and the position of the advance call at 22 suggests that he
                            was intended to enter about 44 (as in the Padua PB); editors, from Rowe
                            on (followed by Bell, Lee), assume the Servant to be one of the F
                                'Attendants' who enter at 11.24 Is't far] F 'far' appears to be heavily
                            deleted, but the mark is only the result of an ink smudge from the
                            facing page (716, sig. 3P1).28 two] Hand II crosses through F 'twain.' and
                            writes 'two' following. So D'Avenant, Douai MS, Lee.38-39 I wish . . . backs.] The marks of
                            deletion (by Hand III) are ambiguous. Possibly (as in Padua PB) both
                            lines are marked for deletion, but it seems more likely that only 39 is
                            meant to be deleted, since D'Avenant omits only 39 (as does Lee) and the
                            scene has earlier shown signs of his influence.52 53 Serva&lt;nt&gt; / Murt&lt;herers&gt;]
                            Hand II. In connection with Macbeth's interview with the two Murderers,
                            it is worth noting that Padua PB cuts the interview with the Murderers
                             completely and that Lee-Salmon PB
                            turns the interview into one between Seyton and Macbeth, in which, with
                            certain necessary slight omissions and revisions, Seyton speaks the
                            lines of both Murderers.Image of prompt-book page 71880 Past in . . . you:] Partly circled (Hand
                            ?III). Cut in D'Avenant; Douai MS, Bell cut 76-86 ('Know . . .
                            meeting.'); Lee makes substantially the same cut as in Douai MS and Bell
                            but retains 84 ('You . . . us.') in revised form.101-104 Lady / Servant / farlow] Hand II
                            ('farlow' Hand ?III). For 'farlow' see above, 22.110 care not] Hand III crosses through F 'am
                            reckless' and substitutes 'care not' above end of line. So D'Avenant,
                            Lee; Douai MS replaces F 'that I am reckless' with 'I'm careless'; Bell
                            cuts the Second Murderer's speech.122-126 Whose loves . . . Reasons.] Circled
                            and x'd through (Hand III). D'Avenant reduces to four lines and rewrites
                            heavily; Bell cuts 121-125; Lee, 122-123 (`but . . . down:').132-133 alwayes thought . . . clearness;]
                            Circled (Hand III). Cut in Douai MS, Pope, Bell, Lee; D'Avenant
                            rewrites.III.ii.(opening) Macbeth] Hand II. PB marks no
                            change of setting here (so Rowe and Lee); D'Avenant interpolates a new
                            scene (between Macduff and Lady Macduff) between F scenes i and ii; Bell
                            gives 'another Apartment in the Palace' (after Theobald).6-7 Curtaine / ready] Hand III. See 56,
                            below.22-23 Banqett / Redy] Hand IV. This is an
                            advance call for III.iv.Image of prompt-book page 71944 Murtherers] Hand II.56] Below this line, Hand III inserts 'here
                                ye Curtaine falls.'. R. C. Bald (PMLA,
                            LVI [1941], 375-76) suggests that this direction indicates that the
                            scene of Banquo's murder was actually played before the front curtain,
                            while the banquet for scene iv was being 'set'; see above, 222-23 and
                            III.iii (opening), below. Such an arrangement would seem to ignore Hand
                            I's setting for III.iii as a 'Groue' (which remains undeleted).
                            Lee-Salmon PB also adds 'Drop Curtain) Stage Dark.'.III.iii.(opening) Enter Banquo and boy] Hand III.
                            Fleance is described as 'Boy to Banquo' in the 1673 quarto list
                            of 'The Persons Names' (followed by D'Avenant).(opening) Banqett Set / on] Hand IV.(opening) Groue] Hand I. See above,
                            III.ii.56. Bell gives 'a Park; the Castle at a Distance' (after
                            Rowe); Lee, 'an avenue to the palace'.(opening s.d.) Enter two
                                    Murtherers.] Hand III deletes F 'three'
                            and writes 'two' above. This scene has been radically cut about by Hand
                            III, largely to bring it into line with D'Avenant's version. Originally
                            the scene was planned as written; Hand II's calls for 'Murtherers' at
                            III.ii.44 and 'Banquo / ffleans' at the beginning of scene iii indicate
                            this (though the number of the 'Murtherers' is ambiguous). As Hand III
                            sets the scene up, Banquo and Fleance cross the stage first and are
                            immediately followed by the 'two' Murderers, whose dialogue has been
                            considerably cut to resemble D'Avenant's. The Murderers follow Banquo
                            and Fleance off-stage and the scene ends. R. C. Bald (PMLA, LVI
                            [1941], 377) is surely mistaken when he says "it is interesting to note
                            that, while Davenant makes the actual murder occur off-stage, in the
                            Dublin version Banquo and Fleance do not even come on beforehand." In
                            D'Avenant the three Murderers enter first, speak nine lines, and exit;
                            then Banquo and Fleance enter, speak five lines, and exit; the Murderers
                            re-enter, speak four lines, and go out after Banquo and Fleance;
                            finally, Fleance, pursued by the Murderers, re-enters on the run and
                            throws a single line at the audience. Bell follows F1 (though with some
                            cutting) down to 18 (' . . . Slave!') and cuts the remainder of the
                            Murderers' lines; Banquo dies on stage. Lee follows a heavily cut
                            version of F1 down to the entrance of Banquo and Fleance and turns to
                            D'Avenant for their speeches; after their exit, the Murderers (First and
                            Second) are given an original line each and then pursue Banquo and
                            Fleance off-stage; finally, Fleance re-enters to deliver D'Avenant's
                            single line.1 Banquo / ffleans] Hand II. See above,
                            opening s.d.1-4 j: It is about ye
                                howre.] Hand III substitutes this single line for F '1. But
                            who . . . us.', which lines are partly circled (in two stages) and x'd
                            through. Compare D'Avenant: '1. Mur. The time is almost come,'.
                            Douai MS cuts F 'But' (1) and 2-4 (' . . . just.') and assigns 4 ('1.
                            Then stand with us.') to `2:'.5 2 The West] Hand III, having deleted the
                            first half-line of the First Murderer's speech, assigns the rest to '2'.
                            D'Avenant gives 5-7 (' . . . Inn.') to First Murderer (6 slightly
                            rephrased) and cuts 7-8 ('and . . . Watch.'); Douai MS assigns 5-8 (' .
                            . . Watch.') to '1:'.8 1. Heark,] Hand III writes `1 over F `3 .
                            D'Avenant assigns to Second Murderer; so too, Lee.9 Banquo within. Give . . . hoa.] Crossed and
                            x'd through (Hand III). D'Avenant omits.11-22 1. Almost a mile: about the horse way is /
                                therefore men / from hence to th'Palace Gate / Make this their
                                usuall walke / 2: come Lets away then and Banquo if thy soule / can
                                in her flight reach / heaven / thy happinesse / begins to / night. /
                                exeunt] Hand III crosses through 11 ('1. His Horses go
                            about.'), alters F '3.' to '1.', interlines 'about', with a caret, after
                            F 'mile: ' (the blot over the 'e' may have been intended to delete the F
                            colon), crosses through 12-13 ('but . . . do,'), and substitutes 'the
                            horse way is'; at this point he apparently planned to keep the rest of
                            the speech as it was, only inserting 'usually' after F 'Gate', but he
                            changes his mind, deletes 'usually' and F 'it' (14), interlining 'this'
                            above, deletes F 'walk.', and inserts 'usuall walke' following. He then
                            adds the speech for the Second Murderer, above and below the F s.d.
                                'Enter Banquo . . . Torch.', which curiously enough remains
                            undeleted. As a result of the crowding of Hand III's first changes, his
                            intention is not clear, and it is possible that he meant the first line
                            to read '1. the horse way is / almost a mile: about'. Lines 14-22 are
                            circled and x'd through, though perhaps Hand III's 'come Lets away' was
                            suggested by F 'Well, let's away' (22). Compare D'Avenant: '1.
                                Mur. His Horses go about almost a Mile, / And men from hence to
                            th' Pallace make it their usual walk.'; and later, when the
                            Murderers re-enter: '1. Mur. Banquo, thou little think'st what
                            bloody feast / Is now preparing for thee. / 2. Mur. Nor to what
                            shades the darkness of this night, / Shall lead thy wandering
                            spirit.'.14-16 Macbeth / Lady / Rosse] Hand II.III.iv.(opening) Cham&lt;ber&gt; [crossed through]
                                / Cour&lt;t&gt;] Hand I. Bell gives setting as 'a room of
                                state in the castle' (Pope, after Rowe); Lee, 'a chamber of
                                state'.(opening s.d.)] F 'Lenox,' crossed
                            through (Hand II). Lee-Salmon PB notes 'Door Open OP'.1 Murth&lt;erer&gt;] Hand II.15-17 Banq&lt;uo&gt; / Gost] Hand II.Image of prompt-book page 72060 distract] Hand III interlines 'distract'
                            above deleted F 'appal'. So D'Avenant.69 Behold, look, how] Hand III deletes F
                            'loe,' after 'look,'. D'Avenant cuts 'Behold, look, loe,'; Douai MS
                            reads 'looke, loe behold' and omits 'how say you:'.75 antient] Hand III deletes F 'olden' and
                            writes 'antient' above. D'Avenant rewrites the line; Douai MS changes
                            the phrase to 'in former times'; Lee alters to 'oldest'.76 &lt;Ba&gt;nquo / &lt;Go&gt;st] Hand II.103 be again, reviue] Hand III deletes F
                            'alive' after 'be' and inserts 'reviue' after 'again,'. Hand II's
                            version while possible is  awkward;
                            perhaps he intended to delete F 'be'. Compare D'Avenant's 'revive a
                            while'.105 and if I meet the not proclaime then]
                            Hand III crosses through F 105 ('If . . . me') and interlines above 'and
                            . . . then'. In making the alteration Hand III omits 'me' after
                            'proclaime'. Compare D'Avenant's 'If any Sinew shrink, proclaim me
                            then'. Bell, Lee accept Pope's 'inhibit' for F 'inhabit'.106 horrid] Hand III alters F 'horrible' to
                            'horrid' by deleting 'le' and changing 'b' to 'd'. So Lee.108 now I am] Hand III inserts 'now' before F
                            'I am'. F3 necessitated some change by misprinting F1 'being gone' as
                            'be gone' in 107. D'Avenant cuts 107 and reads 'So, now I am'. 116 sights] Hand III corrects F3's 'signes'
                            (inherited from F2) to the F1 'sights' by altering 'ne' to 'ht'.120-121 Witches / Heccate] Hand II.142-144 My strange . . . indeed.] Circled
                            (Hand II). Douai MS cuts; D'Avenant rewrites 142-144 (followed
                            substantially by Lee).III.v.(opening) Rock] Hand I. Bell changes scene to
                                'the Heath'; Lee, to 'the open heath. [Stage
                                dark.]' (both after Rowe). Lee-Salmon PB prefaces the scene
                            with 'Curtain down', indicating that the scene was to be played on the
                            forestage before some kind of inner curtain.(opening) Musiqe / boys redy] Hand IV.
                            Presumably 'boys' are here warned to be ready to 'Sing
                            within.', the song called for at 33 below.2 as you are] Crossed through (Hand III). So
                            D'Avenant.Image of prompt-book page 7217-9 Reddy / Curtin] Hand IV.15 Act] Hand II.33-34 And you . . . Enemy.] Circled (Hand
                            ?III). D'Avenant, Lee cut these and the two preceding lines.36 end the ackt [Hand II] / ffall Curtten
                                    [Hand IV]] Compare 'end' inserted here in Padua
                            PB. Bell, followed essentially by Lee, tacks on parts of D'Avenant's
                            conclusion (omitting 33-39 and 50-56) and adds several new lines, giving
                            the majority of the lines to Hecate. Lee-Salmon PB enters 'singin
                            Witches PS' at 28 (D'Avenant's version) and, adapting the Lee s.d.
                                ('A cloud descends, and Hecate (after the ceremony of
                                being anointed) gets into it.'), adds 'Ring Chariot
                            down.' (opposite 31), 'ring up Chariot' (opposite 40), and concludes the
                            scene with 'Drop Curtain.'.III.vi.III.vi.]Hand II circles and Hand III crisscrosses through
                                whole scene, Hand ?IV writing 'Cut' to left of opening F s.d
                            . Padua PB,  Bell, Lee also omit
                            this scene; D'Avenant inserts the scene (as between Lennox and Seyton),
                            with some cuts and rewriting, between F scenes iv and v (preceding it
                            with an original scene between Macduff and Lady Macduff); Douai MS cuts
                            only 25 and reduces 21-22 to 'no more of this.'. Gentleman (Bell) notes
                            that "the scene between Lenox and another useless lord is
                            properly omitted, as unequal to the warmth and spirit of the rest.".</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1780</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div1_act</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">IV.IV.i.(opening) Actus Quartus] Hand III
                            deletes F 'Quintus' and interlines 'Quartus' above with a caret.(opening) Caue / Rock [crossed
                                through]] Hand IV deletes Hand I's 'Rock' and
                            substitutes 'Caue' above. The change was doubtless suggested by the
                            final line in D'Avenant's preceding witch scene: 'Let's to the Cave and
                            our dire Charms prepare.'. Bell gives the setting as 'a dark
                                Cave:'; Lee, 'a cave. [Stage dark.]'. Bald
                                (PMLA, LVI [1941], 376) reads Hand IV's 'Caue' as
                            'Cau[dron], but PB is quite clear at this point.7 Heccate] Hand II. It may be noted that this
                            advance call for Hecate at 38 does not include F's 'other three
                                Witches'. As a rule, however, the prompter does not bother to
                            call for non-speaking characters, and the s.d. in F remains uncut. Padua
                            PB has no call for Hecate or 'the other three Witches', but it
                            does not cancel the F s.d. at 38, nor does it reassign Hecate's speech
                            at 39. D'Avenant, who went in for all the witches he could get, retains
                            the three extra witches, as do Douai MS and Bell. Lee goes even further,
                            reading the s.d. at 38 as 'Enter Hecate and all the singing
                                Witches.' and assigning the parts of the song in D'Avenant's
                            version specifically to the 'singing Witches'. D'Avenant (also in the
                            Yale MS) assigns the last part only of 61 to a fourth witch, but the
                            context makes it clear that he really means Hecate; Douai MS, Bell, Lee
                            do not follow him.22 Mack] Hand IV (very faint and smudged).
                            Hand IV here anticipates his call for Macbeth at 29, presumably because
                            it does not occur until the top of the following page in F.Image of prompt-book page 72229 &lt;Ma&gt;cbeth] Hand IV.55-56 &lt;App&gt;arition] Hand II. Apparently
                            undeleted, but see below, 62-68.62-68 1. Say, if . . . show.] Circled and x'd
                            (Hand III). This is the first of a series of cuts designed to bring the
                            scene into general agreement with D'Avenant's version, in which these
                            lines are also cut, Hecate's role is enlarged, and the Apparitions are
                            entirely cut out. The scene was originally planned
                             by Hand II to include the
                            Apparitions (see above 55-56). Bell, Lee retain the Apparitions; the
                            Lee-Salmon PB gives elaborate directions, raising and sinking them on
                            traps. In a note to the first edition of Bell (1773, p.48), a note
                            dropped in the second edition, Gentleman remarks: "In a very bad
                            alteration of this play, by Betterton [i.e., D'Avenant], he has
                            hit upon what we think an emendation; that is, making the witches
                            deliver all the prophecies; by which the surfeiting quantity of
                            trapwork, ghosts, phantomes, &amp;c. is judiciously lessened."68 s.d. 1. Apparition . . . Head.]
                            Crossed and x'd through (Hand III).69 Tell me you unknown powers what dangers / doe
                                attend my destiny]  Hand III alters F 'thou' to 'you' (by
                            writing 'y' over 'th'), F 'power' to 'powers' (by adding 's'), and adds
                            'what . . . destiny'. Compare D'Avenant, 'What Destinie's appointed for
                            my Fate?'.69-70 1. He knowes . . . nought.] Partly
                            circled and x'd (Hand III). D'Avenant also cuts.71-72 Beware Macduff, avoyding him Makbeth
                                is safe Enough.] Hand III adds 'avoyding . . . safe' after F
                                'Macduff,' and crosses through and x's F 'Beware the
                                Thane of Fife: dismiss me.'. Compare D'Avenant:
                                'Hec. Thou double Thane and King; beware
                                Macduff: / Avoiding him, Macbeth is safe enough.'.
                            Note that the speech in PB is still assigned, as in F, to '1.
                                Appar.'. This is obviously an oversight on Hand III's part,
                            who assigns the remaining speeches of the Apparitions to Hecate, as in
                            D'Avenant.72 s.d. He descends.] Partly crossed
                            through (Hand III).74 But one word more.] Crossed through (Hand
                            III). D'Avenant cuts the whole of 74.75-78 1. He will . . . thee.] Circled and x'd
                            (Hand III). D'Avenant also cuts.79 hec:] Hand III, as in D'Avenant,
                            substitutes 'hec:' (i.e., Hecate) for the F speech-prefix '2.
                                Appar.' (crossed through).79 Horrid musick / ready] Hand III places
                            this prompt call in upper right corner of p. 722 (sig. 3P4v), in preparation for the 'shew of eight Kings'
                            following Macbeth's 'what noise is this?' at 106. Compare the call in
                            the Smock Alley MS prompt-book of Wilson's Belphegor (Folger MS
                            827.1, p. 77): 'Ready for horrid Music / Mrs Osborne
                            ready'.81 s.d. Descends.] Crossed through (Hand
                            III).82 fear thee?] Hand III deletes 'of' in F
                            'fear of thee'. Compare D'Avenant, 'fear thy power:'.86 s.d.-89 3. Apparition . . . to't.]
                            Partly crossed through, circled, and x'd (Hand III). D'Avenant also
                            cuts; Bell, Lee (following Pope) cut only 'to't' in 89, which Lee
                            assigns to Hecate.90 heck.] Hand III, as in D'Avenant,
                            substitutes 'heck.' (i.e., Hecate) for the F speech prefix '3.
                                Appar.' (crossed through).90 hearted] Hand III substitutes 'hearted'
                            for F 'metled' (crossed through); point of insertion marked with a
                            caret. D'Avenant reads the line as: 'Be Confident, be Proud, and take no
                            care'.92-94 or slaine / till Birnam woud / shall come to
                                dunsinane] Hand III substitutes these words for F 'until /
                            Great Byrnam wood, to high Dunsinane Hill, / Shall
                            come against him.' (crossed through). Compare D'Avenant,
                                'Macbeth shall like a lucky Monarch Raign, / Till
                                Birnam Wood shall come to Dunsinane.' (a reading
                            adopted by Lee, substituting 'forest' for 'Wood shall'). Douai
                            MS, anticipating Pope, reads 'to Dunsiman high hill' for F 'to high
                                Dunsinane Hill'; Bell, following Pope, reads 'to
                                Dunsinane's high hill'.99-100 Banquo / 8 kings] Hand II.107-109 Seruant / heere]. Hand IV. This is a
                            call for the Servant who replaces F's 'Lenox' at 135. D'Avenant
                            and Lee replace Lennox with Seyton.110 hec] Hand III substitutes 'hec' (i.e.,
                            Hecate) for F speech-prefix 'All.' (crossed through) .
                            D'Avenant gives the line to the Third Witch and the next line (111) to
                            Hecate, reading: 'Wound through his Eyes, his harden'd Heart, /
                                Hec. Like Shaddows come, and straigth depart.' (so Yale
                            MS); Lee reads the lines as in D'Avenant (restoring 'so' for 'straigth')
                            but assigns them to Hecate.125 heck] Hand III writes 'heck' (i.e.,
                            Hecate) over F speech-prefix '1.'. So D'Avenant, Lee.125 Lenox [crossed through by Hand
                                ?III]] Hand II. See 107-109, above.Image of prompt-book page 723135 s.d. Enter &lt;Ser&gt;vant [Hand
                                    ?III] / here [Hand IV]] Page 722 (sig.
                                3P4v) is damaged at this point. The hand in
                            '&lt;Ser&gt;vant' is impossible to determine, though one would expect it
                            to be either Hand III or Hand IV, probably Hand III, though the 'r' form
                            employed is closer to Hand IV's. The ink, however, is much darker than
                            that in 'here', which, nevertheless, does not seem to be quite the same
                            as in Hand IV's call at 107-109. F 'Lenox' has been crossed
                            through.135 Ser:] Hand ?IV deletes F speech-prefix
                                'Lenox.' and substitutes 'Ser:'. Lennox's later speeches in
                            this scene are not reassigned.136 Macduffs Wife her son, and Rosse.] Hand
                            II places this call  at the extreme
                            left top of p. 723 (sig. 3P5); it has been badly shaved in binding. The
                            phrase 'her son' seems to have been crossed through (Hand ?II); see
                            opening s.d. of IV.ii.147 Mesing / er] Hand IV. This early call for
                            the Messenger who enters at IV.ii.64 has been added by Hand IV because
                            of the later cutting of IV.ii.30-64, 79 ('Where . . . ')-85. The
                            Messenger is played by Seyton in D'Avenant; by Angus in Bell.IV.ii.(opening) Garden] Hand I. Following Rowe,
                            Bell gives the setting as 'Macduff's Castle in Fife'.(opening) Malcome / Macduf] Hand IV. This
                            early call for the entry of Malcolm and Macduff at the beginning of
                            IV.iii again results from the heavy cutting in IV.ii.(opening s.d.) Enter Macduff's Wife, and
                                    Rosse.] Hand III crosses through F 'her
                            Son,'. The omission of Lady Macduff's son follows D'Avenant.
                            Originally the scene was planned by Hand II to include the little boy,
                            as well as the dialogue between mother and son (30-64) and the later
                            dialogue of the Murderers (79 ('Where . . .' )-85), passages also
                            omitted by D'Avenant. D'Avenant substitutes Lennox for Ross; Douai MS
                            makes an unusual number of short cuts in this scene; Bell cuts
                            essentially as in PB but retains the entry of the son; Lee omits the
                            whole scene. Gentleman (Bell) comments on this scene: "Here
                                Shakespeare, as if the vigorous exertion of his faculties,
                            in the preceding scene, required relaxation, has given us a most
                            trifling superfluous dialogue, between Lady Macduff,
                                Rosse, and her son, merely that another murder may be
                            committed, on the stage too. We heartily concur in, and approve of,
                            striking out the greatest part of it." In the second edition (1774), he
                            drops this note but adds: "The character of Lady Macduff, and
                            consequently this scene, is entirely omitted, at some theatres, as
                            unnecessary to representation, the fatal catastrophe of the family being
                            finely introduced in another part of this act."25-26 My pretty . . . you.] Crossed through by
                            Hand III, probably over an earlier light crossing through by Hand II.
                            This cut is obviously the result of omitting Lady Macduff's son, but the
                            omission of these lines makes nonsense of Lady Macduff's reply, which is
                            untouched. D'Avenant substitutes 'Heaven protect you.'; Douai MS retains
                            the present lines but cuts 23-25 (' . . . before.') and 27-30 (' . . .
                            once.').30-64 Wife. Sirra, your . . .
                                talk'st?] Partly circled (Hand III) and crisscrossed (Hand
                            ?II). Cut in D'Avenant, Bell (Lee omits the scene); Douai MS, among
                            other slight changes and cuts, omits 34-36, 41-43, 51-53. Collier MS
                            cuts 32-58.42-43 Messenger] Hand II. See IV.i.147.69-70 Murth&lt;erers&gt;] Hand II. A heavy ink
                            blot makes Hand II's call almost illegible; since the entrance and
                            dialogue of the Murderers is cut, the call would ordinarily have been
                            cancelled. Someone has drawn what looks like a phallic symbol above Hand
                            II's call.75 wicked] Hand III interlines, with a caret,
                            'wicked' above F 'earthly'. D'Avenant substitutes 'a vicious' for F
                            'this earthly'; Douai MS omits 74-79 ('But . . . harm?').79 exit] Hand III. See entry on 79-85.79 Malcolme [crossed through] / Macduffe
                                    [crossed through, both by Hand III]] Hand II.
                            This call replaced by Hand IV at opening of scene ii.79-85 What are . . . you. Exit, crying
                                    Murther.] Partly circled (Hand III) and crisscrossed
                            (Hand II). Cut in D'Avenant, Bell (Lee omits the scene).IV.iii.Image of prompt-book page 724(opening) Towne] Hand I. D'Avenant, to avoid
                            a shift of scene to England, gives the setting as 'Birnam Wood'; Lee
                            follows, adding '[Stage light.]'; Bell, following Rowe, gives
                                'the King of England's Palace'. This scene is cut
                            by about 77 lines in Padua PB; D'Avenant reduces Shakespeare's 240 lines
                            to 167 (divided into two scenes, IV.iii and IV.v); Douai MS omits about
                            10 lines; Bell, according to Gentleman's note, omits about 80 lines,
                            "which retained, would render it painfully tedious"; Lee keeps as a
                            single scene but reduces the lines to roughly 148. In view of all this,
                            it is surprising to find PB cutting only about 43 lines.8 greue] Hand IV substitutes 'greue' for F
                            'wail' (crossed through). Part of larger, and differently handled, cuts
                            in Padua PB, D'Avenant, Bell, Lee.33-34 wear thou . . . afear'd.] Crossed
                            through (Hand ?III). Cut in general revision by D'Avenant, Lee.62 matrons] The blot on this word seems to be
                            offset from the facing page.82 more, I] Hand ?III crosses through F 'that'
                            in the phrase 'more, that I'. Part of larger cuts in Padua PB,
                            D'Avenant, Bell, Lee.94 Doctor [crossed through]] Hand II
                            (crossed through by Hand IV). Hand II thus includes the Doctor episode,
                            also retained in Padua PB.Image of prompt-book page 725113 Rosse] Hand IV. This call, which replaces
                            Hand II's call at 146, would suggest that Hand IV is responsible for the
                            deletions through 137.115 Cut] Hand ?IV. It is not clear whether
                            'Cut' is intended to  refer to the
                            two following cuts or to the cut at 171-173 ('and . . sicken.').117-123 Devilish Macbeth . . .
                                detraction.] Circled and criss-crossed by Hand IV. Padua PB,
                            D'Avenant retain substantially but omit 120-121 ('but . . . me ;'); Lee
                            retains general sense but rewrites.123 Here I abjure] Hand IV interlines 'I' (or
                            possibly 'i'), with a caret, after F 'Here'. D'Avenant reads 'I abjure';
                            Bell cuts 123-131 ('Here . . . self,'); Lee cuts the first part of 123
                            ('Unspeak . . . detraction.') and links 'Here abjure' with the end of
                            122.125-137 I am . . . Quarrel.] Circled in three
                            stages and criss-crossed by Hand IV. D'Avenant cuts 125-131 ('I . . .
                            self,'), rewrites 133-135, and cuts 136-137 ('... Quarrel.'); for Bell,
                            see 123, above; Lee, after turning 123-125 ('Here . . . Nature,') into
                            'And here abjure my former accusation:', cuts 125-131 ('I . . . self,'),
                            adopts D'Avenant's version of 133-135, preceding it with 'Come, cheer
                            thy drooping / Spirits--', and cuts 136-137 ('... Quarrel.').133 thy approach, here] Hand III crosses
                            through 'here' in F 'thy here approach,' and inserts 'here' after
                            'approach,'. Cut in the rewriting by D'Avenant, Lee; Douai MS changes to
                            'thy coming hither'. It will be noted that Hand III's change here
                            suggests that he originally included these lines, and probably those of
                            the preceding cut, and supports the view that the cutting at this point
                            is the work of Hand IV (see above, 113).139 s.d.-159 Enter a Doctor. / Mal. Well .
                                . . Grace.] Circled by Hand III. The ink lines under 'King,'
                            (147) and 157 suggest a tentative first cutting by Hand II. Padua PB
                            retains the Doctor but cuts 149 ('How . . . ')-159; D'Avenant cuts the
                            Doctor but retains eight lines on the King's healing power (completely
                            rewritten); Bell, Lee, Collier MS cut as in PB. Gentleman's comment
                            (Bell) is pungent and to the point: "The author has here lugged in, by
                            neck and heels, a doctor, for the strange purpose of paying a gross
                            compliment to that royal line, which ridiculously arrogated a power of
                            curing the evil, by a touch. But that scene is properly left out in the
                            representation." This note, as usual, is considerably softened in the
                            second edition (1774).145 Rosse [crossed through]] Hand
                            II's call is deleted by Hand IV (see above, 113).171-173 and good . . . sicken.] Circled and
                            crisscrossed by Hand ?III. D'Avenant reduces to 'There good Mens lives
                            expire,  Dying e're they
                            sicken.'.191-192 fame geues n&lt;one&gt;[or
                                n&lt;ot&gt;]] Hand IV substitutes these words for F 'none, /
                            That Christendome gives out.' (crossed through) . Another hand draws a
                            line under (perhaps intended to be through) Hand IV's awkward scribble
                            and repeats above 'fame gives n&lt;one&gt; [or n&lt;ot&gt;]'.
                            D'Avenant cuts 191-192 ('... out.'); Bell, Lee retain, but Lee reads 'is
                            none' for F 'none,'.201 tongue,] Hand ?IV crosses through F 'for
                            ever' after 'tongue,'.220 man.] A large ink blot has accidentally
                            obscured this word.Image of prompt-book page 726221 &lt;A&gt;ct] Hand II.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e2276</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div1_sct</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">V.V.i.(opening) &lt;Co&gt;urt.] Hand I. Following
                            Rowe, Bell gives the setting as 'an Anti-Chamber, in Macbeth's
                                Castle'; Lee gives simply 'an antichamber'; Salmon
                            Lee PB adds prompt note 'Table on.' following opening s.d. D'Avenant
                            reduces this scene to thirty-six lines, and Douai MS makes small cuts
                            amounting to about eight lines. Padua PB, as here, leaves the scene
                            untouched; Bell is generally faithful to the original but cuts 65-67;
                            Lee substantially restores Shakespeare's text but makes a number of
                            deletions and does some rewriting, reducing the scene to about sixty
                            lines.4 &lt;La&gt;dy.] Hand II.50 Macbeth] Hand IV. This early call for
                            Macbeth was dictated by the deletion of scene ii. Note that only Macbeth
                            is called (see below, V.iii).63-64 Macbeth, Cathnes / Angus Rosse [all crossed
                                    through]] Hand II. This call was naturally cancelled
                            when scene ii was omitted. Note that Ross is substituted for Lennox and
                            that Angus is here listed for the first and only time by Hand II.V.ii.(opening) Towne] Hand I. Hand ?II circles and Hand ?III crisscrosses the
                                whole scene for deletion. D'Avenant adapts part of this scene
                            to one between Donalbain, Fleance, and Lennox; Bell, like PB, omits the
                            scene; Lee, giving the setting as 'the field' (after Rowe),
                            retains the scene substantially, but assigns it to 'Rosse, Lenox,
                            Caithness, Angus, &amp;c.' (altered in Salmon-Lee PB to just Ross and
                            Lennox).(opening) Cut] Hand ?IV.Image of prompt-book page 72715 Macbeth Doctor] Hand II (at the top of p.
                            727, sig. 3Q1) See below.V.iii.(opening) doctor] Hand IV. This call has been
                            written partly across F 'Scena' and is made because of the
                            dropping of the Doctor in the opening F s.d. Another call for the
                            Doctor, also by Hand ?IV, appears directly opposite Hand IV's call,
                            after  F 'Tertia.', but has
                            been heavily smudged out with ink. See below.(opening) Servant] Hand II.(opening) Enter Macbeth, and
                                Attendants.] Hand ?IV lightly crosses out F
                                'Doctor,'. Hand II seems to have planned the scene as in F
                            (see above, V.ii.25). When, however, scene ii was cut, by Hand ?III, it
                            became necessary to change the Doctor's entrance to avoid an exit at the
                            end of V.i and immediate re-entry at the beginning at V.iii. The initial
                            move to get rid of scene ii has been attributed to Hand III because the
                            Doctor's entrance at 33-34 is partly in Hand III ('Enter [Hand
                                IV] Doc&lt;tor&gt; [Hand III]') and would seem to
                            suggest that Hand III, therefore, had something to do with the cutting
                            of scene ii. Such an explanation supposes that Hand III allowed Hand
                            II's call for Macbeth and the Doctor at V.ii.15 to serve, neglecting to
                            cancel the call for the Doctor at that point. Why the call for the
                            Doctor, tentatively assigned to Hand ?IV, at the beginning of scene iii
                            was deleted (if it was not accidentally smudged) is not clear. D'Avenant
                            omits the Doctor; Bell, Lee enter him at 37, essentially as in PB (the
                            first edition of Bell, 1773, accidentally retained him in the opening
                            s.d.).13 Seyton [Hand II] Smyth [Hand
                                III]] On the actor Smith, see the Introduction, p.2.33-34 s.d. Enter [Hand IV] Doc&lt;tor&gt;
                                    [Hand III]] See the discussion above.36 Give me mine Armour:] Crossed through (Hand
                            IV). The line carried on across the right margin from the deletion may
                            be intended to mark the point of the Doctor's actual entrance. This is
                            the first of three cuts relating to Macbeth's armor (see below, 48 and
                            v.51-52), and it would seem that the intention was to dress Macbeth in
                            some costume more nearly contemporary; if so, then 33-34, above, were
                            overlooked. Note that the reference to Macbeth's shield at V.viii.32-34
                            is part of a cut by Hand III. That this was the intention, however, is
                            suggested by the deletion of all references to armor in D'Avenant,
                            followed by Lee (except for the reference to 'Hamess' in V.v.51-52);
                            Bell retains the references to armor, indicating, perhaps, a retum to
                            more historical costuming (see, however, p. 8, note 17).39 Cure her of that] Hand III crosses through
                            F 'from' and interlines 'of' above. Hand III thus restores the reading
                            of F1 and F2.39-46 Malcol&lt;me&gt; / Seywar&lt;d&gt; /
                                Macdu&lt;ff&gt; / Seyw: S&lt;on&gt; / Mente&lt;th&gt; /
                                Cathn&lt;es&gt; [the last two crossed
                                     out by Hand
                                IV]] Hand II. See below, scene iv.42 Raise out . . . Brain,] Circled (Hand IV) .
                            Presumably before the line was circled, Hand III made some change in F
                            'Raise' ('Raze' F1, F2), possibly changing it to 'Raisd' (a reading
                            which does not make much sense). Part of the general cut of the Doctor
                            episode in D'Avenant; Bell, Lee keep the line, reading 'Raze' and 'rase'
                            respectively.48 Come, put . . . Staffe:] Circled (Hand IV).
                            Cut in D'Avenant, Lee.61-62 Doct. Were I . . . here.]
                            Circled and crisscrossed (Hand III). Cut in D'Avenant, Bell, Lee; Douai
                            MS reads 'find' for F 'draw' in 62.V.iv.(opening) Grou&lt;e&gt;] Hand I. Bell gives
                            the setting as 'Birnam wood' (after Rowe's 'A Wood');
                            Lee, as 'the field'.(opening) Macduff, and Roose and
                                    Souldiers Marching.] Hand III crosses through F
                                'Seywards Son, Menteth, Cathnes, Angus,' and Hand IV
                            inserts 'and Roose' before F 'and Souldiers'. Hand II had
                            earlier crossed through 'Angus,'. Note that 'Seyw: S&lt;on&gt;' was not
                            deleted in Hand II's call (V.iii.39-46); he has no lines in the scene.
                            D'Avenant includes 'Malcolm, Donalbain, Seymour [his equivalent of
                                Seyward], Macduff, Lenox, Fleance,'; Douai MS adds Ross; Bell,
                            'Malcolm, Siward, Macduff, Siward's Son, Lenox, Angus,'; Lee,
                            'Malcolm, Seyward, Macduff, young Seyward, Rosse, Lenox,
                            Caithness, Angus, &amp;c.' (Lee-Salmon PB deletes Caithness and
                            Angus).1-2 Macb&lt;eth&gt; / Seyton] Hand II.2, 3, 7 R] Hand III assigns Menteith's two
                            speeches and the 'Sold.' speech to Ross, crossing through
                                'Ment.' at 2 and 'Sold.' at 7 but leaving
                                'Ment.' untouched at 3. Bell, Lee cut the 'Sold.'
                            speech; D'Avenant rewrites the opening lines, cuts Menteith's first
                            speech, and gives his second and the 'Sold.' speech to Malcolm;
                            Bell reassigns Menteith's speeches to Lennox; Lee again rewrites the
                            opening lines, partly from D'Avenant, cuts Menteith's first speech, and
                            gives his second to Lennox.14-16 Macd. Let our . . .
                                Souldiership.] Circled (Hand ?IV). D'Avenant rewrites the
                            scene completely after 9; Douai MS cuts 11-16 (' . . . Souldiership.');
                            Lee cuts and adapts part of D'Avenant's rewriting.Image of prompt-book page 72819-21] What looks like a carelessly marked
                            circling of these lines is an offset from the facing page (729, sig.
                            3Q2).V.v.(opening) &lt;Ca&gt;stle] Hand I. Bell,
                            following Rowe's 'The Castle' gives the setting as 'the
                                Castle of Dunsinane'; Lee, as 'the inside
                                 of
                                Dunsinane-castle' (and Lee-Salmon PB indicates that
                            Macbeth, etc. enter 'out of the Castle').(opening s.d.) Enter Macbeth,
                                Seyton,] Hand ?IV circles F 'and Souldiers, with
                                Drum and Dolours.' (see Hand II's call at V.iv.1-2). D'Avenant
                            introduces 'Macbeth, and Souldier'; Bell, 'Macbeth, Seyton,
                                and Officers'; Lee, 'Macbeth, Seyton, and
                            soldiers'.8 &lt;Mes&gt;senger / &lt;Tott&gt;erdell] Hands
                            II and III. On the actor Totterdale, see the Introduction, p.2.11 my hair] Hand ?IV crosses through F 'Fell
                            of' after 'my'. D'Avenant omits the phrase and greatly cuts the speech;
                            Douai MS cuts 11-13 ('and . . . in't.').30-34 &lt;Ma&gt;lcolme / &lt;Sey&gt;ward /
                                &lt;M&gt;acduffe] Hand II.51-52 Ring the . . . back.] Partly circled
                            (Hand ?IV). D'Avenant cuts; Lee-Salmon PB adds prompter's note after
                            'alarum-bell': 'Ring the Bell--'.V.vi.(opening) Macbeth] Hand II.6 young Seyward] Hand II.V.vii.(opening) Allarums] Hand IV.4 s.d. Sttet [Hand IV] Enter Rosse
                                    [Hand III, crossed through by Hand IV] Saward [Hand
                                    IV]] First, Hand III crosses through F 'young
                                Seyward' and substitutes 'Rosse' above; then Hand IV places
                            'Sttet' before F 'Enter' and 'Saward' after and slightly above
                            the deleted F 'Seyward.' By 'Saward' Hand IV presumably intends
                            Young Siward. Having converted Siward to Seymour and deleted Young
                            Siward throughout, D'Avenant here substitutes Lennox.5 Malcolme / Seyward] Hand II.5, 6, 8, 10 R] Hand III substitutes 'R' for F
                                'Y. Sey.' (crossed through). Despite Hand IV's restoration
                            of Young Siward, Hand III's attributions to Ross remain unchanged.10 liest abhorred] Some hand, in pencil,
                            crosses through F 'thou' after 'liest', thus restoring the F1 reading
                            (first editorially restored by Pope). D'Avenant rewrites this speech
                            (see next note).11 Oh my deare Country pardon me yt &lt;I&gt; / doe in a cause soe good soe / quikly
                                dye] Hand II inserts this couplet following F 'speak'st.'.
                            Compare Lennox's dying lines in D'Avenant: 'Oh my dear Country, Pardon
                            me that I, / Do in a Cause so great, so quickly Die.'.13 s.d. Enter Macduffe.] There is no
                            advance call for Macduff.Image of prompt-book page 72923 s.d. Macbeth / Macduffe] Hand II. For an
                            explanation of the mistreatment this last page (729, sig. 3Q2) of the PB
                            has received (i.e., the deletion of the running title and catchword,
                             the four vertical lines running the
                            length of the page, the deletion of some of the prompt materials), see
                            the Introduction, pp. 6-7.V.viii.3 upon them. / Enter Macduff. /
                                Macd. Turn Hell-hound, turn.] The page is damaged at
                            this point, affecting these lines, but there is no evidence of any
                            cutting.13-14 Malcolme / Seyward / Rosse] Hand II.
                            This call is crossed through, but probably by the nineteenth-century
                            exhibitor. Earlier cancelled calls are more roughly scratched through or
                            blotted. All the deletions on this final page are made with a single pen
                            stroke.14 let the divill] Hand III interlines
                            'divill' above F 'Angell' (crossed through). D'Avenant reads as in PB;
                            Douai MS reads the line as 'And let thy angel whom still thou hast
                            serv'd'.32-34 the last.... enough] Hand III crosses
                            through these F lines and writes in the lower margin below 'if by a man
                            it be thy ['thy' crossed through and 'my' written
                                above] Chance to dye / Fight. / Macb: farwell vaine world and
                            that which is most vaine / Ambition. / Macd: Soe may all tyrants fall.
                            exit'. Compare D'Avenant: 'If by a Man it be thy Fate to Die. /
                                [They Fight, Macbeth falls. They shout within. / /
                                Macd. This for . . . I'le as a Trophy bear / Away his Sword, to
                            witness my Revenge. [Exit Macduff. / Macb. Farewell
                            vain World, and what's most vain in it, Ambition. / [Dies.'.
                            The added lines in PB have been crossed through, but again presumably by
                            the nineteenth-century exhibitor. The action in PB is not entirely
                            clear. The F s.d. at 34 'Exeunt fighting. Alarums. / Enter fighting,
                                and Macbeth slain.' has been left untouched, but the added
                            lines in PB seem to rule out any exit and make it clear that Macbeth is
                            slain on stage immediately after fighting with Macduff, who then exits,
                            as in D'Avenant. It is surprising that PB retains the business of
                            Macbeth's head, in view of D'Avenant's more decorous substitution of his
                            sword, followed by both Bell and Lee. Since Macbeth's body apparently
                            remains on stage (a difficulty also with the F text), one must suppose
                            that Macduff exits with the head at 34. Bell, Lee give Macbeth an
                            eight-line dying speech (described by Gentleman as "furnished by Mr.
                                Garrick, to give the actor more eclat"; though he admits
                            that "from the desperate state of Macbeth's mind, we think his immediate
                            death most natural."); the speech begins with two lines suggested by
                            D'Avenant's line ''Tis done! the scene
                             of life will quickly close. /
                            Ambition's vain, delusive dreams are fled,'.35-53 Mal. I would . . . comfort.]
                            The lines have been deleted in probably three stages. First, 38-53 (' .
                            . . him.') were partly circled and crisscrossed by Hand III; second
                            36-37 seem to have been circled and the last half of 53 crossed through
                            by Hand IV; third, 35 was included in the cut with 36-37 by Hand IV
                            (perhaps the third stage was actually a part of the second). The
                            original arrangement (Hand III's) gave Malcolm and Siward
                            three-and-a-half lines before Macduff's entry at 53; the final
                            arrangement (Hand IV's) brings Macduff on directly after Malcolm,
                            Siward, Ross, etc. D'Avenant reduces the F lines to seven; Bell, Lee
                            retain F essentially unchanged.42 Macduffe] Hand II. Crossed through,
                            presumably by nineteenth-century exhibitor.64-73 What's more . . . place:] Circled (Hand
                            IV). D'Avenant rewrites these lines completely, as well as 74-75, and is
                            followed by Lee.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e557</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_1.1</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">I.i.Image of prompt-book page 711(opening) Rock] Hand I. This setting is
                            regularly associated with the appearance of the Witches by Hand I,
                            though Hand IV substitutes 'Caue' in IV.i. Bell, Lee: 'an open
                                Place' (after Theobald); Lee adds '[Stage dark.]'.6 King &amp;c.] Hand II. This is the only
                            example of such a generalized prompt call in this PB.7 There I go to meet] Hand V interlines 'I go',
                            with a caret, above F 'to'. So Pope, Bell; D'Avenant reads: 'There we
                            resolve to meet'; Lee, 'There we'll go to meet'.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e581</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_1.2</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">I.ii.(opening s.d.) Donalbaine, with
                                attendants] Hand ?II deletes F 'Lenox,'
                            following 'Donalbaine,'. PB omits Lennox throughout. D'Avenant,
                            Lee substitute Seyton for the F 'bleeding Captain'.1 Court] Hand I. Part of the Julius
                                Caesar couplet has been written over 'Court'. Bell, Lee: 'a
                                Palace at Foris' (after Theobald, Rowe); Lee adds '[Stage
                                light.]'.7 Doubtful long] Hand V interlines 'long', with
                            a caret, after F 'Doubtful'. So Pope, Bell, Lee; D'Avenant reads: 'It
                            was doubtful ;' for F 'Doubtful . . . stood,'.11-15 Rosse. [crossed through by Hand III] /
                                macduffe [crossed through by Hand IV] / Rosse] Hands
                            II, III, IV. See below, 45 s.d.15 all too] Hand ?V crosses through 's' in F
                            'all's too'. So Pope, Bell, Lee; D'Avenant rewrites 14-15.26 break] Hand ?V crosses through 'ing' in F
                            'breaking'. So Pope, Bell; D'Avenant, Lee rewrite the passage.38 So they redoubled stroaks upon] Hand ?V
                            deletes F 'doubly' and interlines 'up', with a caret, above F 'on'
                            ('vpon' F1 ) . So Pope, Bell, Lee; D'Avenant rewrites 36-41; Douai MS
                            reads: 'for doubly they redoubled stroakes on'.41 I cannot tell:] Crossed through (Hand
                            ?II).45 s.d.] Hand II first deletes F 'and
                            Angus.'; next Hand III deletes F 'Enter Rosse' and writes above
                            F s.d. 'Enter Macduffe'; this in turn is deleted by Hand IV, which then
                            restores 'Rosse', following deleted F s.d., but neglects to restore
                                'Enter' (compare the prompt call at 11-15, above) . In
                            substituting Macduff for Ross, Hand III was following D'Avenant, who
                            completely omits the characters of Ross and Angus from his version of
                            the play. PB cuts the character of Angus throughout, though Hand II
                            inadvertently included his name in the prompt call (later cancelled) for
                            V.ii. Lee retains Angus, but Lee-Salmon PB deletes him here and
                            elsewhere; both retain Ross. Gentleman (Bell) remarks that at Covent
                            Garden the "characters of Rosse and Angus have been
                            judicially blended . . . into those of Macduff and Lenox, to make them
                            more worthy the attention of good performers and the audience"; Drury
                            Lane, however, with Garrick, retained all four characters.45 Thane of Rosse. [crossed
                                    through] Macduffe [crossed through]] Hand
                            III first crosses through F 'Thane of Rosse.' and writes
                            'Macduffe', but Hand IV, after deleting 'Macduffe', fails to restore
                            Ross. Something (perhaps 'Ma') has been written in the extreme right
                            margin opposite Hand III's 'Macduffe', but the leaf has been shaved.
                            D'Avenant substitutes 'Noble Macduff!'.46-47 Lenox. Whathast . . . strange.]
                            Circled (Hand II). This deletion of Lennox's speech follows the deletion
                            of Lennox in the opening s.d. D'Avenant, Bell, Lee omit 47.47, 48, 58, 66 macd] Hand III deletes F
                                'Rosse.' and substitutes 'macd' or (66) 'Macd'. Although
                            Hand IV removes Macduff from the scene, the altered speech prefixes
                            remain uncancelled. Compare V.vii.5,6,8,10.48 worthy Thane? [crossed through] braue
                                Mac&lt;duffe&gt; [crossed through]] Hand III deletes
                            F 'worthy Thane?' and supplies 'braue Mac&lt;duffe&gt;'
                            following it; Hand IV then deletes 'braue Mac&lt;duffe&gt;'. No attempt
                            is made to restore the original F reading. D'Avenant retains 'worthy
                                Thane?'; so, too, Bell, Lee.50 Witches] Hand 11.53 gan] 'be' of F 'began' crossed through by
                            Hand ?V. So Pope, Bell, Lee. D'Avenant substitutes 'long
                            maintain'd'.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e721</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_1.3</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">I.iii.Image of prompt-book page 712(opening) &lt;Ro&gt;ck] Hand I. Bell, Lee:
                                'a Heath' (after Rowe). Lee adds '[Stage dark.]'.
                            D'Avenant brings on the 'Witches flying'; Lee-Salmon PB,
                            interpreting the 'Witches rise again' in Lee, precedes the
                            scene with: `x Ring for 3 Traps to rais Witches / Stage Dark /
                            Thunder Lightning &amp; Rain'; in Bell the Witches 'rise from under the
                            stage.'.3-4 drum / Redy] Hand IV. A warning note for F
                                'Drum within.' at 29. Lee-Salmon PB gives no advance call
                            for the drum at 29, although it keeps the F s.d. in the form of '
                                [Drum heard within.]'. It does, however, call for 'Drum /
                            ready' at 35 in preparation for Macbeth's and Banquo's entry to a
                            'Scotch Ma&lt;rch&gt;'.11-13 Macbeth / Banquo.] Hand 11. For the
                            entry at 37 D'Avenant adds 'Attendants' and Bell 'A
                                March.... Soldiers and other Attendants' (after Rowe); Lee adds
                            only 'A march beat.', but the Lee-Salmon PB notes in its call for
                            Macbeth and Banquo 'men to cry / halt', and the entry is made 'PS'.39 How far . . . Soris?] Crossed
                            through (Hand III).41] PB appears to read 'Earth;' for F 'Earth,'
                            but the reading is probably the result of an ink smudge from the facing
                            page.44-45 By each . . . Lips:] Crossed through
                            (Hand II).55-57 prediction hereafter / of Royal hope,]
                            Hand III crosses through F 'Of . . . and' and 'That . . . withal';
                            'hereafter' may have been deleted; at any rate the ink is so badly
                            smudged as to make the word almost illegible. D'Avenant keeps the
                            substance of F but rephrases (PB's 'hereafter' is not from D'Avenant);
                            Lee slightly rephrases but deletes 57 ('That . . . withal').62 Rosse] Hand II.88 s.d. macduffe [crossed through] enter
                                here. Rosse] In the F s.d. 'Enter Rosse, and Angus.'
                            Hand II originally deletes 'and Angus.'; Hand III then deletes
                            the rest of the F s.d. and writes above it 'macduffe enter here.';
                            finally, Hand IV deletes 'macduffe' and adds 'Rosse'. It should be noted
                            that Hand II's original call for Ross was never deleted. Hand III's
                            'macduffe' follows D'Avenant; Bell, Lee retain the F s.d., but
                            Lee-Salmon PB deletes 'and Angus' and adds 'Flourish' before
                            the entry, which is made 'LD OP'.89 Ma:] Hand III substitutes 'Ma:' for F
                            'Ross.' This speech-prefix was not changed after Ross was restored by
                            Hand IV, nor did Hand III alter Ross's speech-prefix at 104.93-98 silenc'd with . . . post,] Circled (Hand
                            III). D'Avenant reduces and rewrites these lines.100-103 Ang. We are . . . thee,]
                            Circled (Hand II). D'Avenant omits; Bell, Lee retain, but Lee-Salmon PB
                            deletes.Image of prompt-book page 713109 Ross] Hand III. 'Ross' written over F
                                'Ang.'. D'Avenant assigns to Macduff. The speech is still
                            given to Angus in Lee-Salmon PB despite his omission from the scene (see
                            88 s.d., above).120 throughly beleiv'd] Hand 11 circles or
                            doubly crosses through F 'trusted home,' adding 'throughly beleiv'd'
                            after it. D'Avenant rephrases the half line as 'If all be true,'.122 Besides the . . . Cawdor.]
                            Circled or doubly crossed through (Hand II). D'Avenant and Lee both
                            rephrase slightly.125-126 Winne us . . . consequence.] Crossed
                            through (Hand ?III). D'Avenant completely rephrases.127 Cousin] The 's' in F 'Cousins' has been
                            deleted (Hand ?III). This change was dictated by the omission of Angus.
                            Although Lee-Salmon PB deletes Angus, it fails to correct to the
                            singular form; Ross is made to retire 'OP'. D'Avenant omits the
                            half-line.127 King Malcolm / Donalbin] Hand II.129 I thank you Gentlemen:] Crossed through
                            (Hand III). Lee omits, and D'Avenant, in rephrasing Macbeth's whole
                            speech, also omits.135 fflourish] Hand II. Presumably an advance
                            call for the F 'Flourish.' at the beginning of I.iv.137-142 present fears . . . not.] Circled
                            (Hand III). Except for 'present fears' D'Avenant completely recasts
                            these lines; Lee keeps them through 138 and then reverts to a cut
                            version of D'Avenant.145-146 Like strange Garments which weare / not easy
                                but wth help of use.] Hand II substitutes
                            these lines, crossing through F 'our' and 'cleave . . . use.'. Compare
                            D'Avenant: 'and resemble / New Garments, which but seldom fit men well,
                            / Unless by help of use.'. Lee retains F essentially, but with some
                            slight influence from D'Avenant.152-155 Mackbeth / Banqo / Rosse] Hand IV.
                            Hand II seems to have omitted a call for these characters at I.iv.14,
                            though it may have come at the foot of the page (column one), which has
                            been partly torn off.154 The Interim . . . it,] Circled
                            (Hand III). D'Avenant rephrases.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e889</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_1.4</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">I.iv.(opening) Cou&lt;rt&gt;] Hand I. Following
                            Rowe, Bell and Lee give the setting as 'the Palace'; Lee adds
                                '[Stage light.]'; Lee-Salmon
                             PB notes ' Door open
                            OP.'.(opening s.d.)] F 'Lenox' crossed
                            through. Note that the F 'Attendants' are, as usual, not
                            included in Hand II's advance call for this entry at I.iii.127.14 s.d. Banquo and Capt: Ros] Hand
                            III crosses through F 'Ross, and Angus.' and writes above 'and
                            Capt: R'; Hand IV then adds 'os'. D'Avenant introduces Macduff in the
                            place of Ross and Angus; Lee-Salmon PB deletes Angus and marks the entry
                            as 'LD PS'.30-31 nor must . . . so:] Circled (Hand III).
                            Lee cuts; D'Avenant rephrases; Bell retains but substitutes 'and' (Rowe)
                            for F nor.32 Lady.] Hand II. Lee-Salmon PB adds 'a
                            written letter' below its call for Lady Macbeth.44 The Rest . . . you:] Circled (Hand III).
                            The last half of the line is missing in PB, since a tear at the bottom
                            of p. 713 (Sig. 3O5) affects the ends of lines 36-49. D'Avenant
                            completely rephrases.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e939</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_1.5</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">I.v.Image of prompt-book page 714 (first one)(opening) &lt;Gar&gt;den] Hand I. Bell, Lee
                            give 'Apartment in Macbeth's Castle, at Inverness'
                            (from Pope, after Rowe).(opening) &lt;M&gt;essenger] Hand II.32 Macbeth] Hand II.57-62 King / Malcolme / Donalbin / Banquo / Macduffe
                                / Rosse] Hand II.65 Lady] Hand IV.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e971</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_1.6</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">I.vi.(opening) Court] Hand I. Bell, Lee give
                                'before Macbeth's Castle-gate' (from Theobald,
                            after Rowe).(opening s.d.)] PB deletes F 'Lenox'
                            and 'Angus'; these are presumably Hand II's deletions, since
                            these characters are omitted in the advance call at I.v.57-62. D'Avenant
                            omits Ross and Angus; Lee-Salmon PB deletes Angus and marks entry as
                            'OP'.3-9 This Guest . . . haunt:] Circled (Hand III)
                            and underlined (probably by Hand II), though the circling does not seem
                            to include 'This Guest of Summer,' (underlined), which is necessary to
                            the cut. D'Avenant slightly rephrases; Douai MS omits 3 ('This Guest . .
                            . ')-9.9 observ'd it &amp;] Hand ?II adds 'it &amp;'
                            after F 'observ'd', probably influenced by D'Avenant's 'observ'd the
                            Air, / 'Tis delicate.'.12-14 Herein I . . . trouble.] Circled (Hand
                            III). D'Avenant retains but substitutes 'us welcome' for F 'god-eyld
                            us'; Douai MS reads 13-14: 'how you shall thank us for your present
                            trouble.'; Bell retains but reads 'Heav'n-eyld us'; Lee retains, but
                            Lee-Salmon PB cuts 12-14 ('Which . . . trouble.').20 Macbeth.] Hand II.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1012</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_1.7</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">I.vii.Image of prompt-book page 715 (first one)(opening) Lady] Hand II.(opening s.d.) ] F s.d. 'Enter a Sewer,
                                and divers Servants with Dishes and Service over the Stage.'
                            has been crossed through by Hand III. PB marks no new scene setting,
                            thus continuing the 'Court' setting of scene vi. Padua PB, D'Avenant,
                            Bell, and Lee also bring Macbeth on without the banquet preparations;
                            Lee enters him as 'musing'; Lee-Salmon PB enters him 'PS';
                            Douai MS reduces F s.d. to 'Divers Servants with dishes pass over / The
                            Stage--'. D'Avenant, Bell, and Lee omit F 'Ho boyes. Torches.';
                            their retention in PB is probably an oversight. Bell, Lee (subs.) change
                            the scene to 'an Apartment in Macbeth's Castle' (from
                            Theobald after Rowe).2-12 if th' Assassination . . . lips.] Circled
                            (Hand ?II). F3 makes nonsense of 10-11 by combining them. Padua PB cuts
                            5-12 ('Heere . . . lips.'); D'Avenant reduces to five flat lines; Bell
                            as in PB cuts through 'Success:' (4).45-46 Act / Banq [crossed through]]
                            Hand II starts to write 'Banquo' but does not even complete the 'q'.
                            Since the characters are not given advance calls for the first scene of
                            a new act, the call for Banquo was a slip of Hand II's and probably
                            deleted by him.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1055</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_2.1</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">II.i.(opening) Chambe&lt;r&gt;] Hand I. The 'm'
                            in 'Chambe&lt;r&gt;' is far from clear. Bell, Lee (subs.) give the scene
                            as 'a Hall in Macbeth's Castle'; Lee adds '[Stage
                                dark.]', and Lee-Salmon PB notes 'Door OP Shut'.Image of prompt-book page 714 (second one)8-9 Merciful Powers . . . repose.] Underlined
                            (Hand II) and circled (Hand III). D'Avenant rephrases; Bell retains but
                            omits 'Give me my Sword ;' in 9; Lee omits 8-9 (' . . . Sword:'). There
                            is no advance call for Macbeth's and the Servant's entry at 9 in PB.27-28 Beell / Redy] Hand IV.38 Lady] Hand II.40-45 I see . . . rest:] Circled (Hand II).
                            D'Avenant omits all but the last line-and-a-half.53-54 Alarum'd by . . . pace,] Circled (Hand
                            III). D'Avenant rephrases.57 which they may walk,] Crossed through (Hand
                            ?II). Part of a longer cut in D'Avenant; Lee substitutes 'feel not my
                            tread,'; Douai MS omits as in PB.58 desines] Hand III substitutes 'desines' for
                            F 'where about,' (underlined by Hand ?III). Part of a cut in D'Avenant;
                            Lee reads the line as: 'Thy very stones shou'd check my purpose,'.60 Whilest] Hand ?III inserts 't' after F
                            'Whiles'. Part of a cut in Bell, Lee.63-64 Bell / Rings my coronation and thy
                                Knell.] Hand III substitutes 'Bell . . . Knell.' for F
                            'Knell, That . . . hell.' (F 'Knell' crossed through by Hand III; 'That
                            . . . hell.' by Hand II). Based on D'Avenant: 'bell / That rings my
                            Coronation, and thy Knell.'.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1113</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_2.2</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">II.ii.(opening) Macbeth] Hand II. PB marks no
                            change of scene setting. Bell, Lee ignore F 'Scaena Secunda.'.
                            In an advance prompt note for this scene Lee-Salmon PB calls for '2
                            Daggers / &amp; Blood / ready OP'.21 Redy / to knok] Hand IV.Image of prompt-book page 715 (second one)52 Mackduff / Rosse] Hand IV. This replaces a
                            later call by Hand II at the opening of scene iii. See below,
                            II.iii.1-46.62 multitudinous] This word appears to be
                            crossed through, but what looks like a deletion results from an ink show
                            through from verso (p. 716, sig. 3P1V).63 Porter.] Hand II.74 Macbeth] Hand IV.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1149</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_2.3</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">II.iii. (opening) Macduffe / Rosse [both crossed
                                    through by Hand IV]]  Hand II. Hand ?II has also
                            written something to the left of F 'Scena Tertia.' which may be
                            the beginning of 'Macbeth', but only the first ?three letters were
                            written and then crossed through. PB marks no new scene setting; Bell no
                            new scene (after Rowe); Lee indicates 'a hall' (but this was
                            the setting of the preceding scene); Lee-Salmon PB adds 'Door OP Shut'
                            and below 'Time giuen.'.1-46] The order of cutting and restoration in
                            these lines is uncertain. In what seems to be the final form, 5 ('Here's
                            . . . ' )-23 and 28 ('of three . . . ')-46 were cut. Judging by the inks
                            used, Hand II first deletes, by circling, the whole of 1-46, then
                            changes his mind and marks both circled sections with 'stet' and
                            'stett'. Hand III then crisscrosses 5-23 and 28-46 for deletion, adding
                            'to sle&lt;ep&gt;' at the end of 27 to complete the sense. Hand IV
                            tidies things up by placing an advance call for Macduff and Ross at
                            II.ii.52 (deleting Hand II's call at the beginning of scene iii) and an
                            advance call for Macbeth at II.ii.74. Apparently Hand II neglected to
                            mark an advance call for Macbeth; however, see above, II.iii (opening).
                            The order of events as here described presents certain problems, but I
                            am unable to offer any more satisfactory alternative. Padua PB cuts the
                            whole of the Porter's soliloquy; D'Avenant also cuts the soliloquy,
                            reduces the Porter's role to one line (he, here called Servant, and
                            Lennox enter together and after three lines Macduff enters), and
                            replaces 23-46 with eleven lines 
                            between Lennox and Macduff based on F lines 59-66; Douai MS reduces the
                            Porter's soliloquy to 'P: here's a knocking indeed: who's there in the
                            name of belzebub? anon; anon; I am coming. (Opens the doore.)' and omits
                            27-46 ('and drink . . . him.'); Bell cuts everything down to Macduff's
                            entry (24), the Servant, who has opened the 'door' to Macduff
                            and Lennox, being given F 26-27 ('Faith . . . cock:'), and then adds
                            Lennox's speech from F (59-66). These last two speeches are in italics,
                            and Gentleman (Bell) remarks: ". . . and the Italic lines, by
                            transposition, judiciously introduced to give Macbeth time for
                            change of appearance, of which, even now, he is allowed too little.";
                            Lee cuts the Porter's soliloquy, bringing Lennox on alone (Lee-Salmon PB
                            notes 'PS' ), 'who knocks at the chamber door several times pretty
                                hard, then a servant opens it.' (Lee-Salmon PB adds 'OP'),
                            follows D'Avenant's opening two speeches, inserts F 47 ('Is . . .
                            stirring?'), and adds: 'Serv. Not yet, Sir, but he'll scarce
                            lye late; he's of an active spirit, that never suffers his body to lye
                            still when once his mind is up. / Len. Well, say I wait his
                            leisure. / Serv. I will, Sir.' Collier MS shows points of
                            resemblance to Smock Alley PB, since it cuts lines 5-22 ('Here's . . .
                            Bonfire.'), 27-46 ( 'And Drink . . . him.').23 s.d. Enter Macduff, and Rosse [Hand
                                    III] Rosse [Hand II, crossed through] and
                                Ro&lt;sse&gt; [Hand III]] Hand II first deletes F
                                'and Lenox.' and writes 'Rosse' following the deletion;
                            then Hand III deletes Hand II's 'Rosse' and writes 'and Rosse' above the
                            deleted F 'and Lenox.'; finally, Hand III writes 'and
                            Ro&lt;sse&gt;' following the deleted 'Rosse' by Hand II (the order of
                            Hand III's changes may, of course, have been reversed).28 to sle&lt;ep&gt;] Hand III substitutes 'to
                            sle&lt;ep&gt;' for F 'of three things.'. See above, 1-46.49 Lenox.] This speech-prefix has been crossed
                            through but not reassigned. Presumably Hand II deleted it but failed to
                            give it to Ross, who takes Lennox's place in the scene. Lennox's
                            speech-prefixes otherwise remain untouched in this scene, though his
                            speeches must have been spoken by Ross.76 Macd.] Some hand has altered F
                                'b' in 'Macb.' to 'd', thus restoring the
                            reading of F1.Image of prompt-book page 71678 Lady] Hand II.78 s.d. Macbeth and Rosse ['Rosse' crossed
                                through]] Hand ?III deletes F 'Lenox.' and writes
                            'Rosse' below (also heavily deleted). Whoever (Hand ?IV) here deleted
                            'Rosse' neglected to cancel the advance call for his re entry at 85.
                            Despite  this oversight, I suspect
                            that he is not intended to exit with Macbeth at this point but remains
                            on stage to speak Lennox's speech (106-111).79 Banquo] Hand II.83-85 Macbeth / &lt;R&gt;osse] Hand II.88-89 &lt;Ma&gt;lcolme / &lt;Don&gt;albine]
                            Hand II.95 s.d.] Hand ?IV crosses through
                                F'Lenox,'. For Ross's re-entry, see above, 78 s.d.105 Macd.] The ink blot on this
                            speech-prefix does not indicate deletion but is a smudge from the facing
                            page (717, sig. 3P2).131-133 Lady: &amp; instantly let us meet,]
                            Hand II underlines and Hand III crosses through 132-133 ( 'And . . .
                            exposure: ' ) and inserts '&amp; instantly' (after 131). See below,
                            135-138.135-138 Feares and . . . all.] Underlined
                            (Hand II) and crossed through (Hand III). Considering this and the
                            preceding deletion together, one notes that D'Avenant also omits these
                            lines (and a good many others) and works part of 133-135 ('let . . .
                            further.') into a speech by Macbeth a few lines later. In Bell and Lee,
                            Lady Macbeth does not appear in the scene at all, apparently a
                            long-standing practice (G. W. Stone, SP, XXXVIII [1941],
                            621-22); except for references to Lady Macbeth, Lee preserves 131-138
                            essentially intact, but Bell omits 132-133 ('And . . . exposure:') as in
                            PB.139-141 Banqo [Hand IV] / Rosse / Old man
                                    [crossed through]]  Hand II originally calls for
                            'Rosse/ Old man'; then Hand IV deletes 'Old man' and inserts 'Banqo'
                            above 'Rosse'. See scene iv, s.d. (opening).</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1305</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_2.4</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">II.iv.(opening) Rock scan / Towne [crossed
                                    through]] Hand I originally gave the setting as
                            'Towne'; then Hand ? crossed through 'Towne' and inserted 'Rock scan'
                            above. The reading 'scan' is doubtful. Perhaps a form of 'scene'? Bell,
                            Lee: 'Outside of Macbeth's Castle'; Lee adds
                                '[Stage light.]'(opening) Macduffe] Hand II.(opening s.d. ) Banquo and Captaine [Hand
                                    III, 'Captaine' crossed through] / Roose [Hand
                                    IV]] The F s.d. remains untouched; Hand III inserts
                            'Banquo and Captaine' above it; Hand IV then deletes 'Captaine' and adds
                            'Roose' below (cf. I.iv.14 s.d.), clarifying the advance call at
                            II.iii.139-141 by adding 'Banqo' and deleting 'Old man'. R. C. Bald
                                (PMLA, LVI [1941], 375 n., 377-78) explains the change of
                            setting from 'Towne' to 'Rock' as the result of what seems to be an
                            appearance of the Witches later in the scene at Macduff's entrance (20)
                            and suggests that "at least one" of D'Avenant's witch songs was here
                            used (see below, 10-13, 21). Of the two witch
                             songs (D'Avenant, II.v) probably
                            the second is the more likely choice, since it alone is followed by a
                            dance in D'Avenant's version (the first sixteen lines of the song also
                            appeared in the 1673 quarto of Macbeth, interpolated between
                            scenes iii and iv, which is otherwise substantially a reprint of F1).
                            The substitution of Banquo for the Old Man in PB may also perhaps be
                            explained by the importation of the Witches, since their song might seem
                            more suitable for Banquo's ears, though it should be noted that the
                            directions implying the Witches are in Hand IV. In D'Avenant the scene
                            is carried by Lennox and Seyton, down to Macduff's entrance; nor do the
                            witch songs appear in this scene. They are part of the following scene
                            (II.v), a scene ('An Heath.') almost entirely D'Avenant's own
                            creation, and are directed at Macduff and Lady Macduff. Bell, Lee retain
                            Shakespeare's scene with Ross and the Old Man, but place it at the
                            beginning of Act III, inserting a scene with all the Witch business, but
                            minus the Macduffs, from D'Avenant II.v. Bell, Lee-Salmon PB exit the
                            Old Man just before Macduff's entry. Clearly PB, Bell, Lee have one aim
                            in mind: entertainment at any cost. Lee gives no scene setting; in Bell
                                'The SCENE changes to a Wood. Thunder and Lightning.'.1-2 Threescore and . . . time,] Circled (Hand
                            III). This cut and those at 4-5 and 39 are obviously made to adapt the
                            lines in some sort to Banquo, but the Old Man's speech-prefixes remain
                            untouched. The D'Avenant Yale MS substitutes 'Three score and one' for F
                            'Threescore and ten', but the printed text cuts the whole phrase and
                            begins 'I can remember well,' thus better adapting the following lines
                            to Seyton.4-5 Ha, good . . . seest] Crossed through (Hand
                            III). D'Avenant reduces to 'Thou seest'. Collier MS cuts 6-20 ('by th'
                            clock . . . upon't').10-13 Song / Redy / daunce] Hand IV. See
                            above, II.iv (opening).Image of prompt-book page 71721 Sing heere / and daunce] Hand IV. See
                            above, II.iv (opening).27 Act] Hand II.39 Father.] Crossed through (Hand III).
                            D'Avenant, Bell, Lee cut 39-41.40 all happenesse go with you and] Hand III
                            crosses through F 'God's benison' and, with a caret, substitutes 'all
                            happenesse', at the same time crossing through F 'Sir,'. Douai MS
                            substitutes 'blessing' for F 'benison'.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1394</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_3.1</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">III.i(opening) Court] Hand I. Bell, Lee: 'an
                                Apartment in the Palace' (Theobald, after Rowe).(opening) Macbeth Lady Rosse ['Rosse' crossed
                                    through]] Hand II. The deletion of 'Rosse', by Hand
                            ?II, has been badly smudged.10 s.d.] F 'Lenox, Rosse,' crossed
                            through; 'Lenox' by Hands II and III, 'Rosse' very
                            lightly, possibly by Hand II, the hand probably responsible for deleting
                            'Rosse' in advance call above. D'Avenant gives only 'Macbeth, Lenox,
                                and Attendants.'; Bell, Lee, like D'Avenant, omit Lady
                            Macbeth, but otherwise follow F.16-17 Command me, and my dutie / is with most
                                obedient ty] Hand II circles and/or crosses through F 'upon',
                            'to the which' ('the' separately circled), the 's' in 'duties', 'Are',
                            'a', and 'indissoluble tye' and substitutes 'and', 'is', and 'obedient
                            ty'. Before inserting 'and' Hand II seems to have intended reading 'to
                            which'. D'Avenant rewrites; Douai MS reads 'lay your commands on me, to
                            which . . . tye'; Bell, Lee retain but read 'Lay' for F 'Let' in 15
                            (after D'Avenant and Rowe; compare Douai MS).22 farlow] Hand ?III. Nothing seems to be
                            known about this actor, and his name appears in none of the other Smock
                            Alley prompt-books. W. S. Clark (The Early Irish Stage, 1955,
                            p. 207) places him with the Smock Alley company "c. 1674," but
                            this date depends, I assume, on dating the Macbeth PB somewhat
                            earlier than I believe likely. See Introduction, p. 2. Farlow here plays
                            the Servant, and the position of the advance call at 22 suggests that he
                            was intended to enter about 44 (as in the Padua PB); editors, from Rowe
                            on (followed by Bell, Lee), assume the Servant to be one of the F
                                'Attendants' who enter at 11.24 Is't far] F 'far' appears to be heavily
                            deleted, but the mark is only the result of an ink smudge from the
                            facing page (716, sig. 3P1).28 two] Hand II crosses through F 'twain.' and
                            writes 'two' following. So D'Avenant, Douai MS, Lee.38-39 I wish . . . backs.] The marks of
                            deletion (by Hand III) are ambiguous. Possibly (as in Padua PB) both
                            lines are marked for deletion, but it seems more likely that only 39 is
                            meant to be deleted, since D'Avenant omits only 39 (as does Lee) and the
                            scene has earlier shown signs of his influence.52 53 Serva&lt;nt&gt; / Murt&lt;herers&gt;]
                            Hand II. In connection with Macbeth's interview with the two Murderers,
                            it is worth noting that Padua PB cuts the interview with the Murderers
                             completely and that Lee-Salmon PB
                            turns the interview into one between Seyton and Macbeth, in which, with
                            certain necessary slight omissions and revisions, Seyton speaks the
                            lines of both Murderers.Image of prompt-book page 71880 Past in . . . you:] Partly circled (Hand
                            ?III). Cut in D'Avenant; Douai MS, Bell cut 76-86 ('Know . . .
                            meeting.'); Lee makes substantially the same cut as in Douai MS and Bell
                            but retains 84 ('You . . . us.') in revised form.101-104 Lady / Servant / farlow] Hand II
                            ('farlow' Hand ?III). For 'farlow' see above, 22.110 care not] Hand III crosses through F 'am
                            reckless' and substitutes 'care not' above end of line. So D'Avenant,
                            Lee; Douai MS replaces F 'that I am reckless' with 'I'm careless'; Bell
                            cuts the Second Murderer's speech.122-126 Whose loves . . . Reasons.] Circled
                            and x'd through (Hand III). D'Avenant reduces to four lines and rewrites
                            heavily; Bell cuts 121-125; Lee, 122-123 (`but . . . down:').132-133 alwayes thought . . . clearness;]
                            Circled (Hand III). Cut in Douai MS, Pope, Bell, Lee; D'Avenant
                            rewrites.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1490</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_3.2</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">III.ii.(opening) Macbeth] Hand II. PB marks no
                            change of setting here (so Rowe and Lee); D'Avenant interpolates a new
                            scene (between Macduff and Lady Macduff) between F scenes i and ii; Bell
                            gives 'another Apartment in the Palace' (after Theobald).6-7 Curtaine / ready] Hand III. See 56,
                            below.22-23 Banqett / Redy] Hand IV. This is an
                            advance call for III.iv.Image of prompt-book page 71944 Murtherers] Hand II.56] Below this line, Hand III inserts 'here
                                ye Curtaine falls.'. R. C. Bald (PMLA,
                            LVI [1941], 375-76) suggests that this direction indicates that the
                            scene of Banquo's murder was actually played before the front curtain,
                            while the banquet for scene iv was being 'set'; see above, 222-23 and
                            III.iii (opening), below. Such an arrangement would seem to ignore Hand
                            I's setting for III.iii as a 'Groue' (which remains undeleted).
                            Lee-Salmon PB also adds 'Drop Curtain) Stage Dark.'.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1525</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_3.3</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">III.iii.(opening) Enter Banquo and boy] Hand III.
                            Fleance is described as 'Boy to Banquo' in the 1673 quarto list
                            of 'The Persons Names' (followed by D'Avenant).(opening) Banqett Set / on] Hand IV.(opening) Groue] Hand I. See above,
                            III.ii.56. Bell gives 'a Park; the Castle at a Distance' (after
                            Rowe); Lee, 'an avenue to the palace'.(opening s.d.) Enter two
                                    Murtherers.] Hand III deletes F 'three'
                            and writes 'two' above. This scene has been radically cut about by Hand
                            III, largely to bring it into line with D'Avenant's version. Originally
                            the scene was planned as written; Hand II's calls for 'Murtherers' at
                            III.ii.44 and 'Banquo / ffleans' at the beginning of scene iii indicate
                            this (though the number of the 'Murtherers' is ambiguous). As Hand III
                            sets the scene up, Banquo and Fleance cross the stage first and are
                            immediately followed by the 'two' Murderers, whose dialogue has been
                            considerably cut to resemble D'Avenant's. The Murderers follow Banquo
                            and Fleance off-stage and the scene ends. R. C. Bald (PMLA, LVI
                            [1941], 377) is surely mistaken when he says "it is interesting to note
                            that, while Davenant makes the actual murder occur off-stage, in the
                            Dublin version Banquo and Fleance do not even come on beforehand." In
                            D'Avenant the three Murderers enter first, speak nine lines, and exit;
                            then Banquo and Fleance enter, speak five lines, and exit; the Murderers
                            re-enter, speak four lines, and go out after Banquo and Fleance;
                            finally, Fleance, pursued by the Murderers, re-enters on the run and
                            throws a single line at the audience. Bell follows F1 (though with some
                            cutting) down to 18 (' . . . Slave!') and cuts the remainder of the
                            Murderers' lines; Banquo dies on stage. Lee follows a heavily cut
                            version of F1 down to the entrance of Banquo and Fleance and turns to
                            D'Avenant for their speeches; after their exit, the Murderers (First and
                            Second) are given an original line each and then pursue Banquo and
                            Fleance off-stage; finally, Fleance re-enters to deliver D'Avenant's
                            single line.1 Banquo / ffleans] Hand II. See above,
                            opening s.d.1-4 j: It is about ye
                                howre.] Hand III substitutes this single line for F '1. But
                            who . . . us.', which lines are partly circled (in two stages) and x'd
                            through. Compare D'Avenant: '1. Mur. The time is almost come,'.
                            Douai MS cuts F 'But' (1) and 2-4 (' . . . just.') and assigns 4 ('1.
                            Then stand with us.') to `2:'.5 2 The West] Hand III, having deleted the
                            first half-line of the First Murderer's speech, assigns the rest to '2'.
                            D'Avenant gives 5-7 (' . . . Inn.') to First Murderer (6 slightly
                            rephrased) and cuts 7-8 ('and . . . Watch.'); Douai MS assigns 5-8 (' .
                            . . Watch.') to '1:'.8 1. Heark,] Hand III writes `1 over F `3 .
                            D'Avenant assigns to Second Murderer; so too, Lee.9 Banquo within. Give . . . hoa.] Crossed and
                            x'd through (Hand III). D'Avenant omits.11-22 1. Almost a mile: about the horse way is /
                                therefore men / from hence to th'Palace Gate / Make this their
                                usuall walke / 2: come Lets away then and Banquo if thy soule / can
                                in her flight reach / heaven / thy happinesse / begins to / night. /
                                exeunt] Hand III crosses through 11 ('1. His Horses go
                            about.'), alters F '3.' to '1.', interlines 'about', with a caret, after
                            F 'mile: ' (the blot over the 'e' may have been intended to delete the F
                            colon), crosses through 12-13 ('but . . . do,'), and substitutes 'the
                            horse way is'; at this point he apparently planned to keep the rest of
                            the speech as it was, only inserting 'usually' after F 'Gate', but he
                            changes his mind, deletes 'usually' and F 'it' (14), interlining 'this'
                            above, deletes F 'walk.', and inserts 'usuall walke' following. He then
                            adds the speech for the Second Murderer, above and below the F s.d.
                                'Enter Banquo . . . Torch.', which curiously enough remains
                            undeleted. As a result of the crowding of Hand III's first changes, his
                            intention is not clear, and it is possible that he meant the first line
                            to read '1. the horse way is / almost a mile: about'. Lines 14-22 are
                            circled and x'd through, though perhaps Hand III's 'come Lets away' was
                            suggested by F 'Well, let's away' (22). Compare D'Avenant: '1.
                                Mur. His Horses go about almost a Mile, / And men from hence to
                            th' Pallace make it their usual walk.'; and later, when the
                            Murderers re-enter: '1. Mur. Banquo, thou little think'st what
                            bloody feast / Is now preparing for thee. / 2. Mur. Nor to what
                            shades the darkness of this night, / Shall lead thy wandering
                            spirit.'.14-16 Macbeth / Lady / Rosse] Hand II.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1622</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_3.4</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">III.iv.(opening) Cham&lt;ber&gt; [crossed through]
                                / Cour&lt;t&gt;] Hand I. Bell gives setting as 'a room of
                                state in the castle' (Pope, after Rowe); Lee, 'a chamber of
                                state'.(opening s.d.)] F 'Lenox,' crossed
                            through (Hand II). Lee-Salmon PB notes 'Door Open OP'.1 Murth&lt;erer&gt;] Hand II.15-17 Banq&lt;uo&gt; / Gost] Hand II.Image of prompt-book page 72060 distract] Hand III interlines 'distract'
                            above deleted F 'appal'. So D'Avenant.69 Behold, look, how] Hand III deletes F
                            'loe,' after 'look,'. D'Avenant cuts 'Behold, look, loe,'; Douai MS
                            reads 'looke, loe behold' and omits 'how say you:'.75 antient] Hand III deletes F 'olden' and
                            writes 'antient' above. D'Avenant rewrites the line; Douai MS changes
                            the phrase to 'in former times'; Lee alters to 'oldest'.76 &lt;Ba&gt;nquo / &lt;Go&gt;st] Hand II.103 be again, reviue] Hand III deletes F
                            'alive' after 'be' and inserts 'reviue' after 'again,'. Hand II's
                            version while possible is  awkward;
                            perhaps he intended to delete F 'be'. Compare D'Avenant's 'revive a
                            while'.105 and if I meet the not proclaime then]
                            Hand III crosses through F 105 ('If . . . me') and interlines above 'and
                            . . . then'. In making the alteration Hand III omits 'me' after
                            'proclaime'. Compare D'Avenant's 'If any Sinew shrink, proclaim me
                            then'. Bell, Lee accept Pope's 'inhibit' for F 'inhabit'.106 horrid] Hand III alters F 'horrible' to
                            'horrid' by deleting 'le' and changing 'b' to 'd'. So Lee.108 now I am] Hand III inserts 'now' before F
                            'I am'. F3 necessitated some change by misprinting F1 'being gone' as
                            'be gone' in 107. D'Avenant cuts 107 and reads 'So, now I am'. 116 sights] Hand III corrects F3's 'signes'
                            (inherited from F2) to the F1 'sights' by altering 'ne' to 'ht'.120-121 Witches / Heccate] Hand II.142-144 My strange . . . indeed.] Circled
                            (Hand II). Douai MS cuts; D'Avenant rewrites 142-144 (followed
                            substantially by Lee).</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1704</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_3.5</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">III.v.(opening) Rock] Hand I. Bell changes scene to
                                'the Heath'; Lee, to 'the open heath. [Stage
                                dark.]' (both after Rowe). Lee-Salmon PB prefaces the scene
                            with 'Curtain down', indicating that the scene was to be played on the
                            forestage before some kind of inner curtain.(opening) Musiqe / boys redy] Hand IV.
                            Presumably 'boys' are here warned to be ready to 'Sing
                            within.', the song called for at 33 below.2 as you are] Crossed through (Hand III). So
                            D'Avenant.Image of prompt-book page 7217-9 Reddy / Curtin] Hand IV.15 Act] Hand II.33-34 And you . . . Enemy.] Circled (Hand
                            ?III). D'Avenant, Lee cut these and the two preceding lines.36 end the ackt [Hand II] / ffall Curtten
                                    [Hand IV]] Compare 'end' inserted here in Padua
                            PB. Bell, followed essentially by Lee, tacks on parts of D'Avenant's
                            conclusion (omitting 33-39 and 50-56) and adds several new lines, giving
                            the majority of the lines to Hecate. Lee-Salmon PB enters 'singin
                            Witches PS' at 28 (D'Avenant's version) and, adapting the Lee s.d.
                                ('A cloud descends, and Hecate (after the ceremony of
                                being anointed) gets into it.'), adds 'Ring Chariot
                            down.' (opposite 31), 'ring up Chariot' (opposite 40), and concludes the
                            scene with 'Drop Curtain.'.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1765</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_3.6</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">III.vi.III.vi.]Hand II circles and Hand III crisscrosses through
                                whole scene, Hand ?IV writing 'Cut' to left of opening F s.d
                            . Padua PB,  Bell, Lee also omit
                            this scene; D'Avenant inserts the scene (as between Lennox and Seyton),
                            with some cuts and rewriting, between F scenes iv and v (preceding it
                            with an original scene between Macduff and Lady Macduff); Douai MS cuts
                            only 25 and reduces 21-22 to 'no more of this.'. Gentleman (Bell) notes
                            that "the scene between Lenox and another useless lord is
                            properly omitted, as unequal to the warmth and spirit of the rest.".</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e1783</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_4.1</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">IV.i.(opening) Actus Quartus] Hand III
                            deletes F 'Quintus' and interlines 'Quartus' above with a caret.(opening) Caue / Rock [crossed
                                through]] Hand IV deletes Hand I's 'Rock' and
                            substitutes 'Caue' above. The change was doubtless suggested by the
                            final line in D'Avenant's preceding witch scene: 'Let's to the Cave and
                            our dire Charms prepare.'. Bell gives the setting as 'a dark
                                Cave:'; Lee, 'a cave. [Stage dark.]'. Bald
                                (PMLA, LVI [1941], 376) reads Hand IV's 'Caue' as
                            'Cau[dron], but PB is quite clear at this point.7 Heccate] Hand II. It may be noted that this
                            advance call for Hecate at 38 does not include F's 'other three
                                Witches'. As a rule, however, the prompter does not bother to
                            call for non-speaking characters, and the s.d. in F remains uncut. Padua
                            PB has no call for Hecate or 'the other three Witches', but it
                            does not cancel the F s.d. at 38, nor does it reassign Hecate's speech
                            at 39. D'Avenant, who went in for all the witches he could get, retains
                            the three extra witches, as do Douai MS and Bell. Lee goes even further,
                            reading the s.d. at 38 as 'Enter Hecate and all the singing
                                Witches.' and assigning the parts of the song in D'Avenant's
                            version specifically to the 'singing Witches'. D'Avenant (also in the
                            Yale MS) assigns the last part only of 61 to a fourth witch, but the
                            context makes it clear that he really means Hecate; Douai MS, Bell, Lee
                            do not follow him.22 Mack] Hand IV (very faint and smudged).
                            Hand IV here anticipates his call for Macbeth at 29, presumably because
                            it does not occur until the top of the following page in F.Image of prompt-book page 72229 &lt;Ma&gt;cbeth] Hand IV.55-56 &lt;App&gt;arition] Hand II. Apparently
                            undeleted, but see below, 62-68.62-68 1. Say, if . . . show.] Circled and x'd
                            (Hand III). This is the first of a series of cuts designed to bring the
                            scene into general agreement with D'Avenant's version, in which these
                            lines are also cut, Hecate's role is enlarged, and the Apparitions are
                            entirely cut out. The scene was originally planned
                             by Hand II to include the
                            Apparitions (see above 55-56). Bell, Lee retain the Apparitions; the
                            Lee-Salmon PB gives elaborate directions, raising and sinking them on
                            traps. In a note to the first edition of Bell (1773, p.48), a note
                            dropped in the second edition, Gentleman remarks: "In a very bad
                            alteration of this play, by Betterton [i.e., D'Avenant], he has
                            hit upon what we think an emendation; that is, making the witches
                            deliver all the prophecies; by which the surfeiting quantity of
                            trapwork, ghosts, phantomes, &amp;c. is judiciously lessened."68 s.d. 1. Apparition . . . Head.]
                            Crossed and x'd through (Hand III).69 Tell me you unknown powers what dangers / doe
                                attend my destiny]  Hand III alters F 'thou' to 'you' (by
                            writing 'y' over 'th'), F 'power' to 'powers' (by adding 's'), and adds
                            'what . . . destiny'. Compare D'Avenant, 'What Destinie's appointed for
                            my Fate?'.69-70 1. He knowes . . . nought.] Partly
                            circled and x'd (Hand III). D'Avenant also cuts.71-72 Beware Macduff, avoyding him Makbeth
                                is safe Enough.] Hand III adds 'avoyding . . . safe' after F
                                'Macduff,' and crosses through and x's F 'Beware the
                                Thane of Fife: dismiss me.'. Compare D'Avenant:
                                'Hec. Thou double Thane and King; beware
                                Macduff: / Avoiding him, Macbeth is safe enough.'.
                            Note that the speech in PB is still assigned, as in F, to '1.
                                Appar.'. This is obviously an oversight on Hand III's part,
                            who assigns the remaining speeches of the Apparitions to Hecate, as in
                            D'Avenant.72 s.d. He descends.] Partly crossed
                            through (Hand III).74 But one word more.] Crossed through (Hand
                            III). D'Avenant cuts the whole of 74.75-78 1. He will . . . thee.] Circled and x'd
                            (Hand III). D'Avenant also cuts.79 hec:] Hand III, as in D'Avenant,
                            substitutes 'hec:' (i.e., Hecate) for the F speech-prefix '2.
                                Appar.' (crossed through).79 Horrid musick / ready] Hand III places
                            this prompt call in upper right corner of p. 722 (sig. 3P4v), in preparation for the 'shew of eight Kings'
                            following Macbeth's 'what noise is this?' at 106. Compare the call in
                            the Smock Alley MS prompt-book of Wilson's Belphegor (Folger MS
                            827.1, p. 77): 'Ready for horrid Music / Mrs Osborne
                            ready'.81 s.d. Descends.] Crossed through (Hand
                            III).82 fear thee?] Hand III deletes 'of' in F
                            'fear of thee'. Compare D'Avenant, 'fear thy power:'.86 s.d.-89 3. Apparition . . . to't.]
                            Partly crossed through, circled, and x'd (Hand III). D'Avenant also
                            cuts; Bell, Lee (following Pope) cut only 'to't' in 89, which Lee
                            assigns to Hecate.90 heck.] Hand III, as in D'Avenant,
                            substitutes 'heck.' (i.e., Hecate) for the F speech prefix '3.
                                Appar.' (crossed through).90 hearted] Hand III substitutes 'hearted'
                            for F 'metled' (crossed through); point of insertion marked with a
                            caret. D'Avenant reads the line as: 'Be Confident, be Proud, and take no
                            care'.92-94 or slaine / till Birnam woud / shall come to
                                dunsinane] Hand III substitutes these words for F 'until /
                            Great Byrnam wood, to high Dunsinane Hill, / Shall
                            come against him.' (crossed through). Compare D'Avenant,
                                'Macbeth shall like a lucky Monarch Raign, / Till
                                Birnam Wood shall come to Dunsinane.' (a reading
                            adopted by Lee, substituting 'forest' for 'Wood shall'). Douai
                            MS, anticipating Pope, reads 'to Dunsiman high hill' for F 'to high
                                Dunsinane Hill'; Bell, following Pope, reads 'to
                                Dunsinane's high hill'.99-100 Banquo / 8 kings] Hand II.107-109 Seruant / heere]. Hand IV. This is a
                            call for the Servant who replaces F's 'Lenox' at 135. D'Avenant
                            and Lee replace Lennox with Seyton.110 hec] Hand III substitutes 'hec' (i.e.,
                            Hecate) for F speech-prefix 'All.' (crossed through) .
                            D'Avenant gives the line to the Third Witch and the next line (111) to
                            Hecate, reading: 'Wound through his Eyes, his harden'd Heart, /
                                Hec. Like Shaddows come, and straigth depart.' (so Yale
                            MS); Lee reads the lines as in D'Avenant (restoring 'so' for 'straigth')
                            but assigns them to Hecate.125 heck] Hand III writes 'heck' (i.e.,
                            Hecate) over F speech-prefix '1.'. So D'Avenant, Lee.125 Lenox [crossed through by Hand
                                ?III]] Hand II. See 107-109, above.Image of prompt-book page 723135 s.d. Enter &lt;Ser&gt;vant [Hand
                                    ?III] / here [Hand IV]] Page 722 (sig.
                                3P4v) is damaged at this point. The hand in
                            '&lt;Ser&gt;vant' is impossible to determine, though one would expect it
                            to be either Hand III or Hand IV, probably Hand III, though the 'r' form
                            employed is closer to Hand IV's. The ink, however, is much darker than
                            that in 'here', which, nevertheless, does not seem to be quite the same
                            as in Hand IV's call at 107-109. F 'Lenox' has been crossed
                            through.135 Ser:] Hand ?IV deletes F speech-prefix
                                'Lenox.' and substitutes 'Ser:'. Lennox's later speeches in
                            this scene are not reassigned.136 Macduffs Wife her son, and Rosse.] Hand
                            II places this call  at the extreme
                            left top of p. 723 (sig. 3P5); it has been badly shaved in binding. The
                            phrase 'her son' seems to have been crossed through (Hand ?II); see
                            opening s.d. of IV.ii.147 Mesing / er] Hand IV. This early call for
                            the Messenger who enters at IV.ii.64 has been added by Hand IV because
                            of the later cutting of IV.ii.30-64, 79 ('Where . . . ')-85. The
                            Messenger is played by Seyton in D'Avenant; by Angus in Bell.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e2070</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_4.2</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">IV.ii.(opening) Garden] Hand I. Following Rowe,
                            Bell gives the setting as 'Macduff's Castle in Fife'.(opening) Malcome / Macduf] Hand IV. This
                            early call for the entry of Malcolm and Macduff at the beginning of
                            IV.iii again results from the heavy cutting in IV.ii.(opening s.d.) Enter Macduff's Wife, and
                                    Rosse.] Hand III crosses through F 'her
                            Son,'. The omission of Lady Macduff's son follows D'Avenant.
                            Originally the scene was planned by Hand II to include the little boy,
                            as well as the dialogue between mother and son (30-64) and the later
                            dialogue of the Murderers (79 ('Where . . .' )-85), passages also
                            omitted by D'Avenant. D'Avenant substitutes Lennox for Ross; Douai MS
                            makes an unusual number of short cuts in this scene; Bell cuts
                            essentially as in PB but retains the entry of the son; Lee omits the
                            whole scene. Gentleman (Bell) comments on this scene: "Here
                                Shakespeare, as if the vigorous exertion of his faculties,
                            in the preceding scene, required relaxation, has given us a most
                            trifling superfluous dialogue, between Lady Macduff,
                                Rosse, and her son, merely that another murder may be
                            committed, on the stage too. We heartily concur in, and approve of,
                            striking out the greatest part of it." In the second edition (1774), he
                            drops this note but adds: "The character of Lady Macduff, and
                            consequently this scene, is entirely omitted, at some theatres, as
                            unnecessary to representation, the fatal catastrophe of the family being
                            finely introduced in another part of this act."25-26 My pretty . . . you.] Crossed through by
                            Hand III, probably over an earlier light crossing through by Hand II.
                            This cut is obviously the result of omitting Lady Macduff's son, but the
                            omission of these lines makes nonsense of Lady Macduff's reply, which is
                            untouched. D'Avenant substitutes 'Heaven protect you.'; Douai MS retains
                            the present lines but cuts 23-25 (' . . . before.') and 27-30 (' . . .
                            once.').30-64 Wife. Sirra, your . . .
                                talk'st?] Partly circled (Hand III) and crisscrossed (Hand
                            ?II). Cut in D'Avenant, Bell (Lee omits the scene); Douai MS, among
                            other slight changes and cuts, omits 34-36, 41-43, 51-53. Collier MS
                            cuts 32-58.42-43 Messenger] Hand II. See IV.i.147.69-70 Murth&lt;erers&gt;] Hand II. A heavy ink
                            blot makes Hand II's call almost illegible; since the entrance and
                            dialogue of the Murderers is cut, the call would ordinarily have been
                            cancelled. Someone has drawn what looks like a phallic symbol above Hand
                            II's call.75 wicked] Hand III interlines, with a caret,
                            'wicked' above F 'earthly'. D'Avenant substitutes 'a vicious' for F
                            'this earthly'; Douai MS omits 74-79 ('But . . . harm?').79 exit] Hand III. See entry on 79-85.79 Malcolme [crossed through] / Macduffe
                                    [crossed through, both by Hand III]] Hand II.
                            This call replaced by Hand IV at opening of scene ii.79-85 What are . . . you. Exit, crying
                                    Murther.] Partly circled (Hand III) and crisscrossed
                            (Hand II). Cut in D'Avenant, Bell (Lee omits the scene).</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e2153</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_4.3</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">IV.iii.Image of prompt-book page 724(opening) Towne] Hand I. D'Avenant, to avoid
                            a shift of scene to England, gives the setting as 'Birnam Wood'; Lee
                            follows, adding '[Stage light.]'; Bell, following Rowe, gives
                                'the King of England's Palace'. This scene is cut
                            by about 77 lines in Padua PB; D'Avenant reduces Shakespeare's 240 lines
                            to 167 (divided into two scenes, IV.iii and IV.v); Douai MS omits about
                            10 lines; Bell, according to Gentleman's note, omits about 80 lines,
                            "which retained, would render it painfully tedious"; Lee keeps as a
                            single scene but reduces the lines to roughly 148. In view of all this,
                            it is surprising to find PB cutting only about 43 lines.8 greue] Hand IV substitutes 'greue' for F
                            'wail' (crossed through). Part of larger, and differently handled, cuts
                            in Padua PB, D'Avenant, Bell, Lee.33-34 wear thou . . . afear'd.] Crossed
                            through (Hand ?III). Cut in general revision by D'Avenant, Lee.62 matrons] The blot on this word seems to be
                            offset from the facing page.82 more, I] Hand ?III crosses through F 'that'
                            in the phrase 'more, that I'. Part of larger cuts in Padua PB,
                            D'Avenant, Bell, Lee.94 Doctor [crossed through]] Hand II
                            (crossed through by Hand IV). Hand II thus includes the Doctor episode,
                            also retained in Padua PB.Image of prompt-book page 725113 Rosse] Hand IV. This call, which replaces
                            Hand II's call at 146, would suggest that Hand IV is responsible for the
                            deletions through 137.115 Cut] Hand ?IV. It is not clear whether
                            'Cut' is intended to  refer to the
                            two following cuts or to the cut at 171-173 ('and . . sicken.').117-123 Devilish Macbeth . . .
                                detraction.] Circled and criss-crossed by Hand IV. Padua PB,
                            D'Avenant retain substantially but omit 120-121 ('but . . . me ;'); Lee
                            retains general sense but rewrites.123 Here I abjure] Hand IV interlines 'I' (or
                            possibly 'i'), with a caret, after F 'Here'. D'Avenant reads 'I abjure';
                            Bell cuts 123-131 ('Here . . . self,'); Lee cuts the first part of 123
                            ('Unspeak . . . detraction.') and links 'Here abjure' with the end of
                            122.125-137 I am . . . Quarrel.] Circled in three
                            stages and criss-crossed by Hand IV. D'Avenant cuts 125-131 ('I . . .
                            self,'), rewrites 133-135, and cuts 136-137 ('... Quarrel.'); for Bell,
                            see 123, above; Lee, after turning 123-125 ('Here . . . Nature,') into
                            'And here abjure my former accusation:', cuts 125-131 ('I . . . self,'),
                            adopts D'Avenant's version of 133-135, preceding it with 'Come, cheer
                            thy drooping / Spirits--', and cuts 136-137 ('... Quarrel.').133 thy approach, here] Hand III crosses
                            through 'here' in F 'thy here approach,' and inserts 'here' after
                            'approach,'. Cut in the rewriting by D'Avenant, Lee; Douai MS changes to
                            'thy coming hither'. It will be noted that Hand III's change here
                            suggests that he originally included these lines, and probably those of
                            the preceding cut, and supports the view that the cutting at this point
                            is the work of Hand IV (see above, 113).139 s.d.-159 Enter a Doctor. / Mal. Well .
                                . . Grace.] Circled by Hand III. The ink lines under 'King,'
                            (147) and 157 suggest a tentative first cutting by Hand II. Padua PB
                            retains the Doctor but cuts 149 ('How . . . ')-159; D'Avenant cuts the
                            Doctor but retains eight lines on the King's healing power (completely
                            rewritten); Bell, Lee, Collier MS cut as in PB. Gentleman's comment
                            (Bell) is pungent and to the point: "The author has here lugged in, by
                            neck and heels, a doctor, for the strange purpose of paying a gross
                            compliment to that royal line, which ridiculously arrogated a power of
                            curing the evil, by a touch. But that scene is properly left out in the
                            representation." This note, as usual, is considerably softened in the
                            second edition (1774).145 Rosse [crossed through]] Hand
                            II's call is deleted by Hand IV (see above, 113).171-173 and good . . . sicken.] Circled and
                            crisscrossed by Hand ?III. D'Avenant reduces to 'There good Mens lives
                            expire,  Dying e're they
                            sicken.'.191-192 fame geues n&lt;one&gt;[or
                                n&lt;ot&gt;]] Hand IV substitutes these words for F 'none, /
                            That Christendome gives out.' (crossed through) . Another hand draws a
                            line under (perhaps intended to be through) Hand IV's awkward scribble
                            and repeats above 'fame gives n&lt;one&gt; [or n&lt;ot&gt;]'.
                            D'Avenant cuts 191-192 ('... out.'); Bell, Lee retain, but Lee reads 'is
                            none' for F 'none,'.201 tongue,] Hand ?IV crosses through F 'for
                            ever' after 'tongue,'.220 man.] A large ink blot has accidentally
                            obscured this word.Image of prompt-book page 726221 &lt;A&gt;ct] Hand II.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e2279</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_5.1</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">V.i.(opening) &lt;Co&gt;urt.] Hand I. Following
                            Rowe, Bell gives the setting as 'an Anti-Chamber, in Macbeth's
                                Castle'; Lee gives simply 'an antichamber'; Salmon
                            Lee PB adds prompt note 'Table on.' following opening s.d. D'Avenant
                            reduces this scene to thirty-six lines, and Douai MS makes small cuts
                            amounting to about eight lines. Padua PB, as here, leaves the scene
                            untouched; Bell is generally faithful to the original but cuts 65-67;
                            Lee substantially restores Shakespeare's text but makes a number of
                            deletions and does some rewriting, reducing the scene to about sixty
                            lines.4 &lt;La&gt;dy.] Hand II.50 Macbeth] Hand IV. This early call for
                            Macbeth was dictated by the deletion of scene ii. Note that only Macbeth
                            is called (see below, V.iii).63-64 Macbeth, Cathnes / Angus Rosse [all crossed
                                    through]] Hand II. This call was naturally cancelled
                            when scene ii was omitted. Note that Ross is substituted for Lennox and
                            that Angus is here listed for the first and only time by Hand II.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e2310</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_5.2</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">V.ii.(opening) Towne] Hand I. Hand ?II circles and Hand ?III crisscrosses the
                                whole scene for deletion. D'Avenant adapts part of this scene
                            to one between Donalbain, Fleance, and Lennox; Bell, like PB, omits the
                            scene; Lee, giving the setting as 'the field' (after Rowe),
                            retains the scene substantially, but assigns it to 'Rosse, Lenox,
                            Caithness, Angus, &amp;c.' (altered in Salmon-Lee PB to just Ross and
                            Lennox).(opening) Cut] Hand ?IV.Image of prompt-book page 72715 Macbeth Doctor] Hand II (at the top of p.
                            727, sig. 3Q1) See below.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e2334</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_5.3</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">V.iii.(opening) doctor] Hand IV. This call has been
                            written partly across F 'Scena' and is made because of the
                            dropping of the Doctor in the opening F s.d. Another call for the
                            Doctor, also by Hand ?IV, appears directly opposite Hand IV's call,
                            after  F 'Tertia.', but has
                            been heavily smudged out with ink. See below.(opening) Servant] Hand II.(opening) Enter Macbeth, and
                                Attendants.] Hand ?IV lightly crosses out F
                                'Doctor,'. Hand II seems to have planned the scene as in F
                            (see above, V.ii.25). When, however, scene ii was cut, by Hand ?III, it
                            became necessary to change the Doctor's entrance to avoid an exit at the
                            end of V.i and immediate re-entry at the beginning at V.iii. The initial
                            move to get rid of scene ii has been attributed to Hand III because the
                            Doctor's entrance at 33-34 is partly in Hand III ('Enter [Hand
                                IV] Doc&lt;tor&gt; [Hand III]') and would seem to
                            suggest that Hand III, therefore, had something to do with the cutting
                            of scene ii. Such an explanation supposes that Hand III allowed Hand
                            II's call for Macbeth and the Doctor at V.ii.15 to serve, neglecting to
                            cancel the call for the Doctor at that point. Why the call for the
                            Doctor, tentatively assigned to Hand ?IV, at the beginning of scene iii
                            was deleted (if it was not accidentally smudged) is not clear. D'Avenant
                            omits the Doctor; Bell, Lee enter him at 37, essentially as in PB (the
                            first edition of Bell, 1773, accidentally retained him in the opening
                            s.d.).13 Seyton [Hand II] Smyth [Hand
                                III]] On the actor Smith, see the Introduction, p.2.33-34 s.d. Enter [Hand IV] Doc&lt;tor&gt;
                                    [Hand III]] See the discussion above.36 Give me mine Armour:] Crossed through (Hand
                            IV). The line carried on across the right margin from the deletion may
                            be intended to mark the point of the Doctor's actual entrance. This is
                            the first of three cuts relating to Macbeth's armor (see below, 48 and
                            v.51-52), and it would seem that the intention was to dress Macbeth in
                            some costume more nearly contemporary; if so, then 33-34, above, were
                            overlooked. Note that the reference to Macbeth's shield at V.viii.32-34
                            is part of a cut by Hand III. That this was the intention, however, is
                            suggested by the deletion of all references to armor in D'Avenant,
                            followed by Lee (except for the reference to 'Hamess' in V.v.51-52);
                            Bell retains the references to armor, indicating, perhaps, a retum to
                            more historical costuming (see, however, p. 8, note 17).39 Cure her of that] Hand III crosses through
                            F 'from' and interlines 'of' above. Hand III thus restores the reading
                            of F1 and F2.39-46 Malcol&lt;me&gt; / Seywar&lt;d&gt; /
                                Macdu&lt;ff&gt; / Seyw: S&lt;on&gt; / Mente&lt;th&gt; /
                                Cathn&lt;es&gt; [the last two crossed
                                     out by Hand
                                IV]] Hand II. See below, scene iv.42 Raise out . . . Brain,] Circled (Hand IV) .
                            Presumably before the line was circled, Hand III made some change in F
                            'Raise' ('Raze' F1, F2), possibly changing it to 'Raisd' (a reading
                            which does not make much sense). Part of the general cut of the Doctor
                            episode in D'Avenant; Bell, Lee keep the line, reading 'Raze' and 'rase'
                            respectively.48 Come, put . . . Staffe:] Circled (Hand IV).
                            Cut in D'Avenant, Lee.61-62 Doct. Were I . . . here.]
                            Circled and crisscrossed (Hand III). Cut in D'Avenant, Bell, Lee; Douai
                            MS reads 'find' for F 'draw' in 62.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e2424</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_5.4</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">V.iv.(opening) Grou&lt;e&gt;] Hand I. Bell gives
                            the setting as 'Birnam wood' (after Rowe's 'A Wood');
                            Lee, as 'the field'.(opening) Macduff, and Roose and
                                    Souldiers Marching.] Hand III crosses through F
                                'Seywards Son, Menteth, Cathnes, Angus,' and Hand IV
                            inserts 'and Roose' before F 'and Souldiers'. Hand II had
                            earlier crossed through 'Angus,'. Note that 'Seyw: S&lt;on&gt;' was not
                            deleted in Hand II's call (V.iii.39-46); he has no lines in the scene.
                            D'Avenant includes 'Malcolm, Donalbain, Seymour [his equivalent of
                                Seyward], Macduff, Lenox, Fleance,'; Douai MS adds Ross; Bell,
                            'Malcolm, Siward, Macduff, Siward's Son, Lenox, Angus,'; Lee,
                            'Malcolm, Seyward, Macduff, young Seyward, Rosse, Lenox,
                            Caithness, Angus, &amp;c.' (Lee-Salmon PB deletes Caithness and
                            Angus).1-2 Macb&lt;eth&gt; / Seyton] Hand II.2, 3, 7 R] Hand III assigns Menteith's two
                            speeches and the 'Sold.' speech to Ross, crossing through
                                'Ment.' at 2 and 'Sold.' at 7 but leaving
                                'Ment.' untouched at 3. Bell, Lee cut the 'Sold.'
                            speech; D'Avenant rewrites the opening lines, cuts Menteith's first
                            speech, and gives his second and the 'Sold.' speech to Malcolm;
                            Bell reassigns Menteith's speeches to Lennox; Lee again rewrites the
                            opening lines, partly from D'Avenant, cuts Menteith's first speech, and
                            gives his second to Lennox.14-16 Macd. Let our . . .
                                Souldiership.] Circled (Hand ?IV). D'Avenant rewrites the
                            scene completely after 9; Douai MS cuts 11-16 (' . . . Souldiership.');
                            Lee cuts and adapts part of D'Avenant's rewriting.Image of prompt-book page 72819-21] What looks like a carelessly marked
                            circling of these lines is an offset from the facing page (729, sig.
                            3Q2).</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e2507</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_5.5</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">V.v.(opening) &lt;Ca&gt;stle] Hand I. Bell,
                            following Rowe's 'The Castle' gives the setting as 'the
                                Castle of Dunsinane'; Lee, as 'the inside
                                 of
                                Dunsinane-castle' (and Lee-Salmon PB indicates that
                            Macbeth, etc. enter 'out of the Castle').(opening s.d.) Enter Macbeth,
                                Seyton,] Hand ?IV circles F 'and Souldiers, with
                                Drum and Dolours.' (see Hand II's call at V.iv.1-2). D'Avenant
                            introduces 'Macbeth, and Souldier'; Bell, 'Macbeth, Seyton,
                                and Officers'; Lee, 'Macbeth, Seyton, and
                            soldiers'.8 &lt;Mes&gt;senger / &lt;Tott&gt;erdell] Hands
                            II and III. On the actor Totterdale, see the Introduction, p.2.11 my hair] Hand ?IV crosses through F 'Fell
                            of' after 'my'. D'Avenant omits the phrase and greatly cuts the speech;
                            Douai MS cuts 11-13 ('and . . . in't.').30-34 &lt;Ma&gt;lcolme / &lt;Sey&gt;ward /
                                &lt;M&gt;acduffe] Hand II.51-52 Ring the . . . back.] Partly circled
                            (Hand ?IV). D'Avenant cuts; Lee-Salmon PB adds prompter's note after
                            'alarum-bell': 'Ring the Bell--'.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e2564</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_5.6</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">V.vi.(opening) Macbeth] Hand II.6 young Seyward] Hand II.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e2575</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_5.7</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">V.vii.(opening) Allarums] Hand IV.4 s.d. Sttet [Hand IV] Enter Rosse
                                    [Hand III, crossed through by Hand IV] Saward [Hand
                                    IV]] First, Hand III crosses through F 'young
                                Seyward' and substitutes 'Rosse' above; then Hand IV places
                            'Sttet' before F 'Enter' and 'Saward' after and slightly above
                            the deleted F 'Seyward.' By 'Saward' Hand IV presumably intends
                            Young Siward. Having converted Siward to Seymour and deleted Young
                            Siward throughout, D'Avenant here substitutes Lennox.5 Malcolme / Seyward] Hand II.5, 6, 8, 10 R] Hand III substitutes 'R' for F
                                'Y. Sey.' (crossed through). Despite Hand IV's restoration
                            of Young Siward, Hand III's attributions to Ross remain unchanged.10 liest abhorred] Some hand, in pencil,
                            crosses through F 'thou' after 'liest', thus restoring the F1 reading
                            (first editorially restored by Pope). D'Avenant rewrites this speech
                            (see next note).11 Oh my deare Country pardon me yt &lt;I&gt; / doe in a cause soe good soe / quikly
                                dye] Hand II inserts this couplet following F 'speak'st.'.
                            Compare Lennox's dying lines in D'Avenant: 'Oh my dear Country, Pardon
                            me that I, / Do in a Cause so great, so quickly Die.'.13 s.d. Enter Macduffe.] There is no
                            advance call for Macduff.Image of prompt-book page 72923 s.d. Macbeth / Macduffe] Hand II. For an
                            explanation of the mistreatment this last page (729, sig. 3Q2) of the PB
                            has received (i.e., the deletion of the running title and catchword,
                             the four vertical lines running the
                            length of the page, the deletion of some of the prompt materials), see
                            the Introduction, pp. 6-7.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e2646</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook2013/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">div2_5.8</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">V.viii.3 upon them. / Enter Macduff. /
                                Macd. Turn Hell-hound, turn.] The page is damaged at
                            this point, affecting these lines, but there is no evidence of any
                            cutting.13-14 Malcolme / Seyward / Rosse] Hand II.
                            This call is crossed through, but probably by the nineteenth-century
                            exhibitor. Earlier cancelled calls are more roughly scratched through or
                            blotted. All the deletions on this final page are made with a single pen
                            stroke.14 let the divill] Hand III interlines
                            'divill' above F 'Angell' (crossed through). D'Avenant reads as in PB;
                            Douai MS reads the line as 'And let thy angel whom still thou hast
                            serv'd'.32-34 the last.... enough] Hand III crosses
                            through these F lines and writes in the lower margin below 'if by a man
                            it be thy ['thy' crossed through and 'my' written
                                above] Chance to dye / Fight. / Macb: farwell vaine world and
                            that which is most vaine / Ambition. / Macd: Soe may all tyrants fall.
                            exit'. Compare D'Avenant: 'If by a Man it be thy Fate to Die. /
                                [They Fight, Macbeth falls. They shout within. / /
                                Macd. This for . . . I'le as a Trophy bear / Away his Sword, to
                            witness my Revenge. [Exit Macduff. / Macb. Farewell
                            vain World, and what's most vain in it, Ambition. / [Dies.'.
                            The added lines in PB have been crossed through, but again presumably by
                            the nineteenth-century exhibitor. The action in PB is not entirely
                            clear. The F s.d. at 34 'Exeunt fighting. Alarums. / Enter fighting,
                                and Macbeth slain.' has been left untouched, but the added
                            lines in PB seem to rule out any exit and make it clear that Macbeth is
                            slain on stage immediately after fighting with Macduff, who then exits,
                            as in D'Avenant. It is surprising that PB retains the business of
                            Macbeth's head, in view of D'Avenant's more decorous substitution of his
                            sword, followed by both Bell and Lee. Since Macbeth's body apparently
                            remains on stage (a difficulty also with the F text), one must suppose
                            that Macduff exits with the head at 34. Bell, Lee give Macbeth an
                            eight-line dying speech (described by Gentleman as "furnished by Mr.
                                Garrick, to give the actor more eclat"; though he admits
                            that "from the desperate state of Macbeth's mind, we think his immediate
                            death most natural."); the speech begins with two lines suggested by
                            D'Avenant's line ''Tis done! the scene
                             of life will quickly close. /
                            Ambition's vain, delusive dreams are fled,'.35-53 Mal. I would . . . comfort.]
                            The lines have been deleted in probably three stages. First, 38-53 (' .
                            . . him.') were partly circled and crisscrossed by Hand III; second
                            36-37 seem to have been circled and the last half of 53 crossed through
                            by Hand IV; third, 35 was included in the cut with 36-37 by Hand IV
                            (perhaps the third stage was actually a part of the second). The
                            original arrangement (Hand III's) gave Malcolm and Siward
                            three-and-a-half lines before Macduff's entry at 53; the final
                            arrangement (Hand IV's) brings Macduff on directly after Malcolm,
                            Siward, Ross, etc. D'Avenant reduces the F lines to seven; Bell, Lee
                            retain F essentially unchanged.42 Macduffe] Hand II. Crossed through,
                            presumably by nineteenth-century exhibitor.64-73 What's more . . . place:] Circled (Hand
                            IV). D'Avenant rewrites these lines completely, as well as 74-75, and is
                            followed by Lee.</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc></add>