<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><add><doc><field name="id">d1e2</field><field name="section_s">header</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 3 (Midsummer
                    Night's Dream) [a machine-readable transcription] </field><field name="fulltext_t">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 3 (Midsummer
                    Night's Dream) [a machine-readable transcription] Shakespeare, William Creation of machine-readable version: Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia Creation of digital images: Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. 25 kilobytes University of Virginia Library. Charlottesville, Va. Bibliographic Society, ShaMndP Publicly-accessible URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/bsuva/promptbook/ 1997 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century The electronic text contains the Introduction and the Collations.
                    Corresponding images of the prompt-book have been taken from volume III, part
                    ii. Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 3 William Shakespeare Editor G. Blakemore Evans Issued in portfolios. The prompt-books are reproduced in collotype
                            facsimile. University Press of Virginia Charlottesville, VA 1964 Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PR 2757 .E9 1960 v. 3
                            pt. 1-2 Copy 3 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century Published for the Bibliographical Society of the University of
                            Virginia The production of this volume was supervised by Fredson Bowers  Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. All quotation marks retained as data. All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line. The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs. Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings. Library of Congress Subject Headings  1960-1964 English drama; prose LCSH 24-bit color; 400 dpi  July 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Corrected various transcription errors. January 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Added TEI header </field><field name="file_s">ShaMndP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e141</field><field name="section_s">front</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 3 (Midsummer
                    Night's Dream) [a machine-readable transcription] </field><field name="fulltext_t">Image of the spine: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, The Comedy of
                            Errors and Midsummer Night's DreamImage of the cover, part 1: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, The Comedy
                            of Errors and Midsummer Night's DreamImage of the titlepage, part 1: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, The
                            Comedy of Errors and Midsummer Night's DreamImage of the cover, part 2: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, The Comedy
                            of Errors and Midsummer Night's DreamImage of the cover, part 1: Shakespearean Prompt-Books, The Comedy
                            of Errors and Midsummer Night's Dream  SHAKESPEAREAN  PROMPT-BOOKS of the SEVENTEENTH CENTURY Vol. III: Part i Introductions to the 'Nursery'The Comedy of ErrorsMidsummer Night's Dream CollationsEdited by G. Blakemore EvansPublished for The Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia University
                    Press of Virginia, Charlottesville 1964 EDITORIAL ADVISORY
                    COMMITTEE The Bibliographical Society Of the University Of Virginia
                    ARTHUR F. STOCKER, Chairman FREDSON BOWERS JOHN COOK
                    WYLLIE The production of this volume was supervised by Fredson Bowers
                 ContentsIntroduction to The Comedy of Errors . . . . . . 1 The Comedy of Errors: Collations . . . . . . . . . 13 Introduction to A Midsummer Night's Dream . . . 27 A Midsummer Night's Dream: Collations . . . . . . . 31 </field><field name="file_s">ShaMndP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e241</field><field name="section_s">introduction</field><field name="title_s">Introduction A Midsummer Night's Dream First Folio </field><field name="fulltext_t">Introduction A Midsummer Night's Dream First Folio  THE 'Nursery' version of A Midsummer Night's Dream is not a prompt-book,
                    but a simple cutting of the play.1 It contains no
                    prompter's notations. It is possible, however, to link this cutting with the
                    'Nursery' promptbook of The Comedy of Errors by the appearance in it of
                    a common hand (Hand I in Comedy of Errors) and by the general method of
                    marking cuts. It is, moreover, fairly certain that at one time the two
                    separately bound volumes were parts of the same copy of the First Folio. 2 As the collations show there are almost no verbal alterations, but the hand in
                    the three that do occur (see for example I.i.79), as I have noted, is the same
                    as Hand I in The Comedy of Errors, and in both versions the cutting
                    seems to be connected with this hand. It may also be observed that there is very
                    little verbal alteration in The Comedy of Errors. Unfortunately
                    everything from the end of act three (and a leaf containing parts of acts one
                    and two) is missing, making it essentially impossible to say much about the
                    cutting as a whole. Judging from what is left, however, the amount of deletion
                    seems heavy: 511 lines in the first three acts, a figure which does not include
                    what I suspect to be heavy cutting at the beginning of Act II
                     and some probable cutting at the end of Act
                    I.i. I should judge, therefore, a figure of 575 lines for the first three acts
                    would be a fair estimate. With this we may compare the 460 lines cut in the
                    first three acts of the Smock Alley prompt-book (in all, Smock Alley cuts around
                    611 lines), in itself an example of rather heavy cutting. The Smock Alley
                    version thus runs to roughly 1,491 lines; allowing for around 575, lines in the
                    first three acts and about 170 for the last two (by analogy with Smock Alley),
                    the 'Nursery' version will work out at about 1,357. 3 The most interesting cut is the attempt to get rid entirely of the character of
                    Titania or at least so much of her role as is concerned with the quarrel with
                    Oberon over the little Indian boy and the consequent Bottom-enchantment episode.
                    It is unfortunate that even in this case the loss of the leaf containing the end
                    of Act I and the beginning of Act II makes the full extent of the cut somewhat
                    conjectural. But it is certain, that lines 60-97 must have been deleted since
                    they are entirely concerned with the Titania-Oberon quarrel, and almost
                    certainly lines 19-31. In fact as the cutting now stands Oberon's first speech
                    comes at line 245" just after the exits of Demetrius and Helena. In the
                    prompt-book, however, there is a cross in the left margin opposite this speech.
                    Since, in order to make the speech, Oberon must have entered at least fifteen to
                    twenty lines (perhaps more) earlier, this cross cannot indicate his point of
                    entry. In the Smock Alley prompt-books a cross is frequently used to mark the
                    place of an insertion. Here, although no insertion
                     was written in, there is an obvious need
                    for some explanation of the "flower" referred to by Oberon in line 247,
                    Shakespeare's earlier handling of the matter having been cut entirely. It may be
                    noticed that this drastic cut also removes the Bottom-Asshead incident and would
                    necessitate the later cutting of Bottom's dream (IV.i.203-23). As a result it is
                    not clear what exactly is supposed to frighten the "hempen homespuns" at
                    III.i.108. Presumably, however, Puck, although both his speeches have been cut,
                    was meant to appear and scare them away; his entry has been preserved at line
                    55. Such, at any rate, is the way ?Settle handles the situation in his operatic
                    version of the play called The Fairy Queen (1692). Puck watches them
                    perform the Pyramus and Thisbe parody (inserted here by ?Settle) and then
                    without a word 'Robin runs in amongst them' and the mechanicals
                        'Exeunt, running several ways!'. Since like the Padua Winter's Tale, the 'Nursery' Midsummer Night's
                        Dream is merely a cutting of the play which apparently never reached
                    production, only two pages have been reproduced in facsimile: sigs. N1v (p 146) and N5v (p 154). The
                    collation, however, records, as usual, all the cuts and notations for the whole
                    play. The cutting of the 'Nursery' Midsummer Night's Dream has been compared
                    throughout with: (1) the Smock Alley prompt-book (almost certainly before 1700);
                    (2) The Fairy Queen (1692), an operatic version frequently attributed
                    to Elkanah Settle; (3) David Garrick's operatic version, The Fairies
                        (1755)4; (4) George Colman's and David Garrick's
                    acting version (1763)5; (5) Francis Gentleman's
                    suggested cutting in Bell's Shakespeare (1774), vol. VIII. 1. For a discussion of the probable 'Nursery' provenience, see the
                    Introduction to the 'Nursery' Comedy of Errors. 2. This relationship can be deduced from the pattern of staining in
                    the upper, outer corner of the leaves in both. 3. The eighteenth-century acting versions have been so drastically
                    shortened that comparative figures are not very helpful. Garrick's The
                        Fairies (1755) reduces the play to about 695 lines (of which 133 are
                    song lyrics) and omits the whole of the fifth act; the Colman-Garrick version
                    (1763) runs to about "364 lines (of which 189 are again song lyrics) and also
                    omits all but 18 lines of Act V. Francis Gentleman (Bell's Shakespeare,
                    1774, vol. VIII) marks only 176 lines for cutting, but the version he presents
                    (despite William Jaggard's entry [Shakespeare Bibliography, 191 l, p.
                    410]) makes no claim to be 'regulated' from the prompt-book of either house. In
                    a note at the end of Act I he adds; ". . . a little of the serious part might
                    perhaps be spared, but so small a portion, we have not marked the different
                    lines." 4. There are actually two editions of Garrick's text, both dated
                    1755. See my note in Notes and Queries, N.S. (1959), X, 410-411. 5. This version seems to owe its final published form to George
                    Colman (see George Winchester Stone, "A Midsummer Night's Dream in the
                    Hands of Garrick and Colman," PMLA (1939), LIV, 467-482). I have not
                    included George Colman's A Fairy Tale (1763) in the versions
                    examined.  &lt;/page&gt;   &lt;page n=31&gt; </field><field name="file_s">ShaMndP</field></doc></add>