<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><add><doc><field name="id">d1e2</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">header</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 1 (Padua
                            Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 1 (Padua Macbeth)
                    [a machine-readable transcription] Shakespeare, William Creation of machine-readable version: Electronic Text Center Creation of digital images: Electronic Text Center Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. 60 kilobytes University of Virginia Library. Charlottesville, Va. Bibliographic Society, ShaMbeP Publicly-accessible URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/bsuva/promptbook/ 1997 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century. The electronic text contains the Introduction and the Collations. The
                    prompt-book is rendered as page images. Images of the manuscript have been included from volume 1, part 2. Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 1 (Padua
                            Macbeth) William Shakespeare Editor G. Blakemore Evans Issued in portfolios. The prompt-books are reproduced in collotype
                            facsimile. University Press of Virginia Charlottesville, VA 1960 Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PR 2757 .E9 1960 v.1
                        Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century Published for the Bibliographical Society of the University of
                            Virginia The production of this volume was supervised by Fredson Bowers and
                            Sears Jayne.  Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. All quotation marks retained as data. All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line. The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs. Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings. Library of Congress Subject Headings  1960 English drama; prose LCSH 24-bit color; 400 dpi  March 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Corrected various transcription errors. March 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Added TEI header and tags. </field><field name="file_s">ShaMbeP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e140</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">front</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 1 (Padua
                            Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">Image of the spine, vol. 1Image of the cover, vol. 1 part 1Image of the title page, vol. 1 part 1Image of the cover, vol. 1 part 2Image of the title page, vol. 1 part 2  SHAKESPEAREAN PROMPT BOOKS of the
                        SEVENTEENTH CENTURY Vol. I: Part i General Introduction Introduction to the Padua
                        Macbeth Collations  Edited by G. Blakemore Evans  The Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia
                    University Press of Virginia, Charlottesville 1960 EDITORIAL ADVISORY
                    COMMITTEE The Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia
                    Arthur F. Stocker, Chairman Fredson Bowers John Cook Wyllie The
                    production of this volume was supervised by Fredson Bowers and Sears Jayne
                </field><field name="file_s">ShaMbeP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e206</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">introduction</field><field name="title_s">Introduction Macbeth: Padua First Folio</field><field name="fulltext_t">Introduction Macbeth: Padua First Folio In the section of the General Introduction devoted to the Padua prompt-books, I
                    have attempted to link this prompt-book of Macbeth, as
                    well as the other two Padua prompt-books, with Sir Edward Dering's group of
                    amateur actors at Surrenden in Kent. At the same time I tried to show on grounds
                    other than the coincidence of actors' names and initials that this version of
                        Macbeth (and the other Padua prompt-books likewise)
                    should probably be dated somewhere between 1625 and 1635.[1] The evidence for this dating was not conclusive; on the other
                    hand there was no conflicting evidence to challenge an early date. If we accept
                    such a date, the Padua Macbeth and the other Padua
                    prompt-books represent the only pre-Restoration Shakespearean prompt-books now
                        extant.[2] Also examined in the General Introduction was the vexing and finally insoluble
                    question of the extent to which Dering's changes, cuts, etc., allowing that they
                    may be associated with him or another member of his group, represent personal
                    and unprofessional reactions to the text, or whether the treatment of the text
                    arises from a knowledge (however gained) of what was being done on the
                    professional stage in the first three decades of the century.  The version of Macbeth which here emerges from the
                     reviser-prompter's grasp (only one hand can
                    be distinguished)[3] shows, if we compare it with the
                    Smock Alley prompt-book, comparatively slight alterations.[4] Some lines (actually fewer, since this figure includes a few
                    half-lines) are cut. Of these 292 lines, 217 are accounted for by five
                    substantial cuts:  II.iii.1-23 (the Porter scene). This cut would have pleased Coleridge, but it is
                    clearly made on the assumption not that it is poor stuff (the Porter's
                    conversation with Macduff remains untouched), but because it is an easy passage
                    to delete without any obvious complication. The Smock Alley prompt-book retains
                    only lines 1-5 and 24-27. In D'Avenant's version the Porter (played by a
                    Servant) is cut to one line, a handling of the scene which survived even after
                    Garrick 'restored' Macbeth. The Douai MS (1694) reduces
                    the Porter scene to: 'Enter a Porter dressing himselfe. / Knock all the while. /
                    P: here's a knocking indeed: who's there in the name of / belzebub? anon; anon;
                    I am Coming. (Opens the doore.) / Enter Macduffe and Lenox / Macd: was [sic] so late friend, ere you went to bed / That you doe
                    lye so long / P: faith sir we were carowsing till the second cock. / Macd: is
                    thy master  stirring? / Enter Macbeth. / our
                    knocking hath him here he comes.' Lee gives the Servant three short speeches
                    (one from D'Avenant and two original efforts). The Collier MS cuts 5-23 ('Here's
                    . . . Bonfire') , 27-47 ( And . . . him.).  III.i.71-140 (the first interview with the two Murtherers). The alteration in
                    line 48 ('bid em stay there for me') allows the reviser to omit the whole
                    interview between Macbeth and the Murtherers, lines 72-140 below. Since the
                    reviser seems to have been interested in cutting Macbeth's role, this deletion
                    was an obvious choice, the theatrics of the scene resembling the kind of thing
                    Shakespeare was busy with in Richard III. D'Avenant cuts
                    about 10 lines and rewrites slightly; Smock Alley cuts 7 lines; Douai MS, 13;
                    Garrick, 26; and Lee, 22 (rephrasing a little).  III.vi (the scene of comment on Banquo's murder). This is clearly the sort of
                    scene which a reviser on the watch for material to cut would single out. Though
                    expository in nature, the scene contains nothing essential to the understanding
                    of the remainder of the play. The Smock Alley prompt-book and the Garrick and
                    Lee versions also omit this "flat, uninteresting scene" (Bell, p. 44).  IV.iii.2-31, 66-100, 149-158 (part of the Malcolm-Macduff interview). These lines
                    are cut to shorten a long and "painfully tedious" scene (Bell, p. 52). The scene
                    is even more drastically reduced in D'Avenant's text; the Douai MS cuts only 8
                    lines, Garrick about 80, and Lee, eked out by bits of D'Avenant, about 116.
                    D'Avenant, Smock Alley, Garrick, and Lee cut the whole 'Doctor episode'. Why the
                    reviser here should decide to keep part of the episode I do not understand
                    unless perhaps it furnished a few lines for an actor ('T S') whose other part
                    (or parts) left him without anything to say. Apart from these major deletions
                    the play (originally a short one of 2,084 lines) is very slightly reduced.[5] Some of the cuts, changes, and prompt-notations deserve special comment. In
                    general much of the cutting seems to be aimed at reducing the length of
                    Macbeth's part; for this reason the deletion of the first interview with the
                    Murtherers (III.i. 71-140) was an inevitable cut and is skillfully enough
                    patched over by the reviser. At the opening of I.vii, the prompter calls only
                    for Macbeth and takes no notice of the 'Ho boyes',
                     'Torches', and 'Sewer' for which the Folio calls
                    (at I.vi a call for 'Hoboys' noted by the prompter has been crossed
                    through and he also ignores the Folio call for 'Hoboyes'
                    at IV.i. 106). Although the prompter tends to ignore 'Attendants' in
                    his calls (e.g., I.ii, I.vi, etc.), he is (except for 'Hoboys') more
                    careful about notations for musical soundings, etc. It would seem, therefore,
                    that it was intended to cut the 'show' of the banquet in progress and to
                    introduce Macbeth directly. The same change is made in the D'Avenant,
                    Smock Alley, and Garrick versions. Again, stage business seems to be slightly
                    changed at the beginning of III.iv, where the reviser cuts line 10, a line which
                    can be taken to mean that Macbeth seats himself with his guests before joining
                    the First Murtherer (here altered to '2 Murtherer'). The deletion of line 10
                    implies that Macbeth, after welcoming his guests, turns aside directly to talk
                    with the '2 Murtherer'. D'Avenant and Lee likewise cut. We may also notice that
                    the physical appearance of the Ghost of Banquo in this scene is twice vouched
                    for by marginal prompt calls. Some evidence of a desire by the reviser to cut
                    down on the number of 'extras' may be seen in the substitution at III.i and
                    III.iv of 'Angus' in place of the Folio 'Lords', and of
                    'Angus Rosse, Y Seyward' at V.vi in place of the Folio 'their Army'. In
                    V.viii, however, 'Thanes' is expanded to 'Angus Cathnes Mentith Lenox'.
                    We may also note that in III.i the reviser brings Macbeth's Servant on at line
                    44, a handling of the scene found likewise in the Smock Alley version. Later
                    edited texts consider the Servant as being among the 'Attendants' at
                    the opening of the scene. Some of the cuts are clearly made to get rid of
                    difficult passages or passages considered merely poetic. For the first, note the
                    deletions at I.vii.50-54; II.iii.55; III.ii.15; for the second, see I.vii.5-12;
                    V.iii.20-29. The cut at IV.iii.120-121 deletes a reference to the deity and the
                    deletion of the lines on the 'poore player' (V.v.24-26) may reflect a histrionic
                        touchiness.[6] Little has been added in the way of props or offstage sounds. At III.iii.8 there
                    is a call for 'Treacle' to indicate the approach of Banquo's and Fleance's
                        horses;7 and at IV.i a 'Cauldorne' is called for.
                    'Thunder' is duly called for, as in the Folio, by the prompter at the beginning
                    of III.v, but not at the opening of IV.i, perhaps because this is the beginning
                    of an act. For some reason it was decided to dispense with the Folio call for
                        'Musicke' at III.v.31-33 and IV.i.42-43; only 'Song'
                    is called for in both instances, though a call for 'musique'
                    has been crossed through at III.v.33, and Folio 'Musicke' is
                    again ignored in the call for the Witches' dance at IV.i.132. We may also notice
                    the prompter's addition of 'Senett' at the opening of III.iv.8 Several of the minor roles have been assigned by the prompter to individuals by
                    name or initials. 'Mr Carlile' (or 'Mr
                    Carl') doubled as one of the 'Murtherers' at the end of IV.ii and as a
                    'Messenger' at V.v.27-29. A 'Mr H &lt;.&gt; w &lt;. .&gt;',
                    'H.wit', or 'H&lt;ewi&gt;t' (the name is far from clear)9 played a messenger at IV.ii.64. He is perhaps the same person as
                    the 'E H' who plays a 'Seruant' at I.v.31, III.i.43-44, III.ii (opening), and
                    V.iii.8-9. The Doctor at IV.iii.139 is played by 'T S' and the Doctor in V.iii
                    by 'Mr G'. A 'Mr K' plays the '2
                    Murtherer' in III.iv.7-8. It is on the basis of these names ('T S' appears again
                    as a 'Servant' and a 'Lord' in Winter's Tale) that I have suggested an
                    association with Sir Edward Dering's group of amateurs.10 The following characteristics of the prompt-book are worth pointing out:[11] a. A single hand seems to be responsible for all the markings, whether
                    prompt-calls or revisions affecting the text.  b. The prompt-calls and calls for sound effects are not anticipative (except
                    occasionally by a line or two).  c. There are no calls for characters entering at the beginning of an act.  d. Act breaks are carefully marked; see especially the end of Act III.  e. The calls for characters in a new scene are sometimes given at the end of the
                    preceding scene (e.g., I.iii, II.iii, IV.ii, V.iii) instead of at the beginning
                    of the new scene. This may imply the lack of much real sense of break between
                    scenes. Compare Sir E. K. Chambers' comments in his William Shakespeare
                    (1 930), I, 118.  f. Entrances and sound effects are frequently marked with a short horizontal line
                    following or preceding the line of the play before entry or effect.  g. The prompter ignores regularly the Folio call for 'Attendants' (e.g., I.ii, I.vi) and 'Soldiers'
                    (e.g., V.ii, V.iv).  h. Note the general expansion of the Folio stage directions in the final scenes
                    of Act V.  i. In I.vii, at Lady Macbeth's entrance (l. 25), we can see that the
                    cutting was done before the prompt-call was written in; otherwise the call for
                    Lady Macbeth would have followed line 28 as in Folio. The order here
                    implied is the natural order, but it is sometimes difficult to establish.  1. General Introduction, pp. 7-11.   2. The First Folio text of Macbeth, of course, shows
                        signs of being printed from copy-text having connection with the theatre. A
                        prompt-book of Twelfth Night, of unknown provenience (see General
                        Introduction, p. 4), has been described as pre-Restoration (see
                        Halliwell-Phillipps, Some Account of the Antiquities, Coins, Manuscripts
                            . . . Illustrative of the Life and Works of Shakespeare, Brighton
                        Hill [1852], p. 115). The evidence for a pre-Restoration date
                        (Halliwell-Phillipps dates it about 1640) is quite inconclusive.   3. The hand is not, I believe, that of Sir Edward Dering, though
                        Sir Edward seems to have written two fairly distinct hands and may have used
                        others. The same hand has inserted 'Troylus and Cressida' at the beginning
                        of the 'Tragedies' in 'The Catalogue' on sig. [A]r.
                      4. A detailed comparison has been made with D'Avenant's 1674
                        version (and with the Yale MS of D'Avenant's version), the Smock Alley
                        version (c. 1680), the Douai MS version (1694), and
                        the much later versions of Garrick (1744) and Lee (1753). Agreements in
                        cutting with the Collier-Perkins Second Folio have also been noted. The
                        D'Avenant text used is that in Dramatic Works, ed. Maidment and
                        Logan, V (1874), 297-394; the Yale MS adds nothing to the printed text so
                        far as this study is concerned. The Douai MS (in the Douai Public Library,
                        MS 7.87, fols. 171-209), entitled 'The Tragedye of Macbeth' and dated 'Anno
                        Dñi 1694', is based on the Second Folio text, but gives evidence of
                        influence from the First Folio (or possibly the 1673 quarto). It shows no
                        immediate connection with the theatre, but contains numerous verbal
                        'improvements' and makes a good many cuts. The MS, of which I intend to make
                        a separate study, is here used for the first time. The Garrick cutting was
                        printed in Bell's Shakespeare (1773), I. Its connections with
                        Garrick are established by G. W. Stone, Jr. ("Garrick's Handling of
                            Macbeth," SP [1941], XXXVIII, 609-628).
                        Stone also gives some details of other later eighteenth-century versions.
                        John Lee's adaptation was published in Edinburgh in 1753 as The
                            Historical Tragedy of Macbeth (Hogan, Shakespeare in the
                            Theatre, II [1957], 361, lists only a Dublin edition of 1761 and
                        says that Lee's alteration was first acted at Edinburgh 1 January 1754). It
                        is still strongly tinctured with D'Avenant, but a good deal of the original
                        has been restored. This acting version is not mentioned by G. C. D. Odell
                            (Shakespeare from Betterton to Irving [1920], 2 vols.), Stone
                        (op. cit.), or A. C. Sprague (Shakespeare and the Actors [1948]),
                        though it contains a number of interesting theatre characteristics.
                      5. We may compare the approximately 352 lines deleted in the Smock
                        Alley version and the 310 lines which Garrick cut in the course of his
                        "restoration" of the original in 1744. The Lee version is too confused with
                        D' Avenant to make a comparison useful. The number of lines in Macbeth is based on Alfred Hart's count (RES [1932], VIII, 21). I count roughly 2,124 lines
                        in D'Avenant's version, 1,732 in Smock Alley, 1,846 in Garrick's, and 1,857
                        in Lee's (these figures are somewhat lower than those given by Stone [p.
                        621] for Shakespeare, D'Avenant, and Garrick).   6. D'Avenant does not spare the profession, but Harry Rowe (an
                        actor-manager of sorts) makes the same cut on the plea that he considers the
                        lines "as a play-house interpolation, and what Shakespeare would never have
                        put into the mouth of a just man labouring under violent perturbation"
                        (Macbeth, ed. Harry Rowe, 2nd ed. [York, 1799], p. 105). Lee softens to 'a
                        mere player'.   7. See W. J. Lawrence, Pre-Restoration Stage Studies (1927), p.
                        217. Mr. Lawrence notes this scene (together with IV.i) as the earliest
                        example in English drama calling for this particular sound effect, and draws
                        attention to the lack of any "elucidative stage direction" in the Folio. His
                        inference that such a sound effect was intended here is nicely supported by
                        the Padua prompt-book.   8. I have used this notation as part of my evidence for an early
                        date for the Padua prompt-books. See the General Introduction, p. 7.
                      9. See the General Introduction, p. 9.   10. See the discussion of this matter in the General
                        Introduction, pp. 8-9.   11. The heavy line which runs diagonally across sig. 2m2r (p. 135) in the collotype reproduction of the Padua
                        Macbeth is the result of a break in the film from which the reproduction was
                        made.  &lt;/page&gt;   &lt;page n=31&gt; </field><field name="file_s">ShaMbeP</field></doc></add>