<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><add><doc><field name="id">d1e2</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">header</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock Alley
                    Macbeth) [a machine-readable transcription] Shakespeare, William Creation of machine-readable version: Electronic Text Center Creation of digital images: Electronic Text Center Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. 125 kilobytes University of Virginia Library. Charlottesville, Va. Bibliographic Society, ShaMacP Publicly-accessible URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/bsuva/promptbook/ 1996 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century. The electronic text contains the Introduction and the Collations. The
                    prompt-book is rendered as page images. Images of the manuscript have been included from volume 5, part 2. Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) Editor G. Blakemore Evans Issued in portfolios. The prompt-books are reproduced in collotype
                            facsimile. University Press of Virginia Charlottesville, VA 1970 Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PR 2757 .E9 1960 v.5
                        Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century Published for the Bibliographical Society of the University of
                            Virginia  Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. All quotation marks retained as data. All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line. The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs. Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings. Library of Congress Subject Headings  1960-1970 English drama; prose LCSH 24-bit color; 400 dpi  July 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Corrected various transcription errors. Corrected errors in the print text,
                    page 32: because necessary] became necessary; page 33: Mentieth] Menteith; Fixed
                    missing or broken images. July 1997corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Added TEI header and tags. </field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e137</field><field name="section_s">front</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 5 (Smock
                            Alley Macbeth) </field><field name="fulltext_t"> SHAKESPEAREAN PROMPT BOOKS of the SEVENTEENTH
                    CENTURY Vol. V: Part i Introduction to the Smock Alley Macbeth Collations  Edited by G. Blakemore Evans  A Publication of The Bibliographical Society of the University of
                    Virginia University Press of Virginia, Charlottesville 1970 THE
                    UNIVERSITY PRESS OF VIRGINIA Copyright 1970 by the Rector and Visitors of
                    the University of Virginia First published 1970 Standard Book Number
                    8139 0301 7 Library of Congress Catalog Card Number: 60 2680 Printed
                    in the United States of America  ContentsIntroduction to the Smock Alley Macbeth . . 1Collations . . . . . . . 9</field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e189</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="section_s">introduction</field><field name="title_s">Introduction Smock Alley Macbeth Third Folio</field><field name="fulltext_t">Introduction Smock Alley Macbeth Third Folio THE Smock Alley prompt-book of Macbeth has suffered a somewhat adventurous
                    career. After the play was separated from the original copy of the Third Folio
                    (1664) by Halliwell Phillipps, [1] four pages (pp. 711,
                    sig. 3O4; 714 [misnumbered], sig. 3O6V; 719, sig. 3P3; 722,
                    sig. 3P4V) were exhibited in the "Rustic Wigwam" at
                    Hollingbury Copse, Brighton, and the last page of the play (p. 729, sig. 3Q2)
                    was eventually bound up with the Smock Alley Hamlet, the first page of
                        Hamlet (p. 730, sig. 3Q2V) being the verso of
                    the last page of Macbeth. [2] All but the last page
                    found their way to the Folger Shakespeare Library, where they were reassembled.
                        [3] The last page has only recently come to light
                    with the discovery of the Smock Alley Hamlet prompt book in the
                    Halliwell Phillipps collection of the University of Edinburgh Library. All these
                    leaves unfortunately bear the marks of their exhibition: wavy ink lines running
                    vertically through the text on the side of the leaf not intended for exhibition.
                    The damage to the last page of Macbeth is especially heavy (see below, pp. 6-7)
                    and indicates that the first page of Hamlet was also exhibited at some
                    stage in its history, probably at Hollingbury Copse.
                     Professor R. C. Bald's identification of 'Smyth' (Hand III), who plays Seyton in
                    V.iii, with the Smock Alley actor Henry Smith who died in 1682 sets a definite
                    date after which what may be considered as probably the first acted form of the
                    Smock Alley prompt book cannot have been prepared. [4]
                    The only other actors named are John Totterdale (at V.v.8, Hand III), who also
                    played in Henry VIII and Othello, and 'farlow' (at III.i.22, 101-104, Hand ?III
                    ). Nothing further is certainly known of Farlow, but Totterdale seems to have
                    been acting in Dublin from about 1674 to 1688. [5]
                    Totterdale's name, therefore, would seem to suggest an early limit of about 1674
                    for this form of the prompt book. Further possible narrowing of the two limits
                    (1674 and 1682) will be discussed later.  It is possible, as Professor Bald points out, [6] to
                    distinguish what appear to be three layers in the prompt markings and four
                    principal hands. Hand I (which appears as Hand I in Hamlet,
                        Lear, and Twelfth Night and as Hand II in I Henry
                        IV) does nothing but mark the scene settings. Hand II, probably the
                    earliest of the prompt hands, indicates the characters to be called and seems
                    responsible for much of the cutting and occasional textual changes. It appears
                    again as Hand II in Hamlet and Othello and is perhaps the same
                    hand responsible for the Julius Caesar couplet. [7] Hand III, another prompt hand and the same as Hand I in
                        Othello, marks a second stage in the preparation of the play and is
                    largely associated with bringing the performance, as originally outlined by Hand
                    II, into closer conformity with certain aspects of D'Avenant's version of
                    Macbeth (published 1674), particularly in III.iii, IV.i, and V.viii. Hand IV, a
                    peculiarly coarse and heavily formed hand, occasionally makes changes in Hand
                    III's notations, cuts a few lines, supplies prompt notes on off-stage effects,
                    and tidies up generally. It occurs also in Hamlet (Hand III), Merry Wives (Hand I),
                        Othello (Hand VI), and the Julius Caesar acting list and
                    is the principal prompt hand in the Smock Alley Belphegor manuscript
                    prompt-book. It is also possible to distinguish a fifth hand (Hand V) in
                    connection with a few textual emendations near the beginning of the play which
                    appear to be echoes of Pope's text (1723). [8] What
                    seem to be other hands occur occasionally, but I have been unable to associate
                    them with any of the hands in the other Smock Alley prompt-books. In the
                    collation which follows all changes and additions and most deletions are either
                    assigned to one of the five hands listed above (sometimes with a query) or
                    marked as by an unidentified hand. The attempt to determine the hands
                    responsible for the deletions (by circling, crossing through, and
                    criss-crossing) is based on a study of the various inks usually associated with
                    a particular hand. There is, of course, considerable danger in this method, and
                    I have tried to indicate those cases where the evidence seemed especially
                    ambiguous.  In the collation I have compared the Smock Alley Macbeth with the following stage
                    or stage related versions: (1) the Padua prompt-book (see Volume 1 of this
                    series; referred to as Padua PB); (2) Sir William D'Avenant's adaptation, 1674
                    (edited by Christopher Spencer in Five Restoration Adaptations of
                        Shakespeare, Urbana, 1965; referred to as D'Avenant) and the Yale
                    manuscript of D'Avenant's adaptation (edited by Christopher Spencer,
                        D'Avenant's "Macbeth" from the Yale Manuscript, New Haven, 1961;
                    referred to as Yale MS, but not included in the collation unless differing
                    significantly from the 1674 printed text). (3) The Douai manuscript, 1694 (in
                    the Douai Public Library, MS 7.87, fols. 171-209; referred to as Douai MS).[9] (4) The Garrick version, 1744 (in Bell's
                        Shakespeare, 1773, Vol. I; referred to as Bell).[10] (5) The John Lee version, Edinburgh, 1753 (referred to as Lee);
                    (6) The Lee Edward Salmon prompt-book  (in a
                    copy of the 1753 edition, now in the Harvard Theatre Collection, marked by
                    Edward Salmon, the prompter, and belonging to West Digges, who played the role
                    of Macbeth in Edinburgh on 26 December 1757; referred to as Lee Salmon PB, but
                    only where it differs from Lee). [11] I have also
                    included the cuts indicated in the Collier Perkins Second Folio, 1632 (referred
                    to as Collier MS).  Two distinct versions of Macbeth emerge from the work of Hands II and III. Hand
                    II seems to have blocked the play out, making a few verbal changes (I.iii.120,
                    145-146; I.vi.9; III.i. 16-17, 28), marking certain passages or scenes (III.vi,
                    V.ii) for cutting, a total of roughly 163 lines, and writing in the prompt calls
                    for the characters. He regularly omits the characters of Angus and Lennox,
                    except for one occasion each (V.i.63-64 and IV.ii. 125), when they were
                    inadvertently, I think, included. In the General Introduction to this series
                    (I,i,19) I suggested, following R. C. Bald, [12] that
                    Hand II's version may represent the original form in which Smock Alley played
                    Macbeth. This view I no longer consider seriously tenable. It is much more
                    likely that Hand II's version represents a preliminary draft for prompt use and
                    that this "prepared book" was then taken over by Hand III and further adapted
                    for the stage with additional emphasis on D'Avenant's version. An analogous
                    situation may be found in the Smock Alley Hamlet, where, I have
                    suggested, possibly the same hand (Hand II) performed essentially the same kind
                    of preliminary spadework. [13] Hand III initiates less cutting than Hand II (roughly 127 lines as compared with
                    some 163),[14] although in a number of cases he
                    reinforces Hand II's suggested cuts by further marks of deletion. On the other
                    side, his individual textual revisions are much more numerous, particularly in
                    III.iii, IV.i, and V.viii, scenes in which D'Avenant's influence is particularly
                    marked. Hand II's  few verbal changes suggest
                    some vague knowledge of D'Avenant, and his cuts sometimes parallel those in
                    D'Avenant's version. Hand III's changes, however, quite apart from the three
                    scenes noted above, reflect a closer recollection of D'Avenant's wording,
                    although almost invariably with slight verbal inaccuracies or changes. This
                    strongly suggests that Hand III worked from memory, without having a text of
                    D'Avenant's version to consult.[15] Such a view might
                    be considered one reason why the Third Folio text was employed as a prompt-book.
                    But all the Smock Alley productions of Shakespeare used the Third Folio text as
                    a source for the prompt-book. It is, moreover, conceivable that the company
                    preferred Shakespeare's basic text, using D'Avenant only in those scenes (the
                    murder of Banquo and the handling of the Apparitions) where his revision did not
                    interfere materially with the original. A somewhat similar case occurs in the
                    Smock Alley King Lear, in which Shakespeare's text is used until V.ii,
                    at which point some form of Tate's happy ending appears to have been tacked on.  The suggested absence of a printed text of D'Avenant's version, first published
                    in 1674 but performed as early as 1664, may also be advanced as an argument for
                    placing the Smock Alley production of Macbeth at the earliest possible
                    date--Totterdale's advent in the company in 1674. If, indeed, a printed copy of
                    D'Avenant's text was literally not available, this would explain the apparent
                    reliance of Hands II and III on recollections of the London performances. While
                    an early limit (1674) must be allowed as a possibility, I still incline to the
                    opinion I expressed in the General Introduction to this series (I,i,19): between
                    1674 and 1682, with some preference for a later rather than an earlier date.  Hand IV seems certainly to be the latest of the main prompt hands. Although it is
                    principally concerned with prompt notations, particularly off-stage effects or
                    special business, e.g., I.iii.3-4; II.iv.10-13, 21; III.ii.22-23; III.iii
                    (opening); III.v (opening and end); V.vii (opening), it makes a few cuts (about
                    38 lines, limited to IV.iii, V.iii, V.iv, and V.viii), one change of scene
                    (IV.i), and occasional verbal substitutions ( IV.iii.8,
                     123, 191-192; V.v.11). Hand IV also restores
                    Folio 'Rosse' for Hand III's'Macduffe' in I.ii.45 s.d. and I.iii.88 s.d. (from
                    D'Avenant) and Folio 'Saward' for Hand III's 'Rosse' in V.vii.4 s.d. (D'Avenant,
                    'Lennox'). There is, I believe, some evidence to suggest that Hand IV worked on
                    the prompt-book at two different times. The changes made in Hand III's notations
                    and some other notations are written in a faded black-brown ink, while those
                    calls which seem merely to tidy up Hand III's work are generally in a light
                    brown ink. It seems possible, therefore, that some of Hand IV's changes may
                    reflect a somewhat later version of the play. But the evidence is tenuous,
                    sometimes uncertain, and resists any definite conclusion.  It is difficult to give a very satisfactory account of the total number of lines
                    cut in the Smock Alley Macbeth. But as the play finally emerged under
                    Hand IV about 328 lines seem to have been deleted from the original and about
                    five lines, which do not merely substitute for deletions (see III.iii.11-22;
                    V.vii.11; V.viii.32-34), added. Also probably another twenty lines (the second
                    (?) song from D'Avenant's version called for in II.iv.10-13, 21) must be
                    included as an addition. All this leaves a production of about 1,781 lines,
                    somewhat shorter than the Padua PB, D'Avenant, Douai MS, Garrick, Lee, and
                    Lee-Salmon versions.[l6] The principal cuts are as
                    follows: II.iii.5-23, 28 ('of three . . .')-46 (the Porter scene); III.vi (the
                    scene of comment between Lennox and a Lord); IV.ii.30-64, 79-85 (the last part
                    of the scene of Lady Macduff's murder); IV.ii.117-123 ('Devilish . . .
                    detraction.'), 125-137 ('I am . . . Quarrel.'), 139 s.d.-159 (' . . . Grace. ')
                    (parts of the Malcolm Macduff interview); and V.ii (scene of comment by
                    Macbeth's enemies).  The final scene (V.viii) requires special comment. This scene occurs on the last
                    page of Macbeth (p. 729, sig. 3Q2 ) and has been defaced by the
                    nineteenth-century exhibitor. In addition to double verticle lines down each
                    column, two of Hand II's advance calls, Hand III's added lines at the bottom of
                    the page, the running title, and the catchword have been crossed through, each
                    with a single pen stroke. All these deletions must, I think,
                     be "credited" to the vandal exhibitor. They
                    are made more neatly, if that is a virtue, than the usual run of deletions in
                    this prompt-book. If this explanation is accepted, the general intention in the
                    final scene is clear enough, although the cutting in lines 35-53 is somewhat
                    confusing. Even so, however, the scene as here developed does nothing to clear
                    up the difficulty in the Folio text as to where Macbeth dies, on- or off-stage.
                    Here, as in the Folio, he seems to die on-stage, with a line lifted from
                    D'Avenant's version of the scene in which he does indeed die on-stage. At this
                    point, Macduff, with a line original to the Smock Alley prompt-book 'Soe may all
                    tyrants fall.' exits, re-entering immediately after the entrance of Malcolm,
                    Siward, Ross, etc. (lines 35-53 being cut) with Macbeth's head. Unless he cuts
                    it off before exiting, where does Macduff get the head? At best this suggests an
                    awkward bit of stage business, all the more surprising in the Smock Alley
                    production in view of D'Avenant's handling of the matter, by more decorously
                    substituting Macbeth's sword, which Macduff takes from the dying Macbeth just
                    before his exit and produces triumphantly on his re-entry some lines later. Was
                    the taste of an Irish audience more Elizabethan than Augustan?  In a number of instances the changes made in the Smock Alley prompt-book parallel
                    those found both in the earlier Padua prompt-book and in eighteenth-century
                    productions; all such parallels are recorded in the running notes to the
                    collation. It should be noticed, however, that the attitude here dictating the
                    cutting in the Porter scene differs from that at work in the Padua prompt-book.
                    In Smock Alley "decorum" and D'Avenant are pretty clearly responsible, although
                    I do not believe that there is otherwise much evidence of a desire to "refine"
                    Macbeth except in the matter of language. As usual in Restoration versions
                    (contrast the Padua prompt-book), Shakespeare's diction and syntax have been
                    simplified, sometimes, but not always, with the aid of D'Avenant (e.g.,
                    I.iii.55-57, 120, 145-146; II.iii.131-133; II.iv.40; III.i.16-17, 110;
                    III.iv.60, 75, 103, 105, 106; IV.i.69, 90, 92-94; IV.ii.75; IV.iii.8, 133,
                    191-192; V.iv.11; V.Viii.14, 32-34), or "poetic" passages simply deleted (e.g.,
                    I.iii.125-126, 137-142; I.vi.3-9; I.vii.2-12; II.iii.135-138; III.i.122-126;
                    IV.iii.117-123, 125-137, 171-173). The desire to clarify what seemed involved,
                    difficult, or obsolete accounts for a large number of the changes and cuts, and
                    sometimes the poetic quality of the play 
                    suffers though considerably less so than in D'Avenant's "flattened" adaptation.  Two further points may be mentioned. Hand III's importation of Banquo into II.iv
                    in the place of the Old Man is so far as I know unique to the Smock Alley
                    production. His presence there may perhaps be explained by the implied inclusion
                    of the Witches in Hand IV's call for a song and dance at lines 4-5 and 10-13,
                    since Banquo would be a more suitable spectator for this extra effect than an
                    anonymous Old Man. In V.iii.36, 48, and V.v.51-52, Hand IV deletes the
                    references to Macbeth's armor (missing, however, the first one at V.iii.33-34),
                    and Hand III cuts the reference to his shield at V.viii.32-34. Such deletions
                    point to a costuming of Macbeth more in keeping with Restoration military dress
                    than with Shakespeare's conception, a view borne out by several
                    eighteenth-century theatrical paintings and engravings.[17] The scenes employed in the Smock Alley Macbeth are for the most part stock: Court
                    (I.ii,iv,vi; III.i,iv; V.i), Towne (II.iv,deleted; IV.iii; V.ii), Groue
                    (III.iii; V.iv), Castle (V.v), and Chamber (II.i; III.iv, deleted). These scenes
                    all appear in other Smock Alley plays,[18] but three
                    scenes are found only in Macbeth: Rock (I.i,iii; II.iv; III.v; IV.i, deleted),
                    Garden (I.v; IV.ii), and Caue (IV.i). The 'Rock' scene is regularly associated
                    with the Witches and must have been specially prepared for this play. It is
                    possible that the 'Caue' scene substituted by Hand IV in IV.i represents a
                    refinement introduced at perhaps some later date. The only setting which raises
                    any particular question is the use of 'Towne' for the interview between Malcolm
                    and Macduff (IV.iii), a scene which according to Shakespeare's text is supposed
                    to take place at the court of Edward the Confessor in England. Possibly some
                    slight influence of the unity of place may be detected here and in D'Avenant,
                    who, curiously enough, sets the scene in Birnam Wood. 1. See the General Introduction in the first volume of this series
                    (I,i,16). I would like to thank Mr. C. P. Finlayson, Keeper of Manuscripts,
                    Edinburgh University Library, for his kindness in checking various ink shades on
                    the last page of the Smock Alley Macbeth. 2. The Smock Alley Hamlet was published as Vol. IV (1966) of
                    this series. 3. R.C. Bald ("Shakespeare on the Stage in Restoration Dublin,"
                        PMLA, LVI [1941], 369) was thus slightly misleading when he wrote:
                    "The four missing leaves in Macbeth were discovered mounted in a large portfolio
                    as item 233 of the Shakespearean Rarities preserved at Hollingbury
                    Copse." This find did not complete the Smock Alley Macbeth. 4. Bald, pp. 371-372; W. S. Clark, The Early Irish Stage
                    (Oxford, 1955), p. 75. 5. Clark, p. 208. Totterdale also appears in the Smock Alley cast for
                    Fletcher's Night-Walker (see Allan Stevenson, "The Case of the
                    Decapitated Cast," SQ, VI [1955], 285-286). Stevenson notes that
                    Totterdale had a son baptized at St. John's in Dublin in November, 1675. He also
                    notes (p. 289) that Mrs. Elizabeth Farlowe or Farlee was a member of the King's
                    company. She disappears from the London stage after April, 1678 (see The
                        London Stage, Part I, ed. William Van Lennep [Carbondale, 1965], p. 15
                        et passim) . It is possible, though not, I think, very likely, that
                    Mrs. Farlowe played the role of the Servant. If so, this would place the date of
                    the Smock Alley production between 1678 and 1682. 6. Bald, p. 373. 7. See the General Introduction (I,i,14-15). 8. Although Hand V does not appear to be the same as the eighteenth
                    century hand which occurs in the Smock Alley Twelfth Night,
                        Hamlet, King Lear, Midsummer Night's Dream, and
                        Merry Wives, I do not believe that Hand V's changes predate Pope's
                    edition. The isolation of the readings in two scenes (I.i and ii) is extremely
                    suspicious. 9. See my analysis of the Douai manuscript, "The Douai Manuscript--Six
                    Shakespearean Transcripts (1694-95)," in Charles B. Woods and Curt A. Zimansky,
                    eds., Studies in English Drama Presented to Baldwin Maxwell (Iowa City,
                    1962), pp. 158-172. 10. See George W. Stone, "Garrick's Handling of Macbeth,"
                        SP, XXXVIII (1941), 609-628. Professor Stone's article also
                    contains some comments on later eighteenth-century stage versions. 11. The Lee-Salmon prompt-book is used by permission of the Harvard
                    College Library. The 1734 Tonson edition of Macbeth is taken from
                    Theobald's 1733 text and shows no connection with the theatre. An edition of
                        Macbeth published in 1785 (with casts for that year at Drury Lane
                    and Covent Garden) reproduces essentially the Garrick version as it appears in
                    Bell (1773). 12. Bald, p. 373. 13. See the Introduction to the Smock Alley Hamlet
                    (IV,i,4-5). 14. The figures given for the cutting by Hands II, III, and IV are
                    necessarily tentative, since, frequently, the only clue to which hand is at work
                    is the color of the ink used in the marks of deletion--a dangerous criterion. I
                    have included a cut as belonging to a particular hand even when I have felt it
                    necessary to query the attribution. 15. It may be noted that a somewhat similar situation exists in the
                    Smock Alley Hamlet. There is, however, some slight evidence that,
                    despite the inaccuracies of Hand II's changes when compared with the so called
                    actors' quarto (1676), an actual copy of the printed text of that quarto was
                    used to some degree. 16. I have used Alfred Hart's figure of 2,084 lines for Macbeth ("The
                    Number of Lines in Shakespeare's Plays," RES, VIII [1932], 21).
                    D'Avenant's version runs to roughly 2,124 lines; Padua PB to 1,808; Douai MS to
                    1,888; Garrick (Bell) to 1,846; Lee to 1,857; Lee-Salmon to 1,826. The figure of
                    352 lines cut in the Smock Alley Macbeth as given in my General Introduction
                    (I,i,27) was a careless error. 17. Compare the illustration by du Guernier to Macbeth (IV.i) in
                    Rowe's 1709 edition (actually it represents a scene from D'Avenant's version),
                    the famous painting by Zoffany of Garrick in the role of Macbeth (II.i), and
                    Dawes' painting (IV.i). See W. M. Merchant, Shakespeare and the Artist
                    (Oxford, 1959), pp. 53, 58-59. 18. See the General Introduction (I,i,23-24).  &lt;/page&gt;   &lt;page n=9&gt; </field><field name="file_s">ShaMacP</field></doc></add>