<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><add><doc><field name="id">d1e2</field><field name="section_s">header</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 2 (Padua Measure
                    for Measure) [a machine-readable transcription] </field><field name="fulltext_t">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 2 (Padua Measure
                    for Measure) [a machine-readable transcription] Shakespeare, William Creation of machine-readable version: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center Creation of digital images: Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. 60 kilobytes University of Virginia Library. Charlottesville, Va. Bibliographic Society, ShaMeaP Publicly-accessible URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/bsuva/promptbook/ 1997 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century. The electronic text contains the Introduction and the Collations. The
                    prompt-book is rendered as page images. Images of the manuscript have been included from volume 2, part 2. Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 2 (Padua
                            Measure for Measure) William Shakespeare Editor G. Blakemore Evans Issued in portfolios. The prompt-books are reproduced in collotype
                            facsimile. University Press of Virginia Charlottesville, VA 1963 Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PR 2757 .E9 1960 v.2
                        Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century Published for the Bibliographical Society of the University of
                            Virginia The production of this volume was supervised by Fredson Bowers.
                         Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. All quotation marks retained as data. All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line. The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs. Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings. Library of Congress Subject Headings  1960-1963 English drama; prose; non-fiction LCSH 24-bit color; 400 dpi  March 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Added TEI header and tags. </field><field name="file_s">ShaMeaP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e130</field><field name="section_s">front</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 2 (Padua Measure
                    for Measure) [a machine-readable transcription] </field><field name="fulltext_t">Image of the spine, vol. 2Image of the cover, vol. 2 part 1Image of the title page, vol. 2 part 1Image of the cover, vol. 2 part 2Image of the title page, vol. 2 part 2  SHAKESPEAREAN PROMPT BOOKS of the SEVENTEENTH CENTURY  Vol. II: Part i  Introductions to the Padua Measure for MeasureThe Winter's Tale Collations Edited by G. Blakemore Evans  Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia 
                    Charlottesville, Virginia  1963  EDITORIAL ADVISORY COMMITTEE 
                    The Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia  ARTHUR F.
                    STOCKER, Chairman FREDSON BOWERS  JOHN COOK WYLLIE  The production of this volume
                    was supervised by Fredson Bowers.  ContentsIntroduction to Measure for MeasureMeasure for Measure: CollationsIntroduction to The Winter's TaleThe Winter's Tale: Collations</field><field name="file_s">ShaMeaP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e220</field><field name="section_s">introduction</field><field name="title_s">IntroductionMeasure for Measure: Padua First Folio </field><field name="fulltext_t">IntroductionMeasure for Measure: Padua First Folio  In the General Introduction I have advanced reasons for considering a date
                    between 1625 and 1635 for the Padua First Folio prompt-book of Measure for
                        Measure. I also claimed for it some connection, together with the other
                    two Padua prompt-books, with Sir Edward Dering's group of amateur actors and
                    discussed the bearing which this association with Sir Edward had on the relation
                    of these prompt-books to the public stage.1 Unlike the
                    Padua prompt-books of Macbeth and The Winter's Tale, the
                    prompt-book of Measure for Measure does not contain any actors' names
                    or initials, but the hand responsible for making the prompt-notations, and most
                    probably the deletions, is the same as that in Macbeth.  Although much more has been cut by the reviser in Measure for Measure
                    than in Macbeth, the treatment of the play as a whole is more
                        conservative.2 Something under 579 lines (since
                    this figure includes half-lines) have been cut; as in Macbeth, much of
                    the cutting seems to have been aimed at shortening
                     the principal roles (see the notes on
                    II.iv.9-17 and V.i.112-114). These cuts leave a play of about 2,081 lines,3 comparable in length to the 2,134 lines of the Tonson
                    (1722) acting text, the 2,013 lines of the Bell version, and the 2,037 lines of
                    the Inchbald version.4 In Tonson, Bell, and Inchbald,
                    however, the cutting is more concerned with removing certain of the low-comedy
                    scenes and with the usual eighteenth-century process of `refinement,' less
                    concerned with shortening the leading roles.  The longer cuts (18 lines or more) are as follows:  I.ii.7-44 (conversation between Lucio and the two Gentlemen). Tonson and Bell
                    were even more severe on this scene, omitting everything down through 119.
                    Inchbald retains a substantial part of the opening lines, including those of
                    Mistress Overdone and Pompey, but reverses the order of scenes ii and iii.
                    D'Avenant dispenses entirely with Mistress Overdone, Pompey (except as the
                    `Fool' in Acts IV and V), Elbow, Froth, etc. throughout his version.  II.i.230-265 (dialogue between Escalus and Pompey). D'Avenant, Tonson, and Bell
                    omit. Inchbald preserves 258 (`I advise . . .') -267 as part of a separate scene
                    following II.ii.  III.i.21-39 (part of the Duke's speech on death). D'Avenant cuts the whole
                    speech; Tonson, 23-35 (`Thou . . . Moon.'); Bell, 19-21 (`Thou . . . dust.'),
                    35-36 (`and . . . palsied-Eld:'); Inchbald, 17-21 (`Thou . . . dust.'), 23-32
                    (`Thou . . . sooner.').  III.ii.43-89 (conversation in which Pompey tries to persuade Lucio to go bail for
                    him). This considerable cut would have partly satisfied the editor of Bell,
                    Francis Gentleman, who (p. 314) thinks the whole scene, down to line 90, "low
                    ribaldry, too insignificant to make even an upper gallery laugh; and too
                    indecent to bear." Indeed Gentleman later (p. 318) suggests beginning the scene
                    at 209. Nevertheless it was mostly retained in performance (also in Inchbald),
                    somewhat shortened and bowdlerized. The PB reviser does not seem to have been
                    concerned with the moral implications of the lines at all; at least he makes no
                    attempt to chasten Lucio's later speeches in this scene. Tonson cuts 42, 48-55
                    (`for . . . worse?'); Bell, 42, 48-55 (`for . . . worse?'), 58-63
                    ('Clo. Troth . . . so.'), 83; Inchbald, 35-42 (`he . . . sir'), 47-63
                    (`What . . . so.'), 66-72 (`for . . . borne.') .
                     III.ii.197-218 (scene in which Mistress Overdone is sent to prison by Escalus).
                    This cut gets rid of the Bawd's role here entirely. D'Avenant cuts all this
                    material; Bell and Inchbald also omit the Bawd, cutting 200-218 (`But . . .
                    words.').  III.ii.276-296 (the Duke's rhymed moralizing). Part of the general reduction in
                    D'Avenant; Tonson, Bell, and Inchbald cut 277-278 (`Pattern . . . go:'), 287-290
                    (`How . . . ?'). Most modern readers would consider this speech a natural cut,
                    but Gentleman (Bell, p. 320) thinks otherwise: "The sentiments of this soliloquy
                    are just and instructive."  IV.iii.4-21 (Pompey's list of Mistress Overdone's customers). Inchbald cuts as in
                    PB; D'Avenant, Tonson, and Bell omit 1-21.  It will be noticed that only two of these longer cuts are aimed at reducing the
                    major roles (III.i.21-39 and III.ii.276-296); most of the cutting affecting
                    these roles is accounted for by the large number (86 in all) of short scattered
                    deletions (see particularly V.i). Not infrequently, as one might expect, the
                    heart has been cut out of some of the most poetically famous speeches in the
                    play (e.g., I.i.28-43; II.ii.109-125, 166-172; II.iv.9-17, 159-167; III.i.21-39;
                    IV.iv.23-30); and in this respect the Padua prompt-book is rather more culpable
                    than the eighteenth-century versions.  No attempt has been made to reduce the number of characters, nor are any changes
                    made in the assignment of speeches. There is also little to comment on in the
                    matter of stage business. The handling of what modern texts from Pope on,
                    including Bell and Inchbald, call Scene ii of Act III follows the Folio
                    arrangement by which the Duke remains on stage, with no change of scene implied.
                    Pope is the first to introduce a change of scene here, from `The
                    Prison' to `The Street'. Rowe and Tonson retain the Folio
                    arrangement. We may also notice the early entrance for the Provost and others in
                    I.ii, at line 114, an arrangement which appears to ignore the Folio scene break
                    (uncancelled, however) and agrees with Rowe's later handling of the scene.
                    Moreover the reviser-prompter's delay in Lucio's entrance also anticipates Bell
                    and Inchbald.  Two prompt-warnings are of special significance inasmuch as they support a
                    pre-Restoration date for the Padua 
                    prompt-books. At IV.iii we find `Bee ready Abhorson' and at V.i.259, `Bee
                    ready'. I have not found this particular form of imperative warning in
                    Restoration prompt-books, but it is to be found occasionally in prompt-books
                    belonging to the second and third decades of the century.5 The `florish' added at the opening of V.i may also be
                        significant.6 The following characteristics of the prompt-book may be noticed: a. A single hand is responsible for all prompt-notations and calls. The
                        same hand is probably also responsible for the deletions.b. The play was cut first, the calls for the characters being added
                        afterwards. This is shown by the way in which the calls and entrances make
                        allowance for the cuts (see, for example, I.ii.5). A few cuts, however, were
                        made after the original calls.c. The calls for the characters wanted in a scene are essentially
                        non-anticipative. Exceptions may be seen, however, in the use of `Bee
                        ready', twice (IV.iii and V.i. 259), and something of an anticipative nature
                        may be found in the habit, where a new scene begins at the top of the next
                        page or even at the top of the second column, of placing the call for the
                        characters at the bottom of the preceding page or column. An extreme case of
                        this occurs in the notation for I.iii, where the entries for `Duke / Fryer
                        Tho.' are marked at the bottom of the first column, although Scene iii does
                        not begin immediately at the top of the second column. Except for the `Bee
                        ready' notations this is perhaps the clearest case of an anticipative call
                        in the prompt-book. At the beginning of IV.i, which falls at the top of a
                        new page (64), a `Song' is called for by the text. The prompter's call for
                        the song, however, is given on page 63 at the point where, with the cutting
                        of the Duke's final speech, the reviser 
                        has concluded the act. Such a warning for something at the beginning of an
                        act is unique in the prompt-book.d. No characters are called for at the beginning of an act, all act breaks
                        being very carefully marked. See note on III.ii.274.e. There is a tendency for the prompter to bring characters on a little
                        before the Folio's s.d.'s indicate (see I.ii.85, 114; III.ii.41; V.i.166).
                        This is a characteristic of professional prompt-books.  1. Shakespearean Prompt-Books of the Seventeenth Century,
                    Vol. I, Part i (1960), pp. 7-10. 2. I have compared the Padua acting version with the following later
                    stage texts: D'Avenant's The Law against Lovers (1673), in
                        Works, ed. Maidment and Logan, V (1874), 117-211; the Tonson (1722)
                    acting text (Lincoln's-Inn-Fields); the Bell text (Covent Garden), edited by
                    Francis Gentleman, in Shakespeare (1773), Vol. III; and the Inchbald
                    text (Covent Garden) in the British Theatre (1808), Vol. III. The cuts
                    in the Collier-Perkins Second Folio (1632) have also been compared. No attempt
                    has been made to compare Charles Gildon's adaptation of Shakespeare and
                    D'Avenant, Measure for Measure, or Beauty the Beast Advocate
                    (1700). 3. Based on Alfred Hart's total of 2660 lines (RES [1932],
                    VIII, 21). 4. These figures are, more than usually, estimates because of the
                    amount of prose in Measure for Measure. No comparison in length with
                        The Law against Lovers, D'Avenant's telescoped version of
                        Measure for Measure and Much Ado, is possible. 5. See W. W. Greg's discussion of the prompt-books of The Welsh
                        Embassador (c. 1623) and Believe as you List (1631) in
                        Elizabethan Dramatic Documents (1931), pp. 217-219, 279-282,
                    293-300. 6. This direction is added in several places in the Padua Winter's
                        Tale; see, below, the Introduction to that play, p. 20.  &lt;/page&gt;   &lt;page n=7&gt; </field><field name="file_s">ShaMeaP</field></doc></add>