<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><add><doc><field name="id">d1e2</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">header</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 6 (Smock
                            Alley Othello) </field><field name="fulltext_t">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 6 (Smock Alley
                    Othello) [a machine-readable transcription] Shakespeare, William Creation of machine-readable version: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center Creation of digital images: Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. 125 kilobytes University of Virginia Library. Charlottesville, Va. Bibliographical Society, ShaOthP Publicly-accessible URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/bsuva/promptbook/ 1997 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century. The electronic text contains the Introduction and the Collations. The
                    prompt-book is rendered as page images. Images of the manuscript have been included from volume 6, part 2. Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 6 (Smock
                            Alley Othello) William Shakespeare Editor G. Blakemore Evans Issued in portfolios. The prompt-books are reproduced in collotype
                            facsimile. University Press of Virginia Charlottesville, VA 1980 Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PR 2757 .E9 1960 v.6
                        Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century Published for the Bibliographical Society of the University of
                            Virginia The print source incorrectly annotates Act V, scene 2, lines 94-95 as
                            lines 94-85.  Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. All quotation marks retained as data. All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
                    word has been joined to the preceding line. The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
                    use, and thumbnail GIFs. Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
                    establishing analytical groupings. Library of Congress Subject Headings  1960-1980 English drama; prose; non-fiction LCSH 24-bit color; 400 dpi  March 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Added TEI header and tags.</field><field name="file_s">ShaOthP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e130</field><field name="section_s">front</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 6 (Smock
                            Alley Othello) </field><field name="fulltext_t"> SHAKESPEAREAN PROMPT-BOOKSof the SEVENTEENTH CENTURY Vol. VI: Part i Introduction to the Smock Alley
                            Othello Collations Edited by G. Blakemore Evans A Publication of The Bibliographical Society of the University of
                    Virginia University Press of Virginia, Charlottesville 1980 PR
                    2757.E9 1960 V.6 Pt.1 Copy 3 THE UNIVERSITY PRESS OF VIRGINIA
                    Copyright 1980 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia
                    First published 1980Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data Shakespeare,
                    William, 1564-1616. Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth
                    century. ContentsIntroduction to the Smock Alley Othello ....... 1Collations ............................................. 13</field><field name="file_s">ShaOthP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e194</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="section_s">introduction</field><field name="title_s">Introduction Smock Alley Othello Third Folio</field><field name="fulltext_t">Introduction Smock Alley Othello Third Folio THE Smock Alley Othello[1] shares several
                    prompt-hands with other Smock Alley prompt-books and is further linked with the
                    Smock Alley Hamlet, Macbeth, I and II Henry IV, Henry VIII,
                    and John Wilson's Belphegor by the appearance of six actors' names
                    (more than in any other Smock Alley Shakespearean prompt-book), all inserted by
                    Hand V (see below), among the prompt-calls: Joseph Trefusis (as ?Officer in
                    I.iii, and as First Gentleman in II.i), John Totterdale (role uncertain, in
                    I.iii), Barnes (as Sailor in II.i), Walmsley (as Second Senator in I.iii), John
                    Freeman (as Montano in II.i), and Charles [?Ashbury] (as a Messenger in I.iii
                    and as Third Gentleman in II.i).[2] What appear to be
                    two other names occur,  but they have been so badly shaved in binding
                    as to be unidentifiable: `. . . oin' (or'. . . vin'), who played the First
                    Senator in I.iii, and `. . . ick', whose role, also in I.iii, is uncertain.[3] As with other Smock Alley prompt-books, the relative dating of Othello
                    depends upon the appearance of such actors' names. Unfortunately, the evidence
                    for assigning initial and terminal dates for actors appearing at Smock Alley is
                    in most instances more or less conjectural, especially so because actors often
                    seem to have moved back and forth between Smock Alley and the London theatres.
                    W. S. Clark assigns tentative dates for five of these actors: Trefusis (c.
                    1675-88), Totterdale (c. 1674-88), Barnes (c. 1675-c. 1680), Walmsley (c.
                    1675-88), and Freeman (c.1675-82).[4] Allan Stevenson
                    first suggested the possible identification of `Charles' as Charles Ashbury, the
                    son of Joseph Ashbury, himself an actor and the manager of the Smock Alley
                    Theatre from 1675-1720, but we know nothing more definite about Charles than
                    that he was probably associated with Smock Alley around the dates indicated by
                    Clark for the other actors involved.[5] Even if some
                    kind of tentative dating may be suggested on the basis of these actors' names,
                    such dating would probably give us only a terminus ad quem, since there
                    is evidence that the Othello prompt-book may have been used for at
                    least one earlier production before these particular actors took part in the
                        play.6 Only one of the actors named, John Freeman, may perhaps help to set certain
                    probable limits for dating the Othello promptbook, at least in so far
                    as his connection with the production is concerned. Clark's dating for Freeman,
                    as noted above, is "c.  1675-82," but in the light of more complete
                    information now furnished by The London Stage (Part 1: 1660-1700)[7] it can now be shown that Freeman was performing in
                    London at Dorset Garden in December 1680 (1680-81 season), November 1681
                    (1681-82 season), and December 1683 (1683-84 season), but does not appear in
                    London again until March 1686 (1685-86 season). This would seem to leave three
                    probable dates for the appearance of his name in the Othello
                    prompt-book: (1) prior to 1680, (2) the 1682-83 season, and (3) the 1684-85
                        season.[8] A choice between these three possibilities may perhaps be influenced by
                    consideration of the Smock Alley prompt-book (manuscript) of John Wilson's
                        Belphegor,[9] which received its first
                    performance, an apparently disastrous one, in Dublin. Clark and Stevenson differ
                    on the most probable date for this production, but they are agreed that the play
                    was produced at Smock Alley when Wilson was himself in Dublin. Stevenson
                    advances three possible periods that would satisfy this requirement: 1677-78,
                    1680, and 1682-83.[10] Clark advances 1677-78 as the
                    date, without mentioning any other possibility.[11]
                    Stevenson, while admitting that 1677-78 "may have been the most suitable one,"
                    believes that 1682-83 "seems more appropriate for the whole group of actors and
                    fits better" with a satiric allusion,  which he dates as 1683 or
                    after, to the play's failure. Among the eleven actors named in the
                        Belphegor prompt-book, two, John Freeman and Barnes,[12] also appear in Othello, and two other
                    members of the Belphegor cast, George Bright and Mrs. Osborne, can,
                    along with Freeman, be traced on the London stage (Dorset Garden) during some of
                    the years in question. All the available evidence, detailed in the note
                        below,[13] tends to support Clark's claim for the
                    years 1677-78.  The link between the Othello and the Belphegor promptbooks
                    furnished by the common appearance of Freeman and Barnes in both,[14] while admittedly fragile, may suggest that the  two earlier terminal dates for Othello (prior to 1680 or
                    1682-83) are slightly more likely than the third (1684-85). Moreover, the
                    absence of Trefusis in Belphegor and his presence in Othello,
                        Hamlet (c. 1676-79), and I Henry IV (at least
                    before January 1685),[15] where his name is written in
                    by the same hand (there Hand III) as Hand V in Othello, though again
                    evidentially fragile, further suggests that these prompt-books may fall into a
                    position after, but not long after, the Belphegor production, which, as
                    I have shown above, may most probably be dated in 1677-78. In the first volume
                    of this series, I advanced 1680-82 as a likely terminal date for the Othello
                        prompt-book.[16] I would now, in the light of
                    the fuller information on Freeman and the date of the Belphegor
                    production, suggest a terminal date for Othello either shortly before
                    1680 or in 1682-83, still admitting, however, what seems to me the less likely
                    possibility of the 1684-85 season.  Before we consider further the possibility that more than one production of the
                    play is represented in the Othello promptbook, that is, a production
                    predating the insertion of the actors' names by Hand V, it will be necessary to
                    discuss the main prompt-hands and, so far as possible, identify their appearance
                    in the other Smock Alley prompt-books. R. C. Bald long ago noted that "as many
                    as six hands are visible in the notes to Othello."[17] There are, however, a number of notations where exact
                    identification is at best uncertain and still other hands may well be
                        present.[18] Hand I is responsible for the advance
                    prompt-calls and appears again in Macbeth as Hand III. Hand II gives
                    the scene settings and makes occasional changes in the  text, usually
                    in connection with readings found in Q1-3 and Q (1681). It occurs again in
                        Macbeth (Hands I and II), Hamlet (Hands I and II),
                        Lear (Hand b, Twelfth Night (Hand I), Henry VIII
                    (Hand I) and I Henry IV (Hand II).[19] It is,
                    thus, the most ubiquitous and important hand in the Smock Alley prompt-books.
                    Hand III writes in emendations in the text and is to be distinguished from Hand
                    IV, which also inserts emendations, by characteristics usually associated with
                    earlier seventeenth-century hands. Hand IV appears to be later than any of the
                    others (?eighteenth-century) and is, like Hand II, usually associated with
                    changes made in conformity with quarto readings. Neither Hand III nor IV seems
                    to occur elsewhere in the Smock Alley prompt-books. Hand V, which has already
                    been mentioned in connection with the vexed problem of dating, is responsible
                    for all the actors' names and a number of other important prompt-notes. It
                    occurs elsewhere only in I Henry IV (as Hand III] and, possibly (see
                    note 13), in the Belphegor prompt-book. Hand VI inserts a number of
                    prompt-notes mostly concerned with scene settings and sound effects. The same
                    hand also appears in Hamlet (Hand III), Julius Caesar (acting
                    list), Macbeth (Hand IV), Merry Wives (Hand I), and, perhaps,
                    Wilson's Belphegor (main prompt-hand).  With the main prompt-hands now established, we may return to the question
                    postponed above: Does the Smock Alley Othello show evidence of serving
                    for more than one production of the play? Such evidence as there is would seem
                    to support the view that Hand V's participation in the prompt-book may indeed
                    represent a later reworking of an earlier production. Hand V supplements or
                    cancels prompt-notes by other hands, but his own annotations are never
                    superseded or supplemented. The beginning of II.i shows perhaps the clearest
                    example of Hand V's work. His addition to (or perhaps substitution for) Hand
                    II's setting (`&lt;Ca&gt;stle') of `ye Shipps' and his handling of the Folio
                    three Gentlemen, whom he reduces to two, appearing to  supersede (or
                    at least supplementing) Hand I's treatment, as well as his cancelation of
                    prompt-notes by Hand ?III (lines 20, 49-51) and Hand VI (lines 73-74, 75), aimed
                    at getting rid of the gun salutes (lines 55, 94), all strongly suggest a
                    probable reworking of the scene as originally planned. But there is little here
                    to tell us whether Hand V's revisions represent changes for a later separate
                    production or were made as the final stage in the initial preparation of the
                    prompt-book. Perhaps however, Hand V's cancellation of prompt-notes by hands
                    other than Hands I and II, who may be credited with preparing the first rough
                    draft of the prompt-book, may be taken as evidence that Hand V's work represents
                    a distinct new production. If this is so, and I would say the evidence in II.i
                    and elsewhere[20] seems generally to support such a
                    view, we must assign a date for the original production as somewhat earlier than
                    the years associated with Hand V's intervention (i.e. shortly before 1680,
                    1682-83, or possibly 1684-85). How much earlier there is no certain way of
                    knowing, but the general community of prompt-hands, particularly Hand II, with
                    other Smock Alley promptbooks, none of which can be shown to be earlier than
                    1675, suggests a date in the later part of the 1670's.  The Othello prompt-book is, unfortunately, incomplete, lacking six pages
                    (795-800, sigs. 3X5-3Y1 in F3) of the text from II.i.88 to III.iii.19 and the
                    final page (817, sig.3Z4 in F3), containing the concluding lines of the play
                    (V.ii.360-371), a total of 735 lines.[21] The loss of
                    these sections of the text makes it very difficult to determine the exact amount
                    of cutting undertaken for the Smock Alley production (or productions). In  what remains of the prompt-book, roughly around 326 lines have been
                    marked, by one hand or another, for omission, but we can only guess at the
                    extent of the cutting in the missing pages. Of the 723 lines lost between
                    II.i.88 and III.iii.19, the eighteenth-century acting texts cut somewhat over
                    two hundred lines, including the whole of II.ii (the proclamation scene), III.i
                    (the clown scene), and III.ii (Othello giving letters to be sent to Venice).
                    Although the Clown was originally retained in the prompt-call by Hand I at the
                    opening of III.iv, a later hand (Hand ?III) has deleted his entry and cut lines
                        1-22.[22] It seems likely, therefore, that the
                    Clown's earlier appearance in III.i (some 30 lines) was also deleted at the same
                    time, but whether the rest of the scene (another 28 lines) was also cut, as in
                    the eighteenth-century acting texts, or retained, as in the Collier MS cutting,
                    must remain uncertain. Since the amount of cutting in other parts of the Smock
                    Alley Othello is comparatively light, we may perhaps suggest a total of
                    about 95 lines cut in the missing six pages. This would give an over-all total
                    of around 421 lines cut and leave a final acting version of about 2,808 lines, a
                    stage text considerably longer than any found in the eighteenth-century acting
                    texts and Kemble.[23] Marvin Rosenberg, in his interesting stage-history, The Masks of Othello
                    (1961), has analyzed a number of the cuts in the Smock Alley PB and finds there
                    some attempt being made to "refine" both Othello and Desdemona in accordance
                    with  the doctrine of decorum, citing Thomas Rymer's famous attack on
                    the play and its principal characters.[24] While I
                    would agree that questions of decorum may play some slight part in the pattern
                    of cutting, probably under the influence of Thomas Betterton's "heroic"
                    conception of the role of Othello (noted by Rosenberg; see, perhaps, I.iii.273;
                    III.iii.24, 180-183; IV.i.35-44, IV.ii. 56- 64, 161-165), I suspect that the
                    real reason for deleting `Exchange me for a Goat' in III.iii.180-183 was more
                    concerned with a desire to get rid of the difficult language in the following
                    lines than with the possible indecorum in the reference to such a vulgar animal
                    as a goat. In III.iii.345-357, Othello's famous "farewell" to his "occupation,"
                    which is reduced to some four lines,[25] it is
                    possible to see "refinement" at work, perhaps, in the cutting of lines 345-347,
                    but that the latter part of the speech was cut because of an over-bombastic,
                    rhetorical tone, unsuitable to the heroic Othello (as Mr. Rosenberg suggests)
                    seems very questionable. The speech was left untouched in eighteenth-century
                    acting versions and singled out for special praise by Francis Gentleman (see the
                    Collations). More simply, I think, what is behind the cutting here, and for the
                    most part in the remainder of the play, is a desire to shorten the play somewhat
                    by deleting what seemed to the reviser(s) non-essential lines and passages, in
                    two cases perhaps under the influence of Quarto 1 (see IV.iii.22-57, 88-102).
                        [26] And, although one may note the occasional
                    deletion of passages with special sexual reference (as in III.iii.345-347,
                    IV.i.35-44, or IV.ii. 56-64), other passages equally or more explicitly sexual
                    remain untouched. Moreover, although the eighteenth century completely deleted
                    Othello's trance scene in IV.i, excised the character of Bianca from the play
                    and Othello's brief appearance in V.i., each in its way, we may assume,
                    considered  offenses against aspects of the doctrine of decorum, the
                    Smock Alley PB retains them essentially uncut.[27] In
                    other words, decorum or refinement in eighteenth-century terms played a very
                    small part in the production of the Smock Alley PB.  As in the other Restoration theatre versions generally, the reviser(s) at Smock
                    Alley either jettisoned "hard" or obsolete words and phrases (for example,
                    I.i.16; I.ii.17, 56, 89; II.i.63-65; III.iii.287; IV.ii.30) or substituted other
                    readings (for example, I.i.39; I.ii.17, 22; I.iii.275; II.i.8-9; V.i.22). He (or
                    they) also shows a knowledge of the earlier quarto editions, particularly Q2-3
                    and possibly Q1 and Q (1681)[28](see I.i.110; I.ii.22;
                    I.iii.110, 159, 261, etc.), a knowledge that argues for a close connection
                    between the Smock Alley PB and the current London performances, which, according
                    to the 1681 quarto, used the quarto version stemming from Q2 (1630). Since there
                    was a continual exchange between the London theatres and Smock Alley, it is fair
                    to assume that many of the cuts and other changes, which now appear for the
                    first time in the Smock Alley PB, were in fact importations from London and that
                    the Smock Alley PB preserves for us in its essentials Othello as it was
                    performed in Restoration London. Another indication of this influence is the
                    large number of cuts common to the Smock Alley PB and the eighteenth-century
                    London acting versions (see the Collations), since the line of influence would
                    certainly not be through Smock Alley. On the other hand, the Smock Alley PB has
                    a substantial number of cuts (for example, I.ii.19-24; I.iii. 83-87; II.i.36-42;
                    III.iii.351-357) and some twenty-eight readings (I.i.39, 159; I.ii.12, 17;
                    I.iii.59, 258, 264, 274, 279, 374; II.i.8-9, 10, 34 (bis), 53, 56-57,
                    59, 60,66-67; III.iii.135, 137,393,455,478; IV.i.22; IV.ii.74; V.i. 14, 22)
                    which are either unique or anticipate later editorial emendations. There is, of
                    course, no way of determining whether at least some of these cuts or readings
                    are really peculiar to Smock Alley or whether they represent details of the
                    London tradition that failed to leave their mark on later stage practice.  The stage settings used for the Smock Alley Othello seem to be almost
                    entirely stock scenes, all but one (`ye Shipps' II.i) being employed at least
                    once in other Smock Alley Shakespeare  prompt-books.[29] They are: `Towne' (I.i); `Presence' (I.iii, IV.ii
                    [later replaced]); `Castle' (II.i, V.i); `ye Shipps' (II.i [perhaps a rear
                    shutter to be used with `Castle']); `Chamber' (III.iv); `Court' (IV.i
                    [replaced]); `pallace' (IV.i); `Anti-Chamber' (IV.ii); `Bed Chamber' (V.ii
                    [presumably the same as `Chamber' with the addition of a bed]).[30]1. The Smock Alley Othello promptbook is now in the
                        Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C., and is here reproduced by the
                        kind permission of the Trustees.2. It has only recently been pointed out that `Charles' took the
                        roles of Peto and Page in II Henry IV. Gunnar Sorelius discovered
                        twenty-seven cuttings (from the Smock Alley Third Folio) of I Henry
                            IV and twenty-four of II Henry IV in the
                        Halliwell-Phillipps' scrapbooks in the Shakespeare Memorial Library in
                        Stratford-upon-Avon (I Henry IV: Vols. I-III, VI, IX; II Henry
                            IV: Vols. III-VI) and has published an account of what remains of
                        these Smock Alley prompt-books (including the earlier known single fragment
                        of I Henry IV in the Folger Shakespeare Library) in the
                            Shakespeare Quarterly ("The Smock Alley Prompt-Books of
                            I and 2 Henry IV," XXII (1971), 111-128). In addition
                        to the appearance of `Charles' in II Henry IV, Trefusis played the
                        First Carrier in II.i of I Henry IV and Powell (perhaps George
                        Powell, son of Martin Powell, also an actor, who, with his father, appears
                        with the United Company in 1686-87), the Second Carrier. From the Folger
                        fragment it was already known that Longmore (who continued to play at Smock
                        Alley into the eighteenth century) played the Chamberlain in II.i and II.ii.
                        In the dramatis personae list for II Henry IV in the Third
                        Folio (sig. 212v) Sorelius found the names of the actors
                        who played the `Irregular Humorists': Poins by `Shepheard', Falstaff by
                        `Baker', Bardolph by `Eales', Pistol by `Gilbert', `Charles', as already
                        noted, playing Peto and Boy. Except for `Charles', none of these names
                        appears elsewhere in the Smock Alley prompt-books. Francis Baker has long
                        been known to have played Falstaff at Smock Alley before 1685, but this is
                        the first evidence tying him directly to the role. Of the others, apart
                        perhaps from `Charles' [?Ashbury] nothing is known.3. Allan Stevenson ("The Case of the Decapitated Cast or The
                            Night-walker at Smock Alley,"SQ, VI [1955],
                        291) suggests that we might "just possibly" read the second name as
                        `&lt;P&gt;ink' (i.e. William Pinkethman). Pinkethman appears in the cast of
                        the Smock Alley Belphegor about 1677-78 (see later discussion).4. William Smith Clark, The Early Irish Stage: The Beginnings
                            to 1720 (1955), pp.207-209. Clark does not mention
                        `Charles'.5. Stevenson, p. 290.6. Othello was produced at Smock Alley, very shortly
                        after the Restoration, in late 1662 (see Clark, p. 61), but this production
                        could have had no direct connection with the present prompt-book, since it
                        could not have used a copy of the Third Folio (1663/64) as a basis for its
                        prompt-book.7. Ed. by William Van Lennep, 1965 (Critical Introduction by Emmet
                        L. Avery and Arthur H. Scouten).8. We are forced to work with such evidence as we possess, but it
                        should be pointed out that these dates are less definite than they might
                        seem for two special reasons: (1) because an actor can be shown to have
                        taken part in a performance during a given season does not mean that he (or
                        she) necessarily remained with the company throughout the season (he may
                        have acted elsewhere, Smock Alley, for example); (2) on the other hand, the
                        fact that his name is not associated with say the Duke's Company, or later
                        the United Company (from the 1682-83 season on), for other performances (or
                        indeed for any performances) during a particular season does not mean that
                        he did not act various unrecorded roles during that season, since our
                        records of the personnel of the London companies for any given year depend
                        most frequently upon occasional theatre documents and actor lists (printed
                        or manuscript) attached to published versions of the plays performed. More
                        often than not we simply do not know who performed in the bulk of the
                        productions for the season in question.9. Folger MS. V.b.109 (formerly 827.1). The scribe is the same as
                        the one responsible for copying out the missing pages in the Smock Alley
                            Merry Wives of Windsor prompt-book, and as Eland VI in
                            Hamlet. There are numerous textual revisions in Wilson's hand,
                        but whether they are connected with the Smock Alley production or with the
                        much later London production (1690) is not now clear. This prompt-book was
                        unknown to M. C. Nahm (John Wilson's "The Cheats," 1935), who is
                        the principal source of biographical information on Wilson.10. Stevenson, p. 293.11. Clark, pp. 81-82.12. Freeman played the role of Belzebub (46 lines, of which 15
                        have been cut; roughly comparable to his role of Montano in
                        Othello, 60 lines, amount of cutting uncertain because of missing
                        pages in the prompt-book). Of Barnes, who was introduced as a `Boy' to sing
                        a single lyric, (his part as a Sailor in Othello is even slighter,
                        four lines), nothing is really known, although Clark (p. 207) gives "c.
                        1675-C. 1680" as the span of his acting career at Smock Alley. The only
                        evidence for these dates is Clark's dating of Belphegor in 1677-78,
                        a date which I am inclined to accept (see discussion above). All we know
                        further is that a `Mr. Barns' (or `Barnes') turns up as a member of the
                        United Company in London in the seasons of 1689-90 and 1690-91, at which
                        times at least six other actors formerly associated with Smock Alley are
                        also members of the company.13. The London Stage (Part l: 1660-1700), ed. William
                        Van Lennep, 1965) furnishes the following information: (1) George Bright
                        first appears on the London stage (Dorset Garden) in 1678-79 (April 1679),
                        then in 1679-80 (June 1680), 1681-82 (November 1681; January 1682), 1682-83
                        (November 1682; May 1683), 1683-84 (December 1683; March 1684); (2) Mrs.
                        Osborne first appears on the London stage (Dorset Garden) in 1671-72
                        (September 1671; January 1672; August 1672), then in 1672-73 (November 1672;
                        March 1673; May 1673); 1674-75 (November 1674), 167576 (July 1676), 1677-78,
                        (September 1677),1679-80 (February, 1680), 1681-82 (November 1681, twice;
                        January 1682) 1682-83 (May 1683), 1684-85 (August 1685). This evidence,
                        coupled with that on Freeman, suggests that the second and third dates for
                        the Belphegor production are unlikely, first, because, though
                        Bright and Mrs. Osborne appear to have been absent from the London stage in
                        1680-81, Freeman was performing at Dorset Garden in those years (December
                        1680 and January 1681); and, second, because, though Freeman was apparently
                        available for Smock Alley in 1682-83, Bright and Mrs. Osborne (Bright
                        particularly) were acting in London during that season. We are left,
                        therefore, with the earliest proposed date (1677-78). For this date the
                        evidence as far as Freeman and Bright are concerned is negative (i.e., there
                        is no record of their performance in London at this time), but Mrs.
                        Osborne's London record shows that she could have been playing at Smock
                        Alley at any time between October 1677 and January 1679.14. Apart from the appearance of Freeman and Barnes in both casts
                        there are perhaps two other slender connecting links between the
                            Othello and Belphegor prompt-books: (1) the main
                        prompt-hand in Belphegor may be the same as Hand VI in
                            Othello (I am much less sure of this than I was formerly, see
                        Vols. I and IV of this series, pp. 17 and 3 respectively); (2) in both
                        instances where Barnes' name appears in the prompt-calls in
                            Belphegor (pp. 36, 37), it appears to be inserted by a hand
                        different from the main prompt-hand. This second hand may be, though again I
                        cannot be sure, the same as Hand V in Othello the hand responsible
                        for Barnes' and the other actors' names, where Hand V also inserts an
                        actor's name into another hand's advance call (see I.ii.79-82, I.iii.
                        (opening), II.i.1-5).15. Stevenson (p. 284) is wrong when he argues that Francis
                        Baker, who played Falstaff (see note 2), was in London by 1683. He
                        interpreted literally a misprint in the actors' list of Edward Ravenscroft's
                            Dame Dobson (1684; acted May 1683 at Dorset Garden) that
                        assigned the role of Mrs. Francis to `Mr. Baker' instead of, as properly, to
                        Mrs. Baker. Van Lennep (The London Stage, Part I, p. 319) silently
                        corrects the error.16. General Introduction, Vol. I, Part i, pp. 19-20. A single
                        unique agreement at III.iii.362 between the Smock Alley PB and the 1681
                        quarto edition of Othello (see the Collations) is perhaps
                        suggestive but does not in itself rule out a date before 1681 for the
                        version of the Smock Alley PB connection with Hand V. There is possibly some
                        influence of Q(1681) at III.iii.135, where its error might lead to Hand II's
                        unique emendation.17. "Shakespeare on the Stage in Restoration Dublin,"
                            PMLA, LVI (1941), 373.18. See particularly I.i.159; I.iii.342 (and IV.iii.25); III.iv.
                        (opening s.d.); V.ii. (opening).19. I have come to the belated conclusion that Hands I and II in
                            Hamlet and Macbeth, Hand I in Lear,
                            Twelfth Night, and Henry VIII, and Hand II in
                            Othello and I Henry IV are in fact all the same hand.
                        This conclusion, of course, vitiates my treatment of this hand in the Smock
                        Alley Hamlet and Macbeth prompt-books (Vols. IV and V) of
                        this series and telescopes what, in the General Introduction (Vol. I, p.
                        17), I called Hands A and C. I should also  add here that what I treat
                        as Hands III and VII in Hamlet are, I now believe, a single hand. I
                        apologize for what I now consider to be these serious errors, but anyone who
                        has tried to disentangle seventeenth-century hands, especially prompt-book
                        hands, will, I trust, feel more sorrow than anger.20. See the Collation at III.iii.422; III.iv.60-67; IV.i.152-163,
                        177-186, 225; IV.ii (setting), 168; V.ii (setting), 222-226, 243-
                        248.21. Although the reason for the loss of these four leaves can
                        only be guessed at, it seems highly likely that the agent of loss here, as
                        elsewhere in the Smock Alley prompt-books, was Halliwell-Phillipps. Since
                        the last page of Othello (817) in F3 was the recto of the first
                        page (818) of Antony and Cleopatra, it is almost certain, when the
                        Smock Alley F3 was broken up by Halliwell-Phillipps and the plays bound
                        separately, that this page was included with Antony and Cleopatra
                        (now lost). The Smock Alley Macbeth and Hamlet offer an
                        exactly analogous case (see Vol. V, Part i, p. I of this series). The other
                        six missing pages (795-800) were most probably either (1) detached for
                        special exhibition purposes and never reassembled (compare the treatment of
                        four leaves in the Smock Alley Macbeth) or (2) cut up into
                        fragments and pasted into one of Halliwell-Phillipps' many scrapbooks
                        (compare the scandalous treatment of the Smock Alley I and II
                            Henry IV referred to above in Note 2). Someday, we may still hope,
                        all four leaves may be recovered. Professor Gunnar Sorelius (see note 1) has
                        kindly assured me that the missing leaves are not lurking in the Stratford
                        or Folger Halliwell-Phillipps' scrapbooks.22. The Clown appears in the cast list in the 1681 Player's
                        Quarto as played by Joseph Haines in a performance associated with Drury
                        Lane in January of 1675. So far as I know, there is no evidence of his
                        omission on the London stage during the seventeenth century (his omission in
                        an incomplete MS cast list of c. 1690-91 is inconclusive; see The London
                            Stage, I, 387).23. The Smock Alley Othello PB has been compared
                        throughout in matters of staging, cutting, additions, etc. with five
                        eighteenth-century acting versions and one from the early nineteenth
                        century, as well as with the Collier MS (see the Collations). Using Alfred
                        Hart's figure of 3,229 as the total number of lines in an uncut
                            Othello text (R.E.S., VIII [1932], 21), we may offer
                        the following rough estimates of comparative length: Smock Alley PB, 2,808
                        (cutting 421 lines); 1755 Witford edition (Covent Garden), 2,384 (cutting
                        845); John Palmer PB for 1766 (in a copy of the Hitch-Hawes 1761 edition),
                        2,363 (cutting 866); anonymous 1755 PB (in a copy of the Witford 1755
                        edition), 2,266 (cutting 963); 1764 Garland-Exshaw edition (Drury Lane),
                        2,315 (cutting 914); Bell's acting edition (Drury Lane, 1773), 2,429
                        (cutting 800); J. P. Kemble's acting edition (Covent Garden, 1804), 2,539
                        (cutting 690). Occasional references are made to a 1770 acting edition with
                        Drury Lane and Covent Garden casts for 65 and to the R. Butters edition (c.
                        1788; Covent Garden). The Collier MS (in a copy of the Second Folio, 1632)
                        suggests cutting only about 293 lines in all, 83 of these falling in the
                        central missing section of the Smock Alley PB.24. Rosenberg leaves the impression that Rymer's criticism of
                            Othello might have had some direct influence on the cutting in
                        the Smock Alley PB. Considering the date of the Smock Alley PB (not later
                        than 1684-85) and the date of Rymer's critique in A Short View of
                            Tragedy (1692), any such direct influence seems impossible. See
                        also an earlier article by Rosenberg on Othello on the
                        eighteenth-century stage in SP, LI (1954), 75-94.25. The last part of line 357 (`Othello's Occupation's
                        gone.') is wrongly included as part of the cut by Rosenberg.26. These cuts, which more or less follow the Q1 text (1622),
                        may, of course represent an earlier stage tradition and thus indicate no
                        necessary connection with Q1. The scene is even more heavily cut in the
                        eighteenth-century acting texts and Kemble (see Collations).27. In V.i the last three lines (34-36) are marked for cutting,
                        mainly, I suggest, because of textual difficulties (particularly in
                        F3).28. See notes 16 and 26.29. See the list of Smock Alley stage settings in Vol. I, Part i,
                        of this series (pp. 23-24). The recent discovery of parts of the Smock Alley
                            I Henry IV and II Henry IV (see note 2) makes it
                        possible to add three scenes to the above list: I Henry IV,
                        `chamber of State' (I.i. [replaced]); `Stable' (II.i); `Camp' (IV.i, iii;
                        also II Henry IV, IV.i).30. Compare `Chamber without ye Bed' in Smock Alley Merry
                            Wives, I.iv, and Smock Alley Hamlet, II.i.  </field><field name="file_s">ShaOthP</field></doc></add>