<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><add><doc><field name="id">d1e2</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">header</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 2 (Padua Winter's Tale) </field><field name="fulltext_t">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 2 (Padua Winter's Tale) [a
     machine-readable transcription] Shakespeare, William Creation of machine-readable version: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center Creation of digital images: Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. 25 kilobytes University of Virginia Library. Charlottesville, Va. Bibliographic Society, ShaWinP Publicly-accessible URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/bsuva/promptbook/ 1997 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century. The electronic text contains the Introduction and the Collations. The prompt-book is
     rendered as page images. Images of the manuscript have been included from volume 2, part 2. Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 2 (Padua Winter's Tale) William Shakespeare Editor G. Blakemore Evans Issued in portfolios. The prompt-books are reproduced in collotype facsimile. University Press of Virginia Charlottesville, VA 1963 Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PR 2757 .E9 1960 v.2 Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century Published for the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia The production of this volume was supervised by Fredson Bowers.  Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. All quotation marks retained as data. All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has
     been joined to the preceding line. The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and
     thumbnail GIFs. Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing
     analytical groupings. Library of Congress Subject Headings  1960-1963 English drama; prose LCSH 24-bit color; 400 dpi  July 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Corrected transcription errors. March 1997 corrector Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center Added TEI header and tags. </field><field name="file_s">ShaWinP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e140</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">front</field><field name="title_s">Shakespearean prompt-books of the seventeenth century, vol. 2 (Padua Winter's Tale) </field><field name="fulltext_t">Image of the spine, vol. 2Image of the cover, vol. 2 part 1Image of the title page, vol. 2 part 1Image of the cover, vol. 2 part 2Image of the title page, vol. 2 part 2  SHAKESPEAREAN PROMPT BOOKS of the SEVENTEENTH CENTURY  Vol. II: Part i  Introductions to the Padua Measure for MeasureThe Winter's Tale Collations Edited by G. Blakemore Evans  Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia  Charlottesville,
     Virginia  1963  EDITORIAL ADVISORY COMMITTEE  The Bibliographical Society of the
     University of Virginia  ARTHUR F. STOCKER, Chairman FREDSON BOWERS  JOHN COOK WYLLIE  The production of this volume was supervised
     by Fredson Bowers.  ContentsIntroduction to Measure for MeasureMeasure for Measure: CollationsIntroduction to The Winter's TaleThe Winter's Tale: Collations</field><field name="file_s">ShaWinP</field></doc><doc><field name="id">d1e229</field><field name="slug_s">/bsuva/promptbook/</field><field name="project_s">Shakespearean Prompt-Books</field><field name="section_s">introduction</field><field name="title_s">IntroductionThe Winter's Tale: Padua First Folio</field><field name="fulltext_t">IntroductionThe Winter's Tale: Padua First Folio THE association of the prompt-book of The Winter's Tale with the Padua
      Macbeth and Measure for Measure, aside from the fact that it is part of the
     same University of Padua First Folio, rests on the initials `T S.' found three times in this
     prompt-book and once in Macbeth. In Macbeth `T S' plays the role of the
     Doctor in IV.iii; in Winter's Tale he plays a Servant in III.ii and V.i and apparently
     a 'Lord' in V.i. 178 (though it is possible that his second appearance in V.i is as a Servant
     again). In the General Introduction I identified `T S' as a certain `Tho: Slender' who had
     performed in Sir Edward Dering's private production of The Spanish Curate about 1624,
     and on the basis of these initials and other similar evidence I suggested further that the
     Padua prompt-books should be assigned to Sir Edward Dering and his group of amateurs.[1] The prompt-hand that is common to the Padua Macbeth and Measure for Measure
     does not appear in The Winter's Tale. The prompt-hand in The Winter's Tale
     (and I can detect only a single hand at work) is of a more markedly secretary cast than that in
     the other two plays and its spelling forms are noticeably more archaic. Moreover, the owner of
     this hand employs advance calls for his entering characters and some other anticipative
     notations, a characteristic which at once distinguishes him from the reviser-prompter in the
     other two  Padua prompt-books. This use of advance calls
     would seem to suggest a later date for The Winter's Tale prompt-book, but, as I have
     noticed in the General Introduction,[2] such a system of advance calls
     was coming into fashion around 1625-31 and might well be found in a prompt-book contemporary
     with ones still using the older system. One particular prompt-notation also suggests a
     pre-Restoration date: the prompter's addition of the direction `fflurrish' at five (probably
     six) places in the text (all non-anticipative) where there is nothing in the Folio to suggest
     such a direction.[3] So far as I know, Restoration prompters rarely
     used the term `flourish'; where they noted such calls they more generally employed some form
     like 'Trumpet sounds' (Smock Alley Othello, IV.i.225) or `So&lt;u&gt;nd here' (Smock
     Alley Hamlet, I.iv.6), the sounding being prepared for by an advance call `Trumpet
      ready'.[4] The Padua Winter's Tale was probably never completed for production. Although the
     calls for characters are carried through the whole play, the cutting of the play stops with Act
     I, Scene ii; a fate similar to that which later overtook the Smock Alley Winter's
     Tale. Such a state of affairs, however, reverses the usual procedure, cutting (at least a
     preliminary cutting) being ordinarily completed before the character calls or other
     prompt-notations were inserted. Another unusual feature is the assignment to a particular actor
     (`T S.') of two small roles at this very early stage in the preparation of the prompt-book.  The prompter is quite erratic in his use of advance calls for the characters, some calls
     being thirty lines ahead, some as little as seven or eight lines. His `Act' calls are also
     erratic, one  (for Act III) not being anticipative at all
     (see the Collations). Apart from the character and act calls, with one exception, the notations
     are non-anticipative. The exception is the advance call for the `Satire Dance' at
     IV.iv.339-341, a call which is repeated at the point where the dance occurs. The prompter makes
     no attempt to mark point of entry for his characters when they are called within a scene, and,
     as usual, there are no calls for characters at the beginning of an act. In general, the
     prompter deals accurately enough with the frequent massed entries found in the Folio text (see,
     however, I.ii.204 and III.ii.4-6).  Because the Padua Winter's Tale prompt-book represents an unfinished cutting of the
     play, one which could never have reached production, only two pages have been reproduced in
     facsimile: sigs. [2B6]v (p. 300), 2C1r (p. 301). The
     collation, however, records, as usual, all the prompt-calls, notations, etc. for the play as a
     whole.  No full acting text of The Winter's Tale is available before Thomas Hull's Covent
     Garden version which appeared in Bell's Shakespeare, Vol. V (1773).[5] I have used this and J. P. Kemble's Drury Lane version (1802) for comparison with
     the Padua prompt-book. I have also compared where possible the Smock Alley (unfinished)
     prompt-book (c. 1670-85) and the cuts in the Collier-Perkins Second Folio. 1. Shakespearean Prompt-Books of the Seventeenth Century, Vol. I, Part i
     (1960), pp. 8-9. 2. Ibid., p. 7. 3. Compare the frequent additions of `fflorish' in the prompt-book of Lodge's and
     Greene's Looking Glasse for London and England, which dates from c. 1625 (see C. R.
     Baskerville, "A Prompt Copy of A Looking Glass for London and England," MP
     [1932-33] XXX, 37-46). Like the Padua prompt-books, this propmt-book is a printed copy with
     manuscript prompters' notations. 4. The only Restoration examples I know of are to be found (a) in a prompt-book of
     Dryden's Tyrannic Love (after 1672), perhaps belonging to the King's Company (see H.
     H. Adams, "A Prompt Copy of Dryden's Tyrannic Love," Studies in Bibliography
     [1951-52], IV, 170-174); and (b) in a single notation in the Smock Alley Macbeth
     (before 1682) at I. iii. 135. 5. The other eighteenth-century versions of The Winter's Tale deal
     essentially with the Florizel-Perdita part only, although Garrick included the restoration of
     Hermione (see C. B. Hogan, Shakespeare in the Theatre, 1701-1800, II [1957],
     674-676).  &lt;/page&gt;   &lt;page n=25&gt; </field><field name="file_s">ShaWinP</field></doc></add>